<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Living loves betwixt Christ and dying Christians A sermon preached at M. Magdalene Bermondsey in Southwark, near London, June 6. 1654. At the funeral of that faithful servant of Christ Mr. Jeremiah Whitaker, Minister of the Gospel, and pastor of the church there. With a narative of his exemplarily holy life and death. By Simeon Ashe, his much endeared friend and brother. Together with poems and elegies on his death, by divers ministers in the city of London.</title>
            <author>Ashe, Simeon, d. 1662.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1654</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 227 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 46 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A75710</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A3961A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R223578</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99896718</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99896718</idno>
            <idno type="VID">133592</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A75710)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 133592)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2433:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Living loves betwixt Christ and dying Christians A sermon preached at M. Magdalene Bermondsey in Southwark, near London, June 6. 1654. At the funeral of that faithful servant of Christ Mr. Jeremiah Whitaker, Minister of the Gospel, and pastor of the church there. With a narative of his exemplarily holy life and death. By Simeon Ashe, his much endeared friend and brother. Together with poems and elegies on his death, by divers ministers in the city of London.</title>
                  <author>Ashe, Simeon, d. 1662.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 80 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by T.M. for Ralph Smith, at the Bible in Cornhil, near the Royal Exchange,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1654.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Whittaker, Jeremiah, 1599-1654 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Funeral sermons --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:133592:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:133592:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:133592:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:133592:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>LIVING LOVES BETWIXT CHRIST AND DYING CHRISTIANS. A SERMON <hi>Preached</hi> At <hi>M. Magdalene Bermondſey</hi> in <hi>Southwark,</hi> near <hi>London, June</hi> 6. 1654. At the Funeral of that faithful Servant of Chriſt Mr. <hi>Jeremiah Whitaker,</hi> Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of the Goſpel, and Paſtor of the Church there.</p>
            <p>With a Narative of his Exemplarily holy Life and Death.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> SIMEON ASHE, <hi>his much endeared Friend and Brother.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Together with POEMS and ELEGIES on his Death, by divers Miniſters in the City of LONDON.</p>
            <q>
               <hi>The Righteous periſh and no man layeth it to heart, and merciful men are taken away, none conſidering that the righteous is taken away from the evil to come. He ſhall enter into Peace, they ſhall reſt in their beds, each one walking in his uprightneſs.</hi> 
               <bibl>Iſai. 57. 1, 2</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>T. M.</hi> for <hi>Ralph Smith,</hi> at the Bible in Cornhil, near the Royal Exchange. 1654.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:133592:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:133592:3"/>
            <head>The Licencer's Epiſtle to the READER.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is reported in the life of</hi> Ambroſe, <hi>that when he</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ambroſii</hi> vitâ per <hi>Paulinum</hi> ſcriptâ, flebat amariſſimè quotieſcunque fortè nuntia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum illi fuerat de cujuſcun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſancti obitu ſacerdotis, &amp;c. Iſa. 57. 1.</note> 
               <hi>heard of the death of any holy Miniſters, he would weep very bitterly. The like I read of</hi> Philo, <hi>that when he came into any Town or Village, and heard of the death of any good man there dwelling, he would mourn ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly, becau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e of the great loſſe that place and the whole Church of Chriſt had received thereby. How much more cauſe have we of this age to lament our condition, who have in few years loſt ſo many precious Saints, and ſo many Reverend, Learned, and godly Miniſters; Surely this ſad providence of God ſpeaks with a loud voice, that miſeries and calamities are haſting upon this Nation.</hi> For the righteous periſh (<hi>ſaith the Prophet</hi>) and no man layeth it to heart, and merciful men are taken away, none conſidering that the righteous is taken away from the evil to come. <hi>Thus</hi> Auſtin <hi>died a little before</hi> Hippo (<hi>wherin he dwelt) was taken. And</hi> Paraeus, <hi>before</hi> Heil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derbergh <hi>was ſacked. And</hi> Luther <hi>immediately before</hi> Germa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <hi>was overrun with wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and bloodſhed<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Mr. <hi>Scuddar.</hi> Mr. <hi>Greſl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> Mr. <hi>Ferrihj.</hi> Mr. <hi>Ludlam.</hi> Mr. <hi>Nat. Ward.</hi> Dr. <hi>Gouge.</hi> Dr. <hi>Hill.</hi> Mr. <hi>Walker.</hi> Mr. <hi>Conaut.</hi> Mr. <hi>Wilſon.</hi> Mr. <hi>Paramoor.</hi> Mr. <hi>Gataker.</hi> &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>And now of late years many eminent Lights have been extinguiſhed in this Nation, to fore ſignifie the great darkneſſe that is coming upon us. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt which, I cannot but reckon my revere<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d brother Mr.</hi> Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remiah<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Whitaker, <hi>at whoſe Funeral this enſuing Sermon was preached. If I ſhould enter upon his commendation, I might tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſay what</hi> Nazianzene <hi>doth of his ſister</hi> Gorgonia, <hi>That I have more cauſe to fear leaſt I ſhould ſpeak</hi> below, <hi>then a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove the Truth; for he was a</hi> burning <hi>and a</hi> ſhining <hi>light in this our</hi> Iſrael; <hi>a</hi> Meſſenger <hi>and an</hi> Interpreter, <hi>one among
<pb facs="tcp:133592:4"/> a thouſand; a</hi> Bezaleel <hi>in Gods Tabernacle, a true</hi> Nathanael, <hi>that by his integrity, humility, conſtancy, charity, publickneſſe, and peaceableneſſe of ſpirit, and by his diligence and faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in preaching the Goſpel, made his life both amiable and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirable. He was (yet not he, but the grace of God with him</hi>) <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.<note place="margin">Naz. Oratio Funebris in laudem Patris ſui, &amp;c. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>And though I will not ſay what</hi> Nazianzene <hi>ſaith of</hi> Athanaſius, that to commend him, were to commend Vertue, becauſe all Vertues were contracted in him; <hi>yet this I will ſay (which is alſo ſaid of</hi> Athanaſius, <hi>That he was) <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, An</hi> Adamant <hi>and a</hi> Load-ſtone. <hi>To all that converſed with him he was as a</hi> Load-ſtone <hi>to draw their hearts to love him: but in the cauſe of God, &amp; in reference to the truths of Chriſt he is as an</hi> uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querable Adamant. <hi>He was a</hi> Jeremiah <hi>both in mourning for and witneſſing against the ſins of the times. He was a ſecond</hi> Whitaker, <hi>though not ſo eminent in learning as to be (what is</hi>
               <note place="margin">In vita <hi>D. Whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takeri</hi> Oratio Funebris.</note> 
               <hi>ſaid of him</hi>) Mundi miraculum, Academiae oraculum; <hi>yet he was (which is alſo ſaid of him</hi>) ſound in the faith, <hi>one that had no private opinion, that did not</hi> in veteri viâ novam ſemitam quaerere, <hi>ſeek out new pathes of his own, but kept the old way and the old path,</hi> That had a great wit without any mixture of madneſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>It is very diſputable to me, whether he preached more by the heavenlyneſſe of his Doctrine, or by the holineſſe of his life. Sure I am, he had this peculiar diſpenſation, That he preached as ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually by his death, as by his life or Doctrine. For the manner of his ſickneſſe and death speaketh to all that ſaw it, or ſhall now know it by reading this Sermon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>That the</hi> beſt of men <hi>are ſubject to the worst of</hi> Diſeaſes: That all things come alike to all, that no man knoweth love or hatred by all that is before him.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>That though the Lord cauſe his chlldren to paſſe through the</hi> waters <hi>and through the</hi> fire, <hi>yet he</hi> will be with them, <hi>ſo as the</hi> waters <hi>ſhall not</hi> overflow <hi>them, nor the</hi> fire <hi>burn them.
<pb facs="tcp:133592:4"/> Though they are</hi> troubled on every ſide, <hi>yet they are not</hi> di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſed; <hi>though</hi> perplexed, <hi>yet not in</hi> deſpair, <hi>though</hi> perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, <hi>yet not</hi> forſaken; <hi>though</hi> caſt down, <hi>yet not</hi> deſtroyed. <hi>For ſo great was the patience that God meaſured out to this our</hi> dear Brother, <hi>that though he</hi> groaned, <hi>yet he never</hi> grumbled; <hi>though he often</hi> mourned, <hi>yet he never</hi> murmured; <hi>nay, though he often</hi> roared <hi>by reaſon of the greatneſſe of his pain, yet he al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways</hi> juſtified <hi>and</hi> magnified God; <hi>and this he did ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly, and in ſuch a degree and proportion, that as it is ſaid of</hi> Job, <hi>ſo it will be ſaid by the Saints that ſucceed us, for their mutual conſolation and encouragement;</hi> Ye have heard of the patience of <hi>Whitaker: He had an</hi> ulcerated fleſh, <hi>but a</hi> ſound <hi>and</hi> whole ſpirit, <hi>and that made him bear his infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity; he had a</hi> ſtone <hi>in the bladder, but a very</hi> tender <hi>and ſoft</hi> heart; <hi>he had a body</hi> gangren'd, <hi>but a ſoul</hi> unbelepred <hi>with ſin. I heard him often ſay with thankfulneſſe, That under all his bodily ſufferings, he had a bleſſed calmneſſe, and quietneſſe in his ſpirit; that</hi> God <hi>ſpake peace; that though he</hi> roared <hi>for pain, yet the devil was chained up from</hi> roaring <hi>upon him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>It was no ſmall delight to me to behold the tears that were ſhed at his Funeral. Not that I was glad that there was ſuch cauſe of ſorrow, but to ſee (in theſe dayes, eſpecially wherein the godly Miniſtery is ſo much undervalued) a Miniſter that nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther lived</hi> undeſired, <hi>nor died</hi> unlamented: <hi>of whom it may be ſaid, as is of</hi> Stephen, That devout men carried <hi>Stephen</hi> to his burial, and made great lamentation over him. <hi>But I will not detein the Reader from beholding theſe things more largely related in the following Sermon, by one that was his</hi> fidus Achates, <hi>and as dear to him as</hi> Jonathan <hi>to</hi> David. <hi>The Lord ſanctifie this example to all that ſhall hear of it, and fit us his Miniſters that ſupervive, to preach and live as he did,</hi> To fight a good fight, to finiſh our courſe, and to keep the faith, that ſo we may at laſt obtaine a crown of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs which the righteous Judge will give at the laſt day to all that love his appearing.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>So prayeth Your ſervant in the work of the Miniſtery EDM. CALAMY.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:133592:5"/>
            <head>To the Right Honourable ELIZABETH, Counteſſe Dowager of <hi>Exeter.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MADAM,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Ow irreſiſtible is the power of love and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity? The holy Scriptures do plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully manifeſt, that divine love doth ſet Gods All (whether within or without him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf) on work for his childrens good, and that his childrens importunity hath in al A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges prevailed with his Omnipotency, to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare for their comfort: And multitudes of daily experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence do evidence the prevalency of theſe two Arguments among the ſons of men. My ſelf makes one inſtance for the verifying hereof, by preaching at Reverend, worthy Mr. <hi>Whitakers</hi> Funeral, and by printing my Sermon with the Narrative of his mem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rable life; both which come abroad with enlargements; becauſe ſtreights of time, and the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compoſedneſſe of my ſpirit through grief, would not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer me thus fully to dilate upon in the Pulpit. Madam, I am confident that your Ladyſhip can of your own knowledge, not only atteſt the truth of moſt paſſages in my Narrative, but adde alſo much more from your own obſervation, which will render his memory precious unto poſterity.</p>
            <p>And will your Honour give me leave to give ſome fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther account unto the world, wherefore I have preſumed to dedicate unto your Ladyſhip theſe expreſſions of my great reſpect to my precious much endeared brother Mr. <hi>Jeremiah Whitaker;</hi> Gratitude is at the bottom of this De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication. <hi>Madam,</hi> As I ſhall alwayes really acknowledg your Honours favour towards my worthleſſe ſelf; ſo I
<pb facs="tcp:133592:5"/> judg it meet to make known upon this occaſion that more then many thanks are moſt due unto your Ladyſhip from all Mr. <hi>Whitakers</hi> Relations, for your many and great te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonies of your conſtant reſpects unto him all his life long ſince your firſt acquaintance with him. I have often heard him mention before the Lord with praiſes and pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, your Honours abundant kindneſſes, both unto him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe and his family, which I beleeve are on record in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to be fully recompenſed in due time, becauſe they were the products of your ſincere love unto him, as the faithful Miniſter of Jeſus Chriſt. <hi>Madam,</hi> there are not many who be ſo deeply ſenſible as your ſel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e of the great loſſe ſuſtained by the death of this holy man of God: What mine own loſſe is, I had rather expreſſe it before the Lord, then publiſh it unto the world. He was (<hi>Madam</hi>) a faithful ſervant to your immortal ſoul, the wel are where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of God in mercy hath given you to mind much more then all matters ſublunary whatſoever. In reference hereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, he was your wiſe counſellour, in all your doubts and difficulties, your compaſſionate comforter; in all ſtraights and ſorrows, your vigilant Phyſician to prevent ſpiritual ſickneſſe and infection; your zealous Incourager in all wayes of holy ſervice, and a daily Remembrancer of you and yours before the Throne of Grace. Though theſe things ſpeak your loſſe, which may warrantably afflict your heart, yet I beſeech you (good Madam) conſider with comfort, that notwithſtanding this bucket be broken (as Dr. <hi>Preſton</hi> was wont to expreſſe it) nevertheleſs the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of light, life, grace, ſtrength, comfort and ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is ſtill at hand, ever full, and alwayes flowing. He who is now removed out of the Land of the living (to be ſerviceable by preaching, praying, conference no more) was only one of thoſe golden pipes through which the God of your mercies conveyed relief ſweetly and ſeaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably unto your ſoul: the <hi>wel-head</hi> is not removed, and many other choice conveyances of grace and conſolation from Chriſt be ſtill continued to you. Let this therefore be the language of your faith. The <hi>Lord liveth, and bleſſed be the
<pb facs="tcp:133592:6"/> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> my ſalvations,</hi> who will never forſake nor faile the ſoule which in humility and faithfulneſs doth depend upon his Majeſty. And (<hi>Madam</hi>) Mr. <hi>Whitaker</hi> his rich receipts of much ſanctifying grace, ſtrong confidence, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincible patience, undaunted courage, un-interrupted peace, with pure elevating joyes from the Lord may en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage the hopes of the pooreſt Chriſtians to expect great things from heaven, according to their neceſſities and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, becauſe God is no reſpecter of perſons, but free and liberal in the communications of his peculiar goodneſſe. Theſe are the words of his grace, <hi>Open thy mouth wide, and I will fill it,</hi> Pſal. 81. 10. <hi>If any man thirſt, let him come un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me and drink. He that beleeveth on me (as the Scripture hath ſaid) out of his belly ſhall flow rivers of living water,</hi> Joh. 7. 37, 38. The Almighty hath given you ſome taſtes of that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comparable fruit which comes from the Land of promiſe, that you may be encouraged to hold on in the way thither with cheerfulneſſe and perſeverance. <hi>Madam,</hi> It is no ſmall addition unto your honour here, and it will undoubted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly make to your happineſs hereafter, that you do own God in unwearied attendance upon his ſacred Ordinances, laying forth your ſelf for his name faithfully with that prudence, ſelf-denial, and plainneſs of heart where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with he hath adorned you, through his rich mercy in Jeſus Chriſt. <hi>Madam,</hi> I humbly beg pardon for this my bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and crave leave to ſubſcribe my ſelf</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>(Madam)</salute> 
               <signed>Your Honours humble Servant, SIMEON ASHE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:133592:6"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>JOHN 11. 11.</bibl>
               <q>Our friend <hi>Lazarus</hi> ſleepeth.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Heſe are the words of Chriſt concerning <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarus:</hi> and they ſpeak 1. His relation. 2. His diſſolution.</p>
            <p>Firſt, the relation was friendſhip, wherein we are to obſerve,</p>
            <p n="1">1. How far this friendſhip was extended, <hi>viz.</hi> both unto Chriſt, and to his Diſciples, <hi>our friend.</hi> It is not my friend, or your friend, but <hi>our friend,</hi> both yours and mine.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That this friendſhip was acknowledged by Chriſt himſelfe, not only while <hi>Lazarus</hi> was yet alive, but even now when he was dead, <hi>Our friend Lazarus ſleepeth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the ſecond part of the Text (<hi>viz. Lazarus</hi>'s diſſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) we may note</p>
            <p n="1">1. The truth aſſerted (<hi>viz.</hi>) that <hi>Lazarus</hi> though a friend both to Chriſt and to his Diſciples, yet he was dead.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Metaphor whereby it is expreſſed, which is taken from natural ſleep. He ſleepeth.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The notice which our Saviour took of <hi>Lazarus</hi> his deceaſe. This he reporteth unto his Diſciples, he ſaith un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>Our friend Lazarus ſleepeth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus from this plaine diviſion of the Text, I proceed unto the obſervations which do from hence offer them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves naturally unto our conſideration. And the doctrines will be ſix in number, <hi>viz.</hi> three from each part, into which the Text hath been divided.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:133592:7"/>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctr. </seg>1</label> The firſt is this, <hi>viz. That there is a mutual friendſhip be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt Chriſt and true Chriſtians.</hi> Our Lord himſelf here cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth <hi>Lazarus friend.</hi> And that this friendſhip was mutual, it is evident from this hiſtory.</p>
            <p>Firſt, the love of <hi>Lazarus</hi> towards the Lord Jeſus was witneſſed by the many entertainments and hearty wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes which he received at his houſe. And the friendſhip of Chriſt unto <hi>Lazarus</hi> is atteſted by his ſiſters, former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>He whom thou lovest is ſick,</hi> ver. 3. and by this our E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vangeliſt; <hi>Jeſus</hi> loved <hi>Martha,</hi> and her ſiſter and <hi>Laza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus, ver.</hi> 5. And the <hi>Jews</hi> ſaid, <hi>Behold how he loved him. ver.</hi> 36. yea our Saviour himſelf in the Text calleth him <hi>friend.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now as it was betwixt Chriſt and <hi>Lazarus,</hi> ſo is it like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe betwixt Chriſt and all real Chriſtians; their friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip is mutual. The word <hi>friend</hi> expreſſeth love, and this love hath its viciſſitude amongſt friends. As tenniſe balls with rackets are banded and returned to and fro, ſo love amongſt cordial friends hath its intercourſe, it is received<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>amicus, qui amat, vel qui amatur.</hi> Steph. Theſau. Joh. 15. 13. John 15. 14.</note> with acceptance, and returned with requitals. <hi>Greater love has no man then this, that a man lay down his life for his friends.</hi> This expreſſeth Chriſt his love to his Chriſtian friends. <hi>Ye are my friends, if ye do whatſoever I command you.</hi> This ſpeaketh the love and friendſhip of Chriſtians to Chriſt. And you muſt know that this affection of love was not only betwixt Chriſt and ſome peculiar Chriſtians, to Chriſt, as his Diſciples and <hi>Lazarus;</hi> but betwixt him and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſound-hearted Chriſtians alſo. When he preached to a very <hi>great multitude of people,</hi> having warned them to take heed of hypocriſie, he uſeth this compellation, <hi>I ſay unto you</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 12. 1, 5.</note> 
               <hi>my friends.</hi> And long before his incarnation, this was the language of Chriſt (the eſſential Wiſdome of the Father,) <hi>I love them that love me.</hi> Whereas it is ſometimes ſaid of<note place="margin">Prov. 8. 17.</note> our friends, that they have onely one ſoule in ſeveral bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> it is moſt true, being applyed unto Chriſt and ſingle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearted Chriſtians. <hi>The Spirit of God dwelleth in them; and</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Anima eſt, non ubi animat, ſed ubi amat.</hi> Rom. 8. 9.</note> 
               <hi>if any man hath not the Spirit of Chriſt, he is none of his.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As friends, being, in point of friendſhip, acted by the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:133592:7"/> ſame principles, they will and nill the ſame things: So<note place="margin">Eadem velle &amp; nolle est firma amicitia.</note> it is with Jeſus Chriſt and thoſe who are unfained friends unto him. As the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> thus adviſed the <hi>Philippians,</hi> Let <hi>the ſame mind be in you that was in Chriſt;</hi> ſo<note place="margin">Phil. 2. 5. 1 Cor. 2. 16.</note> he affirmeth of the Saints at <hi>Corinth,</hi> that <hi>they had the mind of Christ.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The obligations of love are ſo ſtrong upon friends, that they can heartily ſay one to another, <hi>I am as thou art.</hi> The<note place="margin">2 Chr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n. 18. 3. Eſay 41 8.</note> Lord accounted <hi>Abraham his friend,</hi> and it is conſiderable how God and <hi>Abraham</hi> being friends did communicate themſelves, with their All unto each other.</p>
            <p>As God by way of Covenant promiſeth to be an <hi>al-ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 17. 1. Chap. 11. 3.</note> portion unto him, to <hi>bleſſe thoſe who bleſſe him, and to curſe ſuch who curſe him,</hi> and to beſtow <hi>Canaan</hi> (the land<note place="margin">2 Chron. 20. 9.</note> flowing with milk and hony) <hi>upon him:</hi> ſo <hi>Abraham</hi> gave up himſelfe wholly to be at Gods diſpoſing, in regard of his habitation, to <hi>dwell where</hi> his Majeſty would ſettle him;<note place="margin">Gen. 12. 1, 5.</note> and in reſpect of his relations, to <hi>command his children and his houſhold after him to keep the way of the Lord, to do juſtice</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 18. 19.</note> 
               <hi>and judgement.</hi> In this manner Chriſt and believers, they are for each others, with their All, even as for themſelves. <hi>I</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cant. 2. 16.</note> 
               <hi>am my beloveds</hi> (ſaith the loving, beloved Spouſe) <hi>and my beloved is mine.</hi> They are the ſame 1. In their wills. As they in things moſt difficult and croſſe to themſelves (in ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance) do ſay, <hi>The will of the Lord be done;</hi> So Chriſt is<note place="margin">Acts 21. 14.</note> ready to ſpeak unto them in reference to the regular mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of their wills, as once to the woman of <hi>Canaan, Be it</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 15. 28.</note> 
               <hi>unto thee even as thou wilt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>2. In their <hi>deſires.</hi> As theſe are their breathings; <hi>there is</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 73. 25. Cant. 7. 16.</note> 
               <hi>none upon earth that I deſire beſides thee;</hi> So his <hi>deſires are towards them.</hi> Not long before his departure from his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, to evidence his deſires of ſpiritual fellowſhip with<note place="margin">Luke 22 15. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> them, <hi>He ſaid unto them, with deſire I have deſired to eat this Paſſeover with you before I ſuffer<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>3 And in their <hi>deſigns.</hi> As this is in their eyes and aimes,<note place="margin">Phil. 1. 20.</note> that whether <hi>by life or death Christ may be magnified in them:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jer. 32. 40, 41.</note> So he <hi>will never turn from them to do them good, but will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce over them to do them good.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:133592:8"/>
            <p>Theſe are brief hints in reference to the doctrine, more generally conſidered. In the more diſtinct handling of it, both the branches are to be taken apart, and particularly to be diſcourſed upon.</p>
            <p>And here give me leave to premiſe the reaſons where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I ſhall diſcourſe of this mutual friendſhip under the notion of love, in a latitude: <hi>viz.</hi> becauſe, 1. The word <hi>Friend</hi> (as we already hinted) ſpeaketh <hi>love.</hi> 2. In this Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory theſe phraſes ſignifie the ſame thing; <hi>viz. friend La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarus,</hi> and <hi>Lazarus loved.</hi> 3. And the holy Ghoſt elſewhere uſeth theſe words indifferently, <hi>viz. friend, belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The firſt branch of the doctrine is this, That real right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred<note place="margin">Branch 1.</note> Chriſtians are friends unto Chriſt His endeared Spouſe ſpeaketh this openly; <hi>This is my beloved, and this is my</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cant 5. 16.</note> 
               <hi>friend, O Daughters of Jeruſalem.</hi> Anſwerable whereunto is the language of the Goſpel-Prophet, <hi>a ſong of my beloved</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſay 5<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 1.</note> 
               <hi>to his vineyard.</hi> Let it be noted that Chriſt is not looked up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and loved as an ordinary friend, but as a friend extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary, either a friend already married, or one affected ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gularly with expectations of marriage. <hi>The virgins love</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cant. 1. 3.</note> 
               <hi>thee.</hi> And indeed, none do love Chriſt ſincerely, who do not love him ſingularly, ſuperlatively. Let his own words be well weighed; <hi>He that loveth father or mother more then</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth. 10. 37. <hi>Certè: illi non a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Chriſtum, qui aliquid plus quàm Chriſtum amant.</hi> Aug.</note> 
               <hi>me, is not worthy of me; and he that loveth ſon or daughter more then me is not worthy of me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This aſſertion is bottomed upon good reaſon, becauſe Chriſt both in his own perſonal excellencies, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated advantages, is infinitely better then any crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture with its faireſt amiabilities whatſoever.</p>
            <p>Now this their love is not blinde, but it <hi>aboundeth in all judgement and knowledge,</hi> as will be manifeſt by theſe foure<note place="margin">Phil. 1. 9.</note> reaſons following.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>1</label> Becauſe of his incomparable, unparallelled beauties. This account his dear Spouſe giveth of her ſtrong infla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med affections; <hi>My beloved is white and ruddy, the chiefeſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cant. 5. 10.</note> 
               <hi>ten thouſand. His head is as the moſt fine gold.</hi> And ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving metaphorically commended him from the head to
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:133592:8"/> the foot, ſhe thus concludeth, <hi>This is my beloved, and this is</hi>
               <note place="margin">verſ. 19.</note> 
               <hi>my friend.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>His graces which are like to a moſt fragrant perfume, do in am our the hearts of all them who are truly ſpiritual. <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the ſavour of thy good ointments, thy Name is as an</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cant. 1. 3.</note> 
               <hi>ointment powred forth, therefore do the Virgins love thee.</hi> And in the ſong of conjugal loves, this is rendred as the reaſon of thoſe ſparklings, <hi>Thou art fairer then the children of</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 45. 2.</note> 
               <hi>men. As there was not among the children of Iſrael a goodlier perſon then Saul (from the ſhoulders upwards he was higher</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Sam. 9. 2.</note> 
               <hi>then any of the people</hi>) So Jeſus Chriſt doth wonderfully o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver-top and exceed in all rich endowments, the moſt ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able creatures in the world. And as in all <hi>Iſrael there was</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Sam. 14. 25.</note> 
               <hi>none to be ſo much praiſed as Abſalom for his beauty (from the ſole of his foot even to the crown of his head there was no ble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh in him</hi>) and this might be ſome reaſon of <hi>Davids</hi> great love towards him:) So in the Lord Jeſus, there are per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect beauties without the leaſt blemiſhes: <hi>He is altogether lovely.</hi> No wonder therefore that wiſe, knowing Chriſtians do chuſe and value, and embrace him with vigorous loves.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>2</label> Becauſe of his famous, magnanimous undertakings and adventures as Mediator, that he might at once advance his Fathers glory, and the happineſſe of his Elect.</p>
            <p>We read that <hi>Jonathans ſoul was knit to the ſoul of David,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Sam. 18. 1.</note> 
               <hi>and that he loved him as his own ſoul,</hi> becauſe upon a Duel he had encountered and conquered the Monſter <hi>Goliah,</hi> who had blaſphemed God and vilified his people. Now this ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice was low and inconſiderable, being compared with Chriſts renowned exploits, who hand to hand combated with the devil in the wilderneſſe for the ſpace of <hi>fourty days,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke 4. 2. Col. 2. 15.</note> who <hi>ſpoiled principalities and Powers, made a ſhew of them o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penly, triumphing over them in his croſſe;</hi> Who did beare up bravely againſt the power of darkneſſe to be quell'd under the weight of divine juſtice to be ſatisfied, and under the flames of his Fathers diſpleaſure to be quenched. Theſe and the like rare actings of Chriſt being pondered by Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans do draw forth their hearts in friendſhip towards him.
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:133592:9"/> He himſelf ſaith, <hi>Therfore doth my Father love me, becauſe I</hi>
               <note place="margin">John 10. 17.</note> 
               <hi>lay down my life.</hi> And how can new-born Chriſtians, par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of the divine Nature, be otherwiſe affected upon the ſame account towards their bleſſed Maſter?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>3</label> Becauſe of their manifold rich receipts from Chriſt. <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vids</hi> heart giveth out loves to the Lord, becauſe upon his prayers he had delivered his <hi>eyes from tears, and his feet</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 116<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 1, 8.</note> 
               <hi>from falling.</hi> Now Chriſt hath reſcued his people from wrath to come, and that without reſpect to their requeſts, yea before they ſought him.</p>
            <p>Our Saviour himſelf giveth this as the reaſon where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the ſinful woman loved him, <hi>Many ſins are forgiven her,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk 7. 47. 1 Sam. 19. 5.</note> 
               <hi>therefore ſhe loved much.</hi> And <hi>Jonathan</hi> by this Argument laboureth to win <hi>Sauls</hi> heart towards <hi>David, Becauſe the Lord by him wrought a great ſalvation to all Iſrael.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In this reſpect the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> was rationally under the<note place="margin">2 Cor. 5. 14.</note> conſtraint of commanding Loves to Chriſt, becauſe of quickning grace received by his death.</p>
            <p>Now if I ſhould here diſcover our large enjoyments from Chriſt, it would abundantly appear to every inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuous ſoule, that there is ſufficient cauſe wherefore he ſhould be accounted and affected as an incomparable friend.</p>
            <p>By him we are delivered from ſin and hell (as is hinted e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven now) from the curſe of the Law, the hater of God, the<note place="margin">Gal<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 3. 13. Eph. 2. 14, 16. Gal. 1. 4. 1 Cor. 15. 55. Epheſ. 1. 3, 6. 1 Cor. 1. 30. and 2. 1, 20.</note> deadly ſnares of the world, and the poiſon-ſting of death. <hi>We are bleſſed with all ſpiritual bleſſings in heavenly places. We are accepted in the Beloved. He is made unto us Wiſdom, Righteouſneſſe, Sanctification and Redemption.</hi> And all the <hi>Promiſes of God are in him Yea, and in him Amen.</hi> How rationally therefore doth living love to Chriſt ſpring out of this root?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>4</label> Becauſe of their full expectations from him for the future, even unto ſoul-ſatisfaction, and that to eternity. Many chearing cordials are handed to Chriſtians from Chriſt here upon earth; in which regard he doth lie as a <hi>bundle of myrrh between their breſts;</hi> but he reſerveth the <hi>beſt wine</hi> for<note place="margin">Cant. 2. 13.</note> the laſt. Whatſoever for kind, or for meaſure the believing<note place="margin">John 2 10.</note>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:133592:9"/> Chriſtians comforts are here, yet to be with Chriſt in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven<note place="margin">Phil. 1. 13.</note> will be <hi>far better;</hi> and this, this in glory is looked for through Chriſt. This conſideration cauſeth their love un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Chriſt to break forth in a great flame. Let the words of the Apoſtle be weighed for the evidence hereof, who ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſpoken both of the <hi>Inheritance incorruptible, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>defiled,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Pet 1. 3, 4.</note> 
               <hi>that fadeth not away, reſerved in heaven,</hi> as alſo of the aſſured Perſeverance through <hi>Gods Power,</hi> and all this by <hi>Chriſt,</hi> he adds, <hi>Whom having not ſeen, yet ye love.</hi> Ingenu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous<note place="margin">1 Pet. 1. 8.</note> Chriſtians duly weighing the worth of their future happineſſe, dearly purchaſed by Chriſt, and undoubtedly to be poſſeſſed by them through Chriſt, do hereupon pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctically conclude, that nothing can be imagined more rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable then this, that they ſhould love him as their ſpecial friend.</p>
            <p>Thus from confirmation, I proceed to the Application of this Truth by way of Uſe; which I will propound un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der three heads; <hi>viz. 1. Information. 2. Examination 3. Exhortation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>1</label> Sad therefore is their condition who are not loving friends unto Jeſus Chriſt. For doubtleſſe though they be by profeſſion, &amp; in the eſtimation of others, true Chriſtians; yet they are but only <hi>Slips</hi> in Chriſtianity. As <hi>Judas,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Our Saviour ſpeaketh roundly unto ſuch: <hi>If God were</hi>
               <note place="margin">Joh. 8. 42.</note> 
               <hi>your Father, you would love me.</hi> And if God be not their Father, they are queſtionleſſe the devils children, children of the curſe. How open and expreſſe are the words of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle to this purpoſe? <hi>If any man love not the Lord Jeſus, let</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 16. 22.</note> 
               <hi>him be Anathema Maran-atha.</hi> The heavy and laſting ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledictions of God hang over the heads of all them who love not Chriſt. This is the great ſeverity of God againſt ſuch who are not friends unto Chriſt: and that the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe of his Majeſty herein may be manifeſted, I wiſh that this may be minded, <hi>viz.</hi> that unfriendlineſs to the Lord Jeſus in Goſpel-times (wherein his excellencies &amp; deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vings are ſo fully laid open) doth proceed either from 1. <hi>Infidelity.</hi> Or 2. <hi>Contumacy.</hi> Either people hearing from Scripture of Chriſts lovelineſs, do give <hi>God the lie to
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:133592:10"/> his face by not believing him,</hi> or elſe their diſregard of Chriſt ariſeth from malignity and ſtubbornneſſe of will, though they yield to the report of his incomparable worth. And<note place="margin">1 Joh. 5. 10. <hi>Non à c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>citate mentis, ſed à pravitatecordis.</hi> Aug.</note> both theſe are daring, and God-incenſing provocations.</p>
            <p>Now if any ſhall be awakened by theſe flaſhes of Gods anger, to enquire, Who are to be judged perſons void of love to Jeſus Chriſt? I ſhall referre them for ſatisfaction to Chriſts own <hi>words,</hi> both the parable, and his expoſition of it. The Parable is this, <hi>The Citizens hated him, and ſent a meſſage after him ſaying, We will not have this man to reigne</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke 19 14.</note> 
               <hi>over us.</hi> And the Application made is thus expreſſed, <hi>Thoſe mine enemies, which would not that I ſhould raigne over them, bring them hither and ſlay them before me.</hi> Therefore all ſuch<note place="margin">verſ. 27.</note> are proclaimed Chriſts enemies, Chriſt-haters, (even by Chriſt himſelf,) who refuſe to ſubmit unto him as their Lord and King.</p>
            <p>Its no uncharitableneſſe, but judgment according to the Word of truth, to determine thoſe to be no friends unto Chriſt, whoſe reſolutions are rather to order their lives ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to cuſtoms, humane traditions, their own humours, and the practices of the multitude, then according to the commands and counſels of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>2</label> It much concernes us all to examine our friendſhip unto Chriſt. To quicken this ſearch, theſe things are conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Becauſe many profeſſe much love outwardly, whoſe hearts affect him not unfainedly. As <hi>David</hi> deſcribeth ſome counterfeit Courtiers, whoſe <hi>words were ſoft like oyle, when there were drawn ſwords in their boſomes:</hi> Never was Chriſt more in mens mouths with ſmooth language then<note place="margin">Pſal. 55. 21.</note> now, when their lives ſpeak treachery againſt him. <hi>Thus Judas</hi> calleth him Maſter, and giveth him a kiſſe, yet was no friend. <hi>Have I not choſen twelve</hi> (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>and yet</hi>
               <note place="margin">John 6. 79.</note> 
               <hi>one is a devil?</hi> What Sugered words did the devil uſe, when he deſigned the ruine of <hi>Adam,</hi> and of all his poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity!</p>
            <p n="2">2. Becauſe the comforts of the Goſpel do appertain to
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:133592:10"/> them alone whoſe love is without diſſimulation. The Apoſtles benediction was this, <hi>Grace be with all them who</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eph. 6. 14.</note> 
               <hi>love our Lord Jeſus in ſincerity<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> The rich priviledges of grace are appropriated unto Chriſts cordial friend.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Becauſe Chriſt (whoſe <hi>eyes are like unto flames of</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rev. 1. 14.</note> 
               <hi>fire</hi>) doth diſcern clearly, all them that are falſe friends, though they pretend fair. We read of many <hi>who beleeved</hi>
               <note place="margin">John 2. 23, 24, 25.</note> 
               <hi>when they ſaw his miracles, but Jeſus did not commit himſelfe unto them, becauſe he knew all men, and needed not that any ſhould teſtifie of man; for he knew what was in man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Becauſe we cannot tell how ſoon we ſhall be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to the ſcrutiny. The Lord may be awakening our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, and ſetting them as upon a rack; propound that queſtion unto us, which he asked <hi>Peter</hi> once, and again, and the third time, <hi>Loveſt thou me?</hi> But though he ſhould<note place="margin">John 27. 15.</note> not deal thus with us in our life time, yet be ſure we ſhall be examined upon our departure hence, for after <hi>death</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 9 27.</note> 
               <hi>comes judgment</hi> infallibly. Therefore it will be our wiſdom in the ways of ſelf-renuing, to ſay as <hi>Job</hi> did, <hi>When God vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiteth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Job <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. 14.</note> 
               <hi>what ſhall I anſwer him?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. Becauſe by ſerious ſelf-reflections we may attaine ſuch full aſſurance of our love unto Chriſt, that we may with confidence ſpeak with <hi>Peter, Lord, thou knowest all</hi>
               <note place="margin">Joh. 21. 17.</note> 
               <hi>things, thou knowest that I love thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Having thus moved the examination of your love to Chriſt, I proceed to give in ſome diſcoveries of Chriſts loving friends; and the rather becauſe according to Gods inſtitution, we Miniſters are ſet up amongſt people to <hi>try</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jer. 6. 29.</note> 
               <hi>their wayes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And the characters of love being many, I ſhall be the ſhorter in them all. True it is, that mens love burning in their boſoms, they many times better expreſſe themſelves<note place="margin">Amor eſt inter ea quae melius ſentiuntur, qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> definiuntur.</note> by ſenſe then Arguments; yet God having in his word held forth manifold Signes of ſincere love, it is our duty to make our uſe of them.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Love to Chriſt is alwayes accompanied with hatred of ſinne. <hi>Ye that love the Lord, hate evil.</hi> And the Apoſtle<note place="margin">Pſal. 97. 10.</note>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:133592:11"/> his connexion is obſervable, <hi>Let love be without diſſimula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 12. 9.</note> 
               <hi>abhorring that which is evil:</hi> The ground here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is manifold. Firſt, becauſe Chriſt hateth all ſinne, he<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Quomodo amas Chriſtum, cùm adhuc amas quod in t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> odit Chriſtus</hi>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>Berr.</note> ſuffered death for ſinne, and is diſhonoured by it. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is not poſſible, that love unto Chriſt, and love un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſinne ſhould peaceably<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> lodge together in the ſame boſom.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Love to Chriſt is attended with care to prevent what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever might be injurious or diſpleaſing unto him. Thus the loving Spouſe layeth this command upon all under her Authority. <hi>I charge you that you awake not my Belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved till be pleaſe.</hi> In like manner <hi>Jonathans</hi> love pleadeth<note place="margin">Cant. 3.</note> with <hi>Saul</hi> for <hi>Davids</hi> life. <hi>Let not the King ſin againſt his ſervant, againſt</hi> David: <hi>wherefore wilt thou ſin againſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Sam. 19. 4, 5.</note> 
               <hi>blood, to ſlay</hi> David <hi>without a cauſe?</hi> And <hi>Jacobs</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 33.</note> affections did project the preſervation of his near relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from ruine. Hence it appeareth therefore, that peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of <hi>Gallio</hi> his temper, do not love Chriſt, who <hi>care not</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 18. 17.</note> what wrongs are done to Chriſt, in the liberty or puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of his Ordinances and comfort of his ſervants, if themſelves can ſleep warm in their own well-feathered neſts.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Love to Chriſt diſcovered it ſelf by ſolicitous enqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries after the minde of Chriſt, fearing leaſt through miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takes he might be provoked. How inquiſitive were his Apoſtles to know his pleaſure in all particulars, relating<note place="margin">Mat. 26. 17.</note> to the Paſſeover? <hi>The Diſciples came unto Jeſus, ſaying, Where wilt thou that we prepare for thee to eat the Paſſeover?</hi> And how t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>morous was <hi>Abraham</hi> (Gods friend) leſt he might<note place="margin">Cen. 18. <hi>Res eſt ſoliciti plena timo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>is amor.</hi>
               </note> by overmuch boldneſſe incenſe him, when he was media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting for <hi>Sodom!</hi> Shall they therefore be accounted friends to Chriſt who walk at all adventures, without any fears of his frown, or enquiries after his will?</p>
            <p n="4">4. Love cauſeth flowings forth of thoughts upon its object. The beatings of the pulſe are according to the heat in the heart. In the <hi>Song of Loves</hi> this is the firſt<note place="margin">Pſal. 45. 1.</note> clauſe, <hi>My heart is inditing of a good matter. I ſpeak of the things which I have made concerning the King.</hi> Sparks
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:133592:11"/> do not more naturally ariſe out of a flaming furnace, then muſings upon Chriſt from the ſoule which is fired with loves towards him. With how much intention, frequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy<note place="margin">Amor meus eſt pondus meum.</note> and ſteddineſſe do people think upon the perſons and things which are greatly loved! This conſideration therfore caſts them off as no friends to Chriſt, of whom it may be<note place="margin">Pſal. 10. 4.</note> truly ſaid, in reſpect of diligent meditation, <hi>The Lord is not in all their thoughts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. Longings after Chriſt, together with ſatisfactions while he is ab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ent, are evidences of love unto him. The<note place="margin">Cant. 3. &amp; 5. <hi>Amor currit p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r deſiderium.</hi> Aug.</note> loving Spouſe ſhakes off ſloth, gets out of bed in the night, and goeth <hi>abroad to ſeek him whom her ſoul loved</hi> Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther eaſe in a warm bed, nor chamber<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> comforts, nor Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty-contentments could ſatisfie her. Her Beloved ſhe muſt have, and her Beloved ſhe will have, for ſhe is ſick of love. Love like the Load-ſtone is attractive, and the needle touched with it, will unceſſantly move till it ſtand directly Northward. In like manner will the heart which is well warmed with love to Chriſt: this is its language, <hi>Whom have I in heaven but thee? and there is none that I deſire on earth</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 73. 25.</note> 
               <hi>beſides thee.</hi> Give me Chriſt, or I die.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Contentation in the enjoyment of Chriſt doth de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrate<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>quaſi</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>valdèacquieſco. Amor quieſcit per gaudium.</hi> Aug. <hi>Ad De<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m, apud qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m invenies ſummam tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quillitatem.</hi> Vatabl. in Pſ. 116. 7. Cant. 8. 5. Cant. 1. 13. Phil. 3. 3.</note> love: Some note this from the Greek word, which ſignifieth Love, <hi>viz.</hi> that wherein the heart taketh reſt. When any thing cometh to its centre<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> there it is quiet and ſtill: So it is with the heart which loveth God. This was <hi>Davids</hi> meaning, as ſome Expoſitors judge, when he having expreſſed his love to God, ſpeaketh thus in an holy Soliloquy, <hi>Return to thy reſt O my ſoul.</hi> This reſt the loving Chriſtian attaineth in Chriſt by complacency and dependency. The Spouſe <hi>leaneth</hi> (reſteth her ſelfe) <hi>upon her Beloved,</hi> and he for delight is <hi>a bundle of myrrhe between her breaſts:</hi> whereunto the words of the Apoſtle ſuit very well, <hi>We have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o confidence in the fleſh, but rejoyce in Chriſt Ieſus.</hi> For the ſoul which poſſeſſeth Chriſt, and knoweth what it hath, in having him, will ſay, I have enough, I have all, I need no more; for in him all wants are either ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied or ſanctified. In him juſtifying grace will make up
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:133592:12"/> all defects in ſervice. And what is wanting in the ſtreames of creature enjoyments, is given in with more ſweetneſſe in the full fountain of his Al-ſufficiency.</p>
            <p n="7">7. Communication of ſecrets ſpeaketh friendſhip. <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſther 5. 10. &amp; 6. 13.</note> doth unboſome himſelf to his friends, by laying open unto them all his concernments, both croſſe and comfort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able. And Chriſt bids him who was diſpoſſeſſed of a devil, <hi>Go home to thy friends, and tell them how great things God hath</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mark 5. 19.</note> 
               <hi>done for thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We can put that into a friends boſom which we would not have blazed abroad in the world. Thus Chriſts friends do tell him of all their troubles, fears, wants, tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptations, luſts, as alſo of their comforts, receipts, experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences; upon all occaſions they ſtep unto him, and he knoweth from them by prayer how things go with<note place="margin">1 Sam. 1. 15. Pſal. 103. 4.</note> them, whether by encouragement or diſcouragement in their courſe.</p>
            <p>I here remember the ſpeech of <hi>Sampſons</hi> wife, when he concealed what ſhe deſired to know, <hi>How canſt thou ſay, I love thee, when thy heart is not with me?</hi> And doubtleſs<note place="margin">Judges 16<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 15.</note> our eſtrangement from Chriſt, in not laying open our ſelves upon all occaſions before him, doth more then intimate our unfriendlineſs.</p>
            <p n="8">8. Readineſſe to comply with Chriſts command will undeniably prove that we are his friends. Our Lord is often upon this Argument: <hi>You are my friends if you do whatſoever I command you, He that hath my Commandments</hi>
               <note place="margin">John 15. 15. &amp; 14. 21, 23. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, or <hi>ab</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>and keepeth them, he it is that loveth me. If any man love me, he will keep my words.</hi> Thus <hi>Abraham</hi> made it manifeſt that he was Gods friend, by being ready to offer up <hi>Iſaac</hi> upon his call. And the Apoſtle ſpeaketh of the <hi>labour of love,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe love will not withdrw from any work, wherein God ſeeth cauſe to imploy his friends. The woman who<note place="margin">Heb. 9. 10.</note> loved Chriſt much, will <hi>waſh his feet, and wipe them with the haire of her head.</hi> This is the language of Love, I<note place="margin">Luke 7. 38.</note> account no work too mean, wherein I<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> may ſerve Chriſt.</p>
            <p n="9">9. Love is content to be at any coſt for Chriſt. Heark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:133592:12"/> unto the expreſſions of the loving Spouſe, <hi>At our gates</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cant. 7. 13.</note> 
               <hi>are all manner of pleaſant fruits, new and old, which I have laid up for thee, O my beloved. And I would cauſe thee to</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cant. 8. 2.</note> 
               <hi>drink of ſpiced wine, and of the juyce of Pomgranates.</hi> The beſt of all kinds, and the beſt of the beſt is provided for Chriſt, if he be Beloved. She who loved much, brought <hi>a Box of oyntment very coſtly.</hi> In like manner, whatever<note place="margin">Luke 7. 37. with John 12. 1 2 Sam. 24. 24.</note> duties Chriſts friends diſcharge, or whatever Ordinances they frequent, they are wont to ſay with <hi>David, I will not offer to the Lord that which coſts me nothing.</hi> They ſcorn to give him the chaff and bran, when others eat the Kid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neys of wheat. To be warm and vigorous in creature communion, and <hi>all a-mort,</hi> chil and cold converſing with Chriſt, is an abomination to Chriſts friends.</p>
            <p n="10">10. Love is liberal and free, not grudging any kindneſs laid forth for a friend. <hi>This is the love of God,</hi> (ſaith the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved<note place="margin">1 John 5. 3.</note> Diſciple) <hi>that we keep his Commandments, and his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments are not grievous.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When the moſt is done and endured for Chriſt, the ſoul ſaith, How little have I either acted or ſuffered for Chriſt? Oh that it had been more, Oh that it had been more! How little is all my ſervice, how ſmall are all my disburſments for Chriſt? When <hi>Iacob</hi> had paſſed two Apprentiſhips for <hi>Rachel,</hi> under a ſowre Uncle and churliſh Maſter, wherein he had been pinched with cold, and parched with heat, <hi>They ſeemed to him but a few days,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 29. 10.</note> 
               <hi>for the love he bare unto her.</hi> And when <hi>Ionathan had ſtripped himſelf of the robe that was upon him, and gave it to</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Sam. 18. 3.</note> David, <hi>and his garments, even to his ſword, and to his bow, and to his girdle,</hi> we read not of any repinings after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward; and the reaſon was, becauſe <hi>he loved him,</hi> as <hi>his own ſoul<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> Chriſts friends look upon him as deſerving over and over againe, infinitely more then they ſhall ever be able to requite, and therefore are troubled that Chriſt hath had ſo little ſervice, never repenting that he hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived ſo much. They know that God giveth <hi>liberally</hi>
               <note place="margin">James 1. 5.</note> 
               <hi>and upbraideth not.</hi> Worthy Doctor <hi>Sibs</hi> was wont to ſay, Suppoſing a poſſibility of ſorrow in heaven, this
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:133592:13"/> would be the grief of the Saints there, that they have done ſo little for Chriſt upon earth, from whom they have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived ſo much.</p>
            <p n="11">11. Love maketh couragious for Chriſt. Every one knoweth that St. <hi>Paul</hi> was Chriſts cordial friend, which he expreſſed by his magnanimity. <hi>I am ready not to be bound</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 21. 13. Phil. 3. <hi>Diſcipulus plus amat Christum quam timet ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hennam,</hi> Bern. <hi>Amanti nihil impoſſibile, nihil difficile.</hi> Aug.</note> 
               <hi>only, but to die at Ieruſalem for the Name of the Lord Ieſus, for whom I have ſuffered the loſſe of all.</hi> Much was loſt al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready, and life it ſelf was now at ſtake, Let all go (ſaith Love) for Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Love looketh upon nothing as impoſſible, or as too difficult to be undertaken. The fearful Hen will flie fierce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly at the devouring Creatures which would devoure her chickens; and the timorous ſheep will turn head upon a maſtiff dog, to ſecure her beloved Lamb. <hi>Love is strong</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cant. 8. 6, 7.</note> 
               <hi>as death, many waters cannot quench love, neither can the floods drown it. Mary,</hi> whoſe boſome was full of burning love to Chriſt, is a rare example of that metall and fortitude which love breedeth in Chriſts friends. She ſeeking Chriſts dead body, and meeting with the Gardener (as ſhe imagined) ſhe ſpeaketh thus: <hi>Sir, if thou haſt borne him hence, tell me where thou hast laid him, and I will</hi>
               <note place="margin">John 20. 15.</note> 
               <hi>take him away.</hi> Neither the ghaſtly looks of a dead body could affright, nor the weight of it diſcourage her reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions to bear it away. Though ſhe was not able (good ſoul) by her own ſtrength to carry ſuch a burden, yet her love made her confident that ſhe could do it, and therefore was reſolved to undertake it.</p>
            <p n="12">12. All theſe forementioned actings and adventures of love in Chriſts friends, do ariſe, neither only nor prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally from ſelf-advantages received from him, but from his excellencies, and reſpect to his honour. <hi>Becauſe of</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cant. 1. 3.</note> 
               <hi>the ſavour of thy good ointments, thy Name is an ointment poured forth, therefore do the Virgins love thee.</hi> And in this, Saint <hi>Paul</hi> centered as the laſt end of his love, that <hi>Ieſus Chriſt might be magnified in him, whether by life or</hi>
               <note place="margin">Phil. 1. 20. John 6. 26.</note> 
               <hi>death;</hi> Whereas when Chriſt is looked after <hi>rather for loaves</hi> then for his divine lovelineſſe, it's rather to be judged a
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:133592:13"/> trucking with him, then a loving of him. When men ſeek<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Est mercatura non amicitia, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor amicitiae non acquieſcit in aliqua ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trinſeca adopti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one, ſed quaerit amatum.</hi> Aqui,</note> only to ſerve their turn of Chriſt, as it were by merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dizing, they may be called friends to themſelves, but will never be reputed faithful friends unto him. This diſcovery lies inward and cloſe in our boſoms: in which regard, the more cautiouſneſſe is needful, that we may not be deceived.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, and for our help in the former, I adde this (as the concluſion of this ſearch<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> upon which I have held you ſo long) That ſincere friendſhip unto Chriſt, will raiſe rejoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cings in our hearts upon his advancement, though this may ſeem to tend to our perſonal detriment. Here the words of Chriſt to his drooping Diſciples, fearing that themſelves ſhould be damnified by his departure from them, are very conſiderable; <hi>If you loved me, you would</hi>
               <note place="margin">John 14. 28.</note> 
               <hi>rejoyce becauſe I ſaid, I go unto the Father. John the Baptiſt</hi> is a rare inſtance to evidence this character of true friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip: for he being told that Chriſt was likely to carry away credit from him, returned this anſwer. <hi>He that hath</hi>
               <note place="margin">Joh. 3. 29. 30.</note> 
               <hi>the Bride is the bridegroom; but the friend of the Bridegroom, which ſtandeth and heareth him, rejoyceth greatly becauſe of the Bridegrooms voice: This my joy therefore is fulfilled. He muſt increaſe, but I muſt decreaſe.</hi> And the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi>
               <note place="margin">Phil. 5. 16, 18.</note> was another example of this ingenuous love. <hi>Some</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>preach Christ of envy and ſtrife, ſuppoſing to adde afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on unto my bonds: Notwithſtanding Chriſt is preached: and I therein do rejoyce, and will rejoyce.</hi> Make application hereof, and ask your ſelves this queſtion, whether you can be content that Chriſt ſhould be ſet upon your ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, and that your credit ſhould be cropt, rather then it ſhould hinder his ſhine and proſpect? can you lay your ſelves down in the duſt, that the crown may be ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t upon Chriſts head? can you willingly be little or nothing in the account of the world, that Chriſt may be all in all among the children of men? By ſincere anſwers returned upon ſerious conſiderations of all theſe foregoing parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars, you may be able to give a right judgement of your own eſtate, whether you be in deed and in truth friends to Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:133592:14"/>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>3</label> The Uſe of Exhortation followeth: wherein I am to beſpeak your love unto Jeſus Chriſt. And O that I knew what Arguments to uſe, that I might prevaile with you to become friends unto Chriſt. Might not the remembrance of the forementioned Reaſons wherefore beleevers love him, being faithfully preſſed upon your ſpirits, be hope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully operative for this end? Take into your conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on 1. His incomparable beauties. 2. His famous exploits. 3. Your former rich receipts. 4. Your future expectations from him: and hereupon command your ſoules to give in their anſwer, whether it be not reaſonable that you ſhould love Chriſt. But forbearing the enlargement of thoſe heads, I will deal with you upon principles of ſelf-love, to love the Lord Jeſus. So many and ſo precious are the priviledges belonging unto them who are thus affected, that <hi>David</hi> knew not how to deſire more at the hand of God. <hi>Look thou upon me and be merciful unto me, as thou u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 119. 132.</note> 
               <hi>to do unto thoſe that love thy name.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Shall I mention (and do little more then mention) ſome particulars?</p>
            <p n="1">1. Thus you ſhall work your ſelves into Chriſts boſom, (which will be no ſmall advantage) <hi>I love them that love</hi>
               <note place="margin">P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ov. 8. 17.</note> 
               <hi>me,</hi> ſaid our Lord long ſince. It is reported that <hi>Veſpaſian</hi> commanded a large recompence to be given unto a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man<note place="margin">Item Veſpaſiano adamato.</note> that fell in love with him, and ordered that it ſhould be recorded, that ſuch a ſumme of money was given upon that account. More beautiful wil Chriſt be unto his friends. <hi>That I may cauſe thoſe that love me to inherit ſubſtance, and I</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prov. 8. 21.</note> 
               <hi>will fill their Treaſures:</hi> Riches, ſubſtantial riches, ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantial riches making treaſures: and all this by the right of inheritance, ſhall be the reward of them who love Chriſt.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Hereupon you may confidently expect familiar fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip with Chriſt and his Father, which is the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans Heaven upon Earth, <hi>If any man love me, my Father will love him, and I will love him, and manifest my ſelf to him, and</hi>
               <note place="margin">Joh. 14. 21, 23.</note> 
               <hi>we will come unto him, and make our abode with him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Hence iſſueth aſſurance, that all events and exerciſes
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:133592:14"/> ſhall prove, ſpiritually advantageous. <hi>Alſo we know that</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 8. 28.</note> 
               <hi>all things work together for good unto them who love God.</hi> E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very winde will undoubtedly bring in their profit, and their gain ſhall come in at every doore.</p>
            <p n="4">4. And the <hi>Crown of glory is promiſed to them who love the</hi>
               <note place="margin">James 1. 12.</note> 
               <hi>Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now if you ſhall demand, How may we kindle the fire of love in our breſts towards Chriſt? I anſwer,</p>
            <p n="1">1. By informing your ſelves from the Scripture con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Chriſt his worthineſſe, both in his perſon, relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and ſeveral Adminiſtrations as Mediatour betwixt God and man. As this is his own advice, <hi>Search the</hi>
               <note place="margin">John 5. 39.</note> 
               <hi>Scriptures, for they teſtifie of me:</hi> So by the manifeſtations of him, friendly affections are kindled towards him. Witneſſe the experience of ſuch who during their igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of Chriſt were ſo farre from loving him, that they ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted the love of others groundleſſe, yet underſtanding his unparallel'd beauties, fell in love with him. This is open and apparent by comparing <hi>Cant.</hi> 5. 9. with <hi>ver.</hi> 10. to the end, and with <hi>Chap.</hi> 6. 1. The words being<note place="margin">Prov. 14. 20.</note> many, I refer you to the reading of them. <hi>The rich hath many friends</hi> (ſaith <hi>Solomon</hi>) And are not all the riches of earth and heaven in Chriſts poſſeſſion and at his diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing?</p>
            <p n="2">2. By preſenting often unto your view by meditation<note place="margin">Pſalme 39. 3.</note> all things amiable in Chriſt. <hi>While I muſed</hi> (ſaith the Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt) <hi>the fire burned.</hi> Looking cauſeth loving, <hi>The eye</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lam. 3. 51.</note> 
               <hi>affect the heart:</hi> By blowing a ſpark becomes a flame. As <hi>Abrahams</hi> ſervant brought forth <hi>Jewels of ſilver, and</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 24. 53.</note> 
               <hi>Jewels of go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d</hi> to win <hi>Rebecca</hi> her heart towards <hi>Iſaac;</hi> So ſhould we ſpread before our ſouls frequently thoſe things which are enjoyed i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Chriſt, that our hearts may be ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moured with him. Ponder upon his own expreſſions, <hi>I love them that love me, and thoſe that ſeek me early ſhall finde</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prov. 8. 17, 18, 19.</note> 
               <hi>me. Riches and honour are with me: yea, durable riches and Righteouſneſſe. My fruit is better then Gold, yea then fine Gold, and my revenues then choice Silver.</hi> Dwell upon theſe
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:133592:15"/> and the like conſiderations, and the Lord bleſſe them to the end for which propounded, that your ſouls may flame forth loves upon the Lord Jeſus.</p>
            <p>The ſecond Branch of the Doctrine followeth; <hi>viz. That</hi>
               <note place="margin">Branch 2.</note> 
               <hi>Chriſt is a loving friend unto all true Chriſtians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Howſoever he here calleth <hi>Lazarus</hi> his ſpecial friend, and the Apoſtles were ſo accounted in ſome way of pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liarity, <hi>Henceforth I call you not ſervants, but I have called</hi>
               <note place="margin">John 15 15.</note> 
               <hi>you friends.</hi> Yet this compellation, and this amiable rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion belongeth unto all faithful Chriſtians likewiſe. He <hi>loved all his own in the world;</hi> which is plaine alſo, by that<note place="margin">Joh. 13. 1.</note> gracious invitation, <hi>Eat O friends, and drink O Beloved,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cant. 5. 1.</note> wherein he intendeth to take in all living Chriſtians.</p>
            <p>Now if the reaſon be demanded, Wherefore Chriſt is ſo good a friend unto believing Chriſtians? I anſwer,</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>1</label> 1. Becauſe they are peculiarly his own upon Covenant<note place="margin">Gal. 3. 16.</note> 
               <hi>compact betwixt the Father and himſelf.</hi> The Covenant was primarily betwixt God and Chriſt, whereupon they were committed to his truſt for the praiſe of glorious grace. And <hi>He therefore loved them becauſe his own.</hi> This our Lord him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf<note place="margin">Joh. 13. 1.</note> doth more then intimate in his moſt heavenly prayer, wherein expreſſing his reſpect to his Fathers honour, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with abundant love towards the Elect, he doth very often touch upon them <hi>as given unto him</hi> by the Father. And<note place="margin">Joh. 17. 2, 4, 6, 7, 8, 9, 11. 12, 24</note> upon this account it was that he thus ſpeaketh of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion which he had with his Father before the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the world were laid. <hi>I was by him as one brought</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 8. 30. 31.</note> 
               <hi>up with him, and I was daily his delight, rejoycing alwayes before him Rejoycing in the habitable parts of his earth, and my delights were with the ſons of men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>2</label> Becauſe of the dear deliberate purchaſe which he made<note place="margin">Titus 2. 14.</note> of them, that they might be brought in to friendly fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip with him. It is commonly ſaid, that the mother loveth thoſe children moſt which coſt her the moſt paine when ſhe brought them into the world. The Prophet calleth the <hi>fruit of the womb, Beloved.</hi> And that is very<note place="margin">Hoſ. 9. 16.</note> conſiderable to this purpoſe which the Evangelical
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:133592:15"/> Prophet foretold of Chriſt, <hi>He ſhall ſee of the travel of his</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 53. 11. 1 Cor. 6. 19, 20</note> 
               <hi>ſoul, and ſhall be ſatisfied.</hi> We are Chriſts by redemption, and in this regard alſo we are his beloved friends, and highly eſteemed by him above others, as the Prophet witneſſeth, <hi>Since thou waſt precious in my ſight, I loved thee,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 43. 4.</note> 
               <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>3</label> 3. Becauſe of their ſpiritual troth-plight unto Chriſt. The Apoſtle ſpeaketh of <hi>eſpouſing the beleeving Corinthians</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 11. 2. Hoſea 2. 19.</note> unto him as <hi>their huſband.</hi> And as this is done in <hi>loving kindneſſe and mercy,</hi> ſo becauſe of this relation, Chriſt is propounded as an example of great love. <hi>Huſbands, love</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eph. 5. 25.</note> 
               <hi>your wives, even as Chriſt loved his Church, and gave himſelfe for it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>4</label> 4. Becauſe they are incorporated into Chriſt as mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers<note place="margin">1 Cor. 12. 12.</note> of his body myſtical. <hi>As the body is one, and hath ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny members, ſo alſo is Chriſt.</hi> And upon this ground like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe is Chriſts love to his people inferred, <hi>No man ever yet</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eph. 5. 29 30.</note> 
               <hi>hated his own fleſh, but nouriſheth and cheriſheth it, even as the Lord his Church: For we are members of his body, of his fleſh, and of his bone.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>5</label> 5. Becauſe all the revenues (as it were) of Chriſts ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and reputation on earth, are raiſed from among be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving Chriſtians: for <hi>praiſe waiteth for him in Zion:</hi> and<note place="margin">Pſal. 65. 1. Pſal. 22. 30. Exod. 19. 5. Mal. 3. 17. 2 Cor. 8. 23.</note> this is the <hi>ſeed which ſhall ſerve him.</hi> As before his incar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation they are called Gods <hi>peculiar treaſure,</hi> and his <hi>Jew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els;</hi> ſo ſince his Aſcenſion the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> ſtileth them the <hi>Glory of Chriſt.</hi> And in this regard a principle of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine ſelf-love doth incline the Lord Chriſt to be a friend unto beleevers.</p>
            <p>For the illuſtration of this truth, know, that this love of Chriſt is fourfold; <hi>viz.</hi> 1. Of his <hi>eternal pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe.</hi> 2. Of <hi>Benevolence.</hi> 3. Of <hi>Complacency,</hi> 4. Of <hi>Compaſſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. There is a love of divine good pleaſure appertaining unto Gods people: In this ſenſe God ſaith, <hi>Jacob have</hi>
               <note place="margin">Amor benepla<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> citi.</note> 
               <hi>I loved:</hi> and in the purſuit hereof the Lord in due time con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verteth<note place="margin">Rom. 9. 13.</note> them unto himſelfe; <hi>I have loved thee with an ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jer. 31. 3.</note>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:133592:16"/> 
               <hi>love, therefore with loving kindneſſe have I drawn thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The Lord loveth them with the love of benevolence,<note place="margin">Amor benevo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e.</note> communicating to them, together with himſelf and his loves, his All, for their comfort: <hi>Who loved me</hi> (ſaith Saint <hi>Paul) and gave himſelf for me. All are yours;</hi> and<note place="margin">Gal 2. 20. 1 Cor. 3. 21. 2 Cor. 4. 15.</note> 
               <hi>all things are for your ſakes,</hi> ſaith the ſame Apoſtle. Chriſt himſelf being the heir of all things, both in heaven and earth, the fountaine both of grace and comfort, brings along with himſelf all needful accommodations, terreſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, celeſtial, whether they concern this life, or that which is to come. How liberal was Gods love to <hi>Abraham his friend,</hi> giving all <hi>Canaan</hi> to him and his ſeed after<note place="margin">1 Chron. 20. 7.</note> him!</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Lord embraceth them with a love of delight<note place="margin">Amor Amiciti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> and complacency, he himſelf having made them lovely by putting upon them his own robes and ornaments, both by juſtifying and ſanctifying grace. This is taught by<note place="margin">Pſ. 45. 9, 11, 13.</note> ſundry expreſſions in that Song of Loves. <hi>The Kings Daughter is all glorious within, her cloathing is of wrought Gold. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon thy right hand did ſtand the Queen in Gold of Ophir: ſo ſhall the King greatly deſire thy beauty.</hi> And to the ſame purpoſe doth the Prophet <hi>Ezekiel</hi> metaphori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally hold for this truth, <hi>I waſhed thee with water, yea, I throughly waſhed away thy blood from thee, and I anointed thee with oile: I clothed thee alſo with broidered work, I</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezek. 16. 9, 10, 11, 12, 13 14</note> 
               <hi>girded thee about with fine linnen, and covered thee with ſilk, I decked thee alſo with Ornaments, and I put bracelets upon thy hand, and a chaine on thy neck: And I put a Jewel on thy fore head, and ear-rings in thy ears, and a beautiful crown on thy head. Thus waſt thou decked with Gold and Silver, and thy raiment was of fine linnen and ſilk, and broidered work, and thou waſt exceeding beautiful; and thy renown went forth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Heathen for thy beauty, for it was perfect through my comelineſſe put upon thee, ſaith the Lord God.</hi> Therefore though the Elect themſelves are rather loathſome then delightful in their unregenerate eſtate, yet being covered with Chriſt his righteouſneſſe, and adorned with the gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces<note place="margin">Tit. 3. 3. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:133592:16"/> of his holy Spirit, they are friends in whom he taketh much delight. Hereupon the Church is called <hi>Hephzibah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 62. 4.</note> 
               <hi>for the Lord delighteth in her.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. Chriſt expreſſeth towards them the love of compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Amor miſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordiae.</hi> Iſa. 63. 9.</note> ſympathizing with them in all their ſorrows and ſufferings: in all <hi>their affliction he was afflicted.</hi> As in refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to his friend <hi>Lazarus,</hi> being brought to the place<note place="margin">Joh. 11. 35, 36.</note> where he was buried, <hi>Jeſus wept.</hi> And hence the Jewes inferred this concluſion, <hi>behold how he loved him!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>1</label> This makes much for the comfort of all truly gracious Chriſtians, ſeeing the Lord Jeſus is their friend. God intending to give <hi>David</hi> a cordial upon the death of his childe, beſtoweth upon him <hi>Solomon,</hi> with this aſſurance<note place="margin">2 Sam. 12. 24, 25.</note> that he loved him, whereupon he was called <hi>Jedi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iah;</hi> And for the chearing of <hi>Daniels</hi> heart, he was told once and againe, that <hi>he was greatly beloved by the Lord.</hi> Now<note place="margin">Dan. 3. 23. &amp; 10. 11, 19.</note> this refreſhing reacheth all Goſpel-Chriſtians univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſally.</p>
            <p>In the ſerving out of this cordial, I will briefly endeavour to lay before you</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. The Characters of Chriſts beloved friends.</item>
               <item>2. The comforts hence deducible for their relief.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Firſt, for theſe ſignes of Chriſts beloved friends, I refer you to the review and application of the particulars in the former branch of the Doctrine, for the diſcovery of ſuch who are his loving friends. For this is moſt certaine, that Chriſt <hi>loveth all thoſe who love him.</hi> And I adde<note place="margin">Prov. 8. 17.</note> theſe two further evidences of them who are beloved of Chriſt.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Thoſe who <hi>are beloved of the Lord are called to be Saints.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 1. 7.</note> Two things are conſiderable in the quotation, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That theſe Saints are not ſo titularly onely (becauſe ſo reputed and nominated among men;) but Saints in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ality and practice, being perſons whoſe hearts are ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from common pollutions, raiſed above creature con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents, to minde the matters of God in good earneſt: in which reſpect they are called <hi>his Saints</hi> devoted unto him<note place="margin">Pſal 56. 5.</note> peculiarly.</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:133592:17"/>
            <p>And this calling is not alone external (for thouſands who continue haters of God, are called upon, to lay down<note place="margin">Iſa. 65. 2, 3.</note> their arms of <hi>rebellion,</hi> and to ſubmit unto the government of Chriſt) but it is a calling internal and efficacious, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quering the ſoul to come in unto Chriſt, leaving all in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution, affection, and endeavour for him. Therefore in the application of this, note, the Quere ſhould be, which way the ſtrongeſt ſtream of minde and will do run? whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſin—ward, world-ward, or God-ward? and what is the greateſt deſigne, driven on by project and practice, whether to ſatisfie luſts, and to grow great in the world, or to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form unto laws divine, and to advance Chriſts glory.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> conjoyneth <hi>faithful and beloved.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Tim. 6. 2.</note> Perſons beloved by the Lord, are faithful to the Lord. And this fidelity doth evidence it ſelfe by two things eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially.</p>
            <p n="1">1. By cleaving inſeparably unto the guidance of God, when others are ſwayed by the multitude, ſwimming down the tide of times. In this regard in times of general Apoſtacy, <hi>Judah</hi> is ſaid to continue <hi>faithful with the Saints,</hi> holding cloſe to his will in holy worſhip, when<note place="margin">Hoſ. 11. 12. with chap. 5. 11.</note> 
               <hi>Ephraim</hi> followed mens traditions and commandments.</p>
            <p n="2">2. By intending Gods glory more then perſonal advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage in courſe of life and converſation.</p>
            <p>And in this reſpect the Apoſtle ſpeaking of the ſervants duty, doth place <hi>purloyning,</hi> in oppoſition to <hi>good fidelity;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tit. 2. 10.</note> that ſervant who purſeth his Maſters gaine, he is not faithful. If theſe things were brought home by an unpartial application, how many would be found in theſe times not befriended by Chriſt, though they would be cryed up as his chiefeſt favourites among men?</p>
            <p>Secondly, the comforts which belong unto ſuch whom Chriſt affecteth as his friends, may be conſidered under two heads, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1. The quality</cell>
                     <cell cols="2">of his love towards them.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>2. The efficiency</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, his love them ward, for quality is,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Moſt cordial. They are <hi>the dearly beloved of his ſoul.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jer. 12. 7.</note>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:133592:17"/> It is not lip-love, love from the teeth outward, but love from the heart-root.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Moſt large: <hi>it paſſeth knowledge,</hi> it exceedeth all di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menſions.<note place="margin">Eph. 3. 19.</note> Whereas <hi>never greater love</hi> was expreſſed, <hi>then</hi>
               <note place="margin">Joh. 15. 13.</note> 
               <hi>that a man ſhould die for his friend. Chriſt</hi> commendeth his love as much more, becauſe he <hi>died for ſinners, and for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 5. 6. 7, 8</note>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Moſt refreſhing. This love is not only <hi>ſweeter then</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cant. 1. 3. Pſal. 63. 3.</note> 
               <hi>wine,</hi> but alſo <hi>better then life,</hi> yea better then lives, as the Original imports. All the comforts of life natural and ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, all the comforts of the ſeveral ages and conditions of life are not comparable to this love.</p>
            <p n="4">4 Moſt conſtant; whom he <hi>loveth once, he loveth to the</hi>
               <note place="margin">Joh. 1. 31.</note> 
               <hi>end.</hi> This Chriſt did caſt in to chear his Diſciples, being to depart from them. No oppoſition, loſſe, or change what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever, can <hi>poſſibly ſeparate beloved</hi> Chriſtians <hi>from this love,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 8. 55</note> which the Apoſtle mentioneth as a matter of high joy and holy triumph. Whereas <hi>Solomon</hi> telleth us, that <hi>a friend</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prov. 17. 17. &amp; 18. 24.</note> 
               <hi>loveth at all times,</hi> and that <hi>there is a friend that ſticketh clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer then a brother;</hi> this may moſt truly be applied unto our loving friend Chriſt Jeſus. This the Text ſuggeſteth; for Chriſt did not only love <hi>Lazarus</hi> while he lived, but called him friend, even now when he was dead, <hi>Our friend Laza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus ſleepeth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, the efficiency of his love is admirably comfort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, to all ſuch who enjoy it. For firſt, it worketh their deliverance from whaſoever may be grievous and dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous. <hi>He loved us, and waſhed us from our ſins in his blood.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rev. 1. 5. Gal. 3. 13. 1 Theſ. 1. 10.</note> And hence follows deliverance <hi>from the curſe of the Law, and from the wrath to come.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, it procureth whatſoever may be joyous unto a ſpiritual heart.</p>
            <p n="1">1. He hath made us (upon this account) <hi>Kings and Prieſts unto God and his Father.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rev. 1. 6.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. He feedeth the ſoul plentifully by the dainties of ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Ordinances; <hi>Eat O my friends, and drink, yea drink</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cant. 5. 1.</note> 
               <hi>abundantly, O my beloved.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. This his love running through all providences, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:133592:18"/> bleſſings the more ſweet, and ſupporteth the ſink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſoule under croſſes. As <hi>Hezekiah</hi>'s recovery was the<note place="margin">Iſa. 38. 17. Heb. 12. 5, 6.</note> more pleaſant, becauſe <hi>God in love to his ſoul</hi> wrought it: ſo the Apoſtle puts this as a prop under a fainting af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted Chriſtian, that the Lord correcteth with paternal <hi>love.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. And his love will prepare his beloved for glory. Chriſt loved the Church that <hi>he might ſanctifie it, with the waſhing of water by the word<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that he might preſent it to</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eph. 5. 26.</note> 
               <hi>himſelfe a glorious Church, not having ſpot, or wrinkle, or any ſuch thing, but that it might be holy and without blemiſh.</hi> If unto all theſe (which I mentioned without enlargement) we add the complacency which he taketh in all communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations of his love, it will be a great addition to their joy. <hi>The Lord will rejoyce over thee, he will reſt in his love, he will</hi>
               <note place="margin">Zeph. 3. 17.</note> 
               <hi>joy over thee with ſinging.</hi> God ſeemeth to take ſuch con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent in his loving tranſactions them-ward, as though he deſired nothing more.</p>
            <p>Let the friends of Jeſus Chriſt feed and feaſt themſelves with theſe expreſſions and proviſions of his love.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>2</label> How ſhould the remembrance of ſuch rare refreſhings belonging to them, who are the beloved friends of Chriſt, quicken endeavours in all ſorts to gain a ſhare in his friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip. To enforce this exhortation, I will caſt theſe few thoughts into your mindes.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Whereas <hi>Solomon</hi> telleth us (What every dayes ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience alſo ſpeaketh) that <hi>many ſeek the Rulers favour;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prov. 10. 6. &amp; 29. 26. 1 Tim. 6. 15. Mat. 28. 18. Prov. 8. 15, 16.</note> Jeſus Chriſt is <hi>the King of kings, and the Lord of lords, the only potentate unto whom all authority in heaven and earth is committed, by whom Kings reigne, Princes rule, and all the Judges of the earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. That it will be an high honour to be called Gods friend. In holy ſtory <hi>Huſhai</hi> and <hi>Zabud</hi> have this title of<note place="margin">2 Sam. 15 27. 1 Kings 4. 5.</note> reſpect put upon them, that they were the <hi>kings friends.</hi> And it will be for the everlaſting credit of father <hi>Abraham,</hi> that he is recorded in ſacred pages, <hi>to be the friend of God.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 41. 8.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. That Chriſt is and ever will be in favour with God, to
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:133592:18"/> make and to maintaine our peace with his Majeſty, though we frequently, and fearfully do provoke him e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very day. <hi>The inhabitants of Tyre and Sidon made Blaſtus</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 12. 20.</note> 
               <hi>the Kings chamberlaine their friend, when Herod was high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſpleaſed with them, becauſe their countrey was nouriſhed by the Kings countrey.</hi> And is not our dependance more upon God? And do not we hourly give the Almighty great occaſion to reject us, yea to take up arms againſt us? And is there any one, either on earth or in heaven, that can aſſwage Gods anger, and procure his favour, beſides Jeſus Chriſt? Therefore ſhould meanes be uſed to make him our friend.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The people of God conceiving hope that Chriſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gardeth us, they will be encouraged with the more affectio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate confidence to pray for us in the times of our need. As the ſiſters of <hi>Lazarus</hi> making addreſſe unto him in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half of their dear brother, pleaded this, <hi>Lord, he whom thou</hi>
               <note place="margin">Joh. 11. 3.</note> 
               <hi>loveſt, is ſick.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. Hereby we ſhall be heartned with the more hope to apply our ſelves unto God by prayer for our ſelves. Our Saviour ſuggeſteth this in the parable of the man, who go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth<note place="margin">Luk. 11. 5. 6, 9.</note> at mid-night <hi>to his friend to borrow bread;</hi> he applieth it to incourage prayer.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Becauſe all our creature-friends may either fall off by unfaithfulneſſe, or forſake us by death or be forced from us other wayes. This the doleful complaints of ſundry dear unto the Lord recorded in Scripture, do declare: <hi>My lovers and my friends ſtand aloof from my ſore, and my</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 38. 11. and 88. 18. 1 King. 16. 11. Luke 16.</note> 
               <hi>kinſmen stand aloof off, Lover and friend thou haſt put far from me, and my acquaintance into darkneſſe.</hi> Upon this conſideration, the humane prudence of the unjuſt Steward is commended, in projecting to provide friends againſt the time of need. How far our experience at this day ſpeaketh our loſſe of creature-friends, <hi>viz.</hi> of ſome by death, and of others by an unfaithful deſerting, I forbear to ſpeak: But I do upon this conſideration move your care to gaine the friendſhip of Chriſt, who will love and live for ever: Now if theſe arguments ſhall force reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:133592:19"/> in your boſoms to ſeek Chriſts love, and thereupon means to attain it, ſhall be enquired after; I give theſe ſhort directions.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Accept of God, and of Goſpel-righteouſneſſe with him, by a ſelf-outing, and a Chriſt-prizing faith. <hi>The Scripture ſaith, Abraham beleeved God, and it was imputed</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jam. 2. 23.</note> 
               <hi>unto him for righteouſneſſe, and he was called the friend of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Upon the ſerious conſideration of his worthineſs, and hopeful expectations of happineſſe by him; labour to endear Chriſt unto your hearts. Although our love to him doth not merit his love, yet it will clearly make manifeſtation thereof unto our ſouls. <hi>I love them</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>who love me.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prov. 8. 17.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. And (as an expreſſion of your love) ſubmit obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently unto his government, ſtudiouſly conforming unto all his commands. This is his own promiſe which he will perform infallibly. <hi>He that hath my Commandments and</hi>
               <note place="margin">Joh. 14. 21.</note> 
               <hi>keepeth them, he it is that loveth me, and I will love him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>3</label> The third Uſe is to be directed unto them whom Chriſt embraceth as friends with love, and they are to be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded unto real gratitude for his love. The Diſciple whom Chriſt loved, having touched upon his incompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable love, addeth this doxology: <hi>To him be glory and</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 16.</note> 
               <hi>dominion for ever, and ever, Amen.</hi> From whence might be noted,</p>
            <p n="1">1. That the glory to be returned unto Chriſt for his love ſhould not be verbal onely, but real alſo, expreſſed by ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection unto his dominion.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That this obediential gratitude ſhould not be confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to term of time, but extended unto eternity, <hi>for ever and ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. And all Chriſtians ſhould heartily give in their aſſent and atteſtation hereto by annexing their <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the amplification of this perſwaſion, I might call you back to the review both of the proof of this doctrine, and of the qualities and efficiency of his love, ſpoken unto, in the firſt Uſe: But that I may not tautologize by telling the ſame things again, I wiſh you to meditate upon theſe particulars which will yet further commend Chriſts love,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:133592:19"/> and may call you forth in thankfulneſſe for it.</p>
            <p n="1">1. His love was primary to us, and ours ſecundary, ſuccee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding it, as the effect and conſequence thereof, <hi>we loved</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Joh 4. 19.</note> 
               <hi>him, becauſe he loved us firſt.</hi> If he had not fired our hearts with the flames of his love, we ſhould never have beſtowed one ſpark of ſpiritual affection upon him.</p>
            <p n="2">2. His love was free, when there was much loath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomneſſe, and no lovelineſſe at all in us. <hi>When thou waſt</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezek. 16. 5, 6. 7, 8.</note> 
               <hi>caſt out in the open field, to the loathing of thy perſon in the day that thou waſt born. And when I paſſed by thee, and ſaw thee polluted in thy blood, when thou wast naked and bare. Now when I paſſed by thee, and looked upon thee, behold thy time was the time of love.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. His love worketh him unto a familiar converſing with them, which himſelf expreſſeth by feaſting with them, <hi>He brought me into the banqueting houſe, and his banner over</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cant. 1. 4.</note> 
               <hi>me was love; I will ſup with them, and the, ſhall ſup with me:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rev. 3. 20.</note> and by acquainting them with himſelf, <hi>I will manifeſt my</hi>
               <note place="margin">Joh. 14 21.</note> 
               <hi>ſelf unto them:</hi> as alſo by revealing his ſecrets, <hi>I have called you friends: for all things that I have heard of my Father, I</hi>
               <note place="margin">Joh. 15. 15.</note> 
               <hi>have made known unto you.</hi> As alſo by conjugal embracings: <hi>His left hand is under my head, and his right hand doth im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cant. 2. 6.</note> 
               <hi>me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now if Chriſts beloved friends, thankfully diſpoſed to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards him for his love, ſhall demand how their gratitude ſhould be really diſcovered? I anſwer in the words of <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon; A man that hath friends, muſt ſhew himſelfe friendly:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prov. 18. 24.</note> which is done,</p>
            <p n="1">1. By a cautious declining of whatſoever may be offenſive unto him; as the returning of evil for good is very ſinful, and a practiſe prejudicial to our ſelves, ſo is it taken very unkindly by the Lord. Thus <hi>David</hi> complaineth of <hi>Achitophel,</hi> (and as ſome conceive, Chriſt of <hi>Judas) My friend that did eat of my bread, hath lifted up his heel against</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal 41. 9. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>me.</hi> As <hi>Caeſar</hi> was moſt afflicted with the wound received from his own ſons hands. And thou my ſon too!</p>
            <p>Therefore upon remembrance of Chriſts kindneſſe learn to beat back temptations as <hi>Joſeph</hi> did. <hi>How then
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:133592:20"/> ſhall I do this wickedneſſe, and ſin againſt the Lord</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 39 9.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. By an inſeparable adherence unto Chriſt in dayes of deepeſt difficulty and danger. The ſervant engaged to his Maſter by his favours, is willing to have his eare <hi>bored, that he may dwell with him for ever. Ruth</hi> upon the receipt<note place="margin">Exod. 21. 5, 6.</note> of leſſe love a great deal from <hi>Naomi</hi> her mother in law, taketh up this reſolution, <hi>Nothing ſhall part thee and me</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ruth 1. 16.</note> 
               <hi>but death.</hi> God forbid that ever we by our Apoſtacy ſhould give Chriſt occaſion to ſpeak by way of reproach to us as <hi>Abſalon</hi> did to <hi>Huſhai</hi> (deſerting <hi>David,</hi> as he apprehended) <hi>Is this thy kindneſſe to thy friend? Why wenteſt</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Sam. 16. 17.</note> 
               <hi>not thou with thy friend?</hi> So be you ſure that this one circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance will gripe your hearts with great grief for your backſlidings. As <hi>Peter</hi> in this regard <hi>wept bitterly,</hi> becauſe he<note place="margin">Mat. 26. 75.</note> had denied, and deſerted Chriſt, ſo good a Maſter, ſo well deſerving a friend.</p>
            <p n="3">3. By unfained love unto all them, who are the belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved friends of Chriſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> This is the inference of Saint <hi>John,</hi> from this conſideration under diſcourſe, that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>we ought to love one another, and we ought to lay down our lives for the brethren.</hi> But of this more in the doctrine<note place="margin">1 Joh 4. 11. and 3. 16.</note> following.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>2</label> That <hi>all Chriſts friends are mutually loving friends unto one another.</hi> As Chriſt here ſaith not, my friend, but <hi>our friend Lazarus,</hi> thereby intending to declare the friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip which was betwixt <hi>Lazarus</hi> and his Diſciples, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt himſelf and <hi>Lazarus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the proof of this doctrine, I will point at two particulars (which I conceive this inſtance under hand may hint.)</p>
            <p n="1">1. That there is friendlineſſe and love amongſt all good Chriſtians. In this reſpect the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> in his<note place="margin">Eph. 1. 15.</note> Epiſtle to the <hi>Epheſians,</hi> joyneth their <hi>faith in Chriſt,</hi> and<note place="margin">Philem. 5.</note> their <hi>love to all Saints.</hi> And in his Epiſtle to <hi>Philemon,</hi> he connexeth his love to Chriſt, and <hi>his love to all Saints.</hi> Yea, our Saviour maketh this the livery whereby his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants may be diſtinguiſhed from others. <hi>By this ſhall</hi>
               <note place="margin">Joh. 13 35.</note>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:133592:20"/> 
               <hi>all men know that ye are my Diſciples, if ye have love one to another.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. That there is a peculiarity of friendly reſpect in Chriſtians unto Chriſts Miniſters, as here in <hi>Lazarus</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Chriſt his Apoſtles. This is obſervable in the Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſent from <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> to <hi>Antioch,</hi> wherein their expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of ſpecial love is recorded; <hi>viz. Our beloved Barnabas</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 15. 25.</note> 
               <hi>and Paul.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But I will not deal with the Doctrine in both theſe bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches diſtinctly. The handling of it more generally (for bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity ſake) ſhall be alone undertaken.</p>
            <p>And the Reaſons of the point are foure.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>1</label> 1. Becauſe of their relation both unto Chriſt and amongſt themſelves. They ſtand related unto Chriſt as his ſubjects, ſervants, children, Spouſe, Members, (which, all will acknowledge, and therefore needeth no proof.) And hence iſſueth love. As <hi>David</hi> was ready to ſhew kindneſſe to the houſe of <hi>Saul</hi> for <hi>Jonathans ſake.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Sam. 9. 1.</note>
            </p>
            <p>And among themſelves they are related many<note place="margin">P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ilemon 16. 1 Pet. 3. 8. a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d 2. 17. 1 Cor. 12. 25.</note> wayes moſt nearly. They are brethren, and the <hi>brotherhood is to be loved.</hi> And they are fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>members, and therefore to have mutual <hi>reſpect one to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>2</label> 2. Becauſe of Chriſt his expreſſe command, which is repeated, and ſtrengthened with his own example. <hi>This</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Joh. 4 21.</note> 
               <hi>command we have from him, that he who loveth God, loveth his brother alſo. A new Commandment I give unto you,</hi>
               <note place="margin">John 13. 34. and 15. 12.</note> 
               <hi>That ye love one another, as I have loved you, that ye love one another.</hi> And again, <hi>This is my Commandment, That ye love one another, as I have loved you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>3</label> 3. Becauſe of the image of God engraven upon them,<note place="margin">1 Joh. 5. 1.</note> expreſſed by their holy converſation.</p>
            <p>The Apoſtle <hi>John</hi> aſſerts this, <hi>That every one who loveth him that begat, loveth him alſo that is begotten of him.</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the childe is the picture (as it were) of his father, therefore beloved for his fathers ſake.</p>
            <p>I here forbear to diſcover how Beleevers begotten <hi>again</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Pet. 1. 3. Iſa. 9. 6. 1 Cor. 15. 49.</note> by Chriſt (as the <hi>everlaſting Father) do bear his image;</hi>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:133592:21"/> but this I propound as the reaſon of Chriſtians mutual love.</p>
            <p>As the <hi>inward affection of Titus was more abundant to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 7. 15.</note> 
               <hi>the Corinthians whileſt he remembred their obedience;</hi> And as it's reported of <hi>Beucer</hi> and <hi>Calvin,</hi> that they loved all them in whom they could eſpy <hi>aliquid Chriſti,</hi> any thing of Chriſt: So doubtleſſe it is with all others who are friends unto Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>4</label> Becauſe of the habitation and operation of Gods Spirit in their hearts. The Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> calleth this love,<note place="margin">Col. 1. 8.</note> 
               <hi>love in the Spirit.</hi> And the Apoſtle Saint <hi>John</hi> diſcourſing of this Chriſtian affection, and conſequently of Gods dwelling in us (being thereby evidenced) giveth in this as the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation of both, <hi>Becauſe he hath given us of his Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Joh. 4. 12, 13.</note>
            </p>
            <p>This I place as the laſt Argument, becauſe it is the true reaſon which maketh all the former concluding: For nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſpiritual relation, nor divine injunction, nor Chriſts image upon the Chriſtians ſoul, could have any command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing influence to draw forth this holy love amongſt Belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, if God did not co-operate by the power of the holy Ghoſt.</p>
            <p>Thus from the confirmation I proceed to the Applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Doctrine; which I ſhall make in four Uſes; <hi>viz. 1. Conviction. 2. Examination. 3. Comfort. 4. Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>3</label> Hence two ſorts of perſons are caſhier'd, as people who are ſtrangers to friendly fellowſhip with Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Such who are rather enemies, then friends unto the people of God, as their own conſciences witneſſe to themſelves, and their practices proclaim to the world, this being their deſign and endeavour (if they could effect it) to ruinate them in their comforts and lives altogether; <hi>They have ſaid</hi> (in their deſires, though not with their lips) <hi>Come let us cut them off from being a Nation, that the</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 83. 4.</note> 
               <hi>name of Iſrael may be no more in remembrance.</hi> Whatſoever ſhew of love unto Chriſt theſe perſons make among men,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:133592:21"/> doubtleſſe they are adverſaries to him, as ſundry paſſages, ſurrounding the laſt quotation do clearly expreſs. <hi>Keep not</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 83. 1, 2, 5.</note> 
               <hi>thou ſilence O God, hold not thy peace, and be not ſtill O God. Lo thine enemies make a tumult, and they that hate thee, have lift up the head, they are confederate againſt thee.</hi> As<note place="margin">2 Sam. 3 17.</note> 
               <hi>Joab</hi> took <hi>Abner aſide to ſpeak peaceably, but ſmote him under the fifth rib that he died;</hi> So theſe, though they ſmile upon Chriſts face with a ſalute, yet they ſtab his body; or (as one wittily expreſſeth it) they kiſſe the mouth and tread upon the toes. Such unfriendlineſſe to godly Chriſtians,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Argueth an unregenerate eſtate. <hi>The upright in his</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prov. 29. 27.</note> 
               <hi>way is an abomination to the wicked.</hi> And he that loveth not thoſe who are like God, <hi>is one of the children of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Joh. 3. 10.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. And is not conſiſtent with meetneſſe to be made par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers<note place="margin">Col. 1. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> of the inheritance of Saints in light. For it is not a heaven, but a hell rather to be confined to the company of<note place="margin">1 Joh. 3. 14, 15.</note> ſuch as are hated. <hi>He that loveth not his brother abideth in death, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As this doctrine falls thus heavy upon all thoſe who are enemies, rather then friends unto ordinary Chriſtians: ſo upon ſuch eſpecially who are profeſſed adverſaries to the Miniſters of Chriſt. You know how the holy Ghoſt doth ſtigmatize <hi>Ahab,</hi> who hated <hi>Michaiah,</hi> that he was a man who <hi>ſold himſelf to do wickedneſs;</hi> whereas unto true Goſpel.<note place="margin">1 Kings 21. Rom. 10. 15.</note> Beleevers the very <hi>feet of them are beautiful</hi> who bring the glad tidings of peace.</p>
            <p>Secondly, thoſe much more are by this doctrine ſet aſide as no friends to Chriſt, who are Boutefeuz and Incendiaries, ſeeking to kindle coals of contentions, and to increaſe the flames of diſcontent and animoſities among the people of God. This practice proveth them to be Factors for the Devil, and expoſeth them to the wrath of God. It was an <hi>evil ſpirit that made diviſion betwixt Abimelech and the men of Shechem.</hi> The Devil is pictured with a cloven foot,<note place="margin">Judg. 9. 27.</note> to ſignifie that it's his work to cauſe and continue diviſions in the world; And thoſe who ſow thoſe <hi>ſeeds of diſcord</hi> are<note place="margin">Prov. 6. 16, 19.</note> reckoned by <hi>Solomon</hi> among them whom the <hi>Lord hateth,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:133592:22"/> and who are an abomination unto him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>2</label> From this open Conviction I proceed unto Exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, becauſe there are many who upon trial will not be found real friends unto Gods people, though they be not ſuch notorious oppoſites as were deſcribed in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Uſe.</p>
            <p>Therefore take thoſe diſcoveries of them who are right in their loves to real Chriſtians.</p>
            <p>Firſt, from the <hi>object</hi> of love, <hi>viz. Sanctif<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing grace.</hi> There are many lovely qualifications in Gods faithful ſervants,<note place="margin">Mark. 6. 20.</note> which an ingenuous moral man may value; as <hi>Herod</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verenced <hi>John the Baptiſt;</hi> but it's holineſs which is the load<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone to draw the love of the regenerate Chriſtian. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>Saints, therefore excellent</hi> in a gracious eye. And hence<note place="margin">Pſal. 16. 2. Eph. 1. 15. 2 Cor. 7 15.</note> followeth <hi>univerſality of Love</hi> to all ſuch, and the aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of reſpect according to the increaſe of Grace.</p>
            <p>Secondly, from the <hi>qualities</hi> of his friendſhip: It is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied,</p>
            <p n="1">1. With an honourable eſtimation of them. The heirs of heaven <hi>do honour ſuch who ſear the Lord.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 15. 4. Pſal. 16. 2.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. And with complacency, <hi>All my delight</hi> (ſaith <hi>David) is in them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, from the <hi>Effects</hi> of this love; <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Readineſs to perform real offices for their comfort. Thus S. <hi>Paul</hi> proved the <hi>ſincerity of the Corinthians love,</hi> by<note place="margin">2 Cor. 8. 8, 24.</note> their contribution, for the relief of poore Saints.</p>
            <p n="2">2. And compaſſionate ſympathies when they are in trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. <hi>To him that is afflicted pity ſhould be ſhewed from his</hi>
               <note place="margin">Job 6. 14.</note> 
               <hi>friend.</hi> By this <hi>David</hi> did demonſtrate his real reſpects unto ſome who ill deſerved them, <hi>When they were ſick, my cloa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 35. 13, 14.</note> 
               <hi>was ſackcloth, I behaved my ſelf as tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gh he had been my friend.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe ſhort hints I leave to your amplification and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful application, that your ſelves may underſtand whether your love unto godly Chriſtians be ſuch as will evidence your regenerate eſtate.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>3</label> The third Uſe is for the comfort of all them, who can in this grace of Chriſtian love and friendſhip, approve their
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:133592:22"/> ſincerity unto God, not doubting but that Chriſt himſelfe will give the like teſtimony unto them herein, as he did unto <hi>Lazarus</hi> in the Text. <hi>Our friend.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For 1. It is no ſmall priviledge to partake in the love of all heavens favourites, and this love is mutual: Thoſe who are cordial friends to Chriſtians, are cordially beloved by Chriſtians, which is a matter of <hi>much joy</hi> to them who will conſider it, as in other regards, ſo becauſe their <hi>love draweth our prayers</hi> unto God, as need requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth.<note place="margin">Pſal. 122. 6, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>
            </p>
            <p>2. From hence they may infallibly conclude their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generation by ſpecial grace. <hi>Let us love one another,</hi> (ſaith Saint <hi>John) for love is of God, and every one that loveth</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Joh. 4. 7. <hi>Noſcitur ex ſocio, &amp;c.</hi> 2 Tim. 3 3.</note> 
               <hi>is born of God.</hi> Whereas perſons under the power of depra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved nature, <hi>are deſpiſers of them who are good.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>3. And, as they may upon this evidence lay claime to the comforts of grace upon earth, ſo may they raiſe confidence of future glory in heaven. <hi>We know that we</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Joh. 3. 14.</note> 
               <hi>have paſſed from death unto life, becauſe we love the bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>4</label> The laſt Uſe is exhortation, wherein two duties might be perſwaded.</p>
            <p>Firſt, to love Chriſtians, becauſe they are like unto Chriſt, and belonging unto him in the neareſt relations. The holy Ghoſt is often and earneſt in this perſwaſion,<note place="margin">1 Pet. 2. 17. and 3. 8. Col. 3. 14.</note> 
               <hi>Love the brotherhood, love as brethren: and above all things put on charity, which is the bond of perfectneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As helps herein, let theſe meditations be moulded be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievingly upon your hearts. 1. That they are in regard of ſpiritual beauties, the lovelyeſt people under the Sun, <hi>Exceeding beautiful.</hi> The Church is called <hi>the faireſt among</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezek. 16. 13. Cant. 6. 1. &amp; 5.</note> 
               <hi>women.</hi> And this is not the judgement of perſons ſubject to miſtakes, but even of Chriſt himſelf, which he gives in, again and again, both as a ground of his own love, and requiring attention unto his teſtimony. <hi>Behold thou art</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cant. 1. 15, 16. and 4. 7.</note> 
               <hi>faire my beloved, behold thou art faire; behold thou art faire, yea pleaſant. Thou art all faire my love, there is no ſpot in thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:133592:23"/>
            <p>Therefore that you may beget love in your boſomes towards Saints, do not ſo much pore upon their blemiſhes as their beauties, look rather upon their vertue then their vices; as <hi>Titus by remembring the obedience,</hi> rather then the diſobedience of the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> found <hi>his affections</hi> enlarged<note place="margin">2 Cor. 7. 15.</note> towards them.</p>
            <p>2. That the obligations of love which the Goſpel hath laid upon you, are many, and commanding. Here I will only name (without enlargement) the particulars, whereby Saint <hi>Paul</hi> perſwadeth the Chriſtian <hi>Epheſians,</hi> to keep<note place="margin">Eph. 4 3, 4, 5, 6</note> 
               <hi>the unity of the ſpirit in the bond of peace. There is one body, and one ſpirit, one baptiſme, one God and Father of all, who is above all, and through all, and in you all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>3. That no perſons whatſoever, have been, or are likely to be, ſo uſeful to your ſelves and to the publick, as theſe Saints and ſervants of the moſt high God. This argument <hi>Paul</hi> preſſeth upon <hi>Philemon,</hi> to move his affections to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards<note place="margin">Phil. 11.</note> converted <hi>Oneſimus,</hi> becauſe <hi>now</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>profitable to thee and me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe <hi>are repairers of breaches, and reſtorers of paths to</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 58. 12. Iſa. 1. 9.</note> 
               <hi>dwell in. And theſe are the remnant, which if God had not left, we ſhould have been like unto Sodom and Gomorrah.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I forbear to report how they beſtead the publick,</p>
            <p n="1">1. By their prayers. As <hi>if Moſes had not ſtood up in the breach to turne away Gods wrath, Iſrael had been de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 106. 13.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 And by their preſence, As God told <hi>Lot,</hi> he could <hi>do nothing</hi> till he removed from <hi>Sodome.</hi> By this reaſon<note place="margin">Gen. 19. 22.</note> 
               <hi>Jonathan</hi> ſpeaketh to move <hi>Saul</hi>'s bowels towards <hi>David, For he did put his life in his hand, and ſlew the Philiſtine, and</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Sam. 18. 5.</note> 
               <hi>the Lord wrought a great ſalvation for all Iſrael.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, I might from this doctrine deale with all ſorts by perſwaſion to endeavour to become godly, that they may be admitted as friends into the boſomes of Gods people. Although I know that there are higher ends to be intended in undertaking the practice of piety, <hi>viz.</hi> Gods glory, and our own ſalvation; yet this conſideration under hand would not be ſlighted, if theſe particulars (which
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:133592:23"/> I ſhall onely name) were well weighed.</p>
            <p>1. That the love of Gods people towards us will<note place="margin">Phil. 1. 4, 6.</note> produce their frequent and fervent addreſſes unto hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven for us according to our ſerviceable neceſſities.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That their applications unto the Lord, are very<note place="margin">Job 42. 8.</note> prevalent in regard of their great favour with his High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Their love will work them unto readineſſe in any other kinde to ſerve us with their intereſts and abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,<note place="margin">Heb. 6. 10.</note> counſels and communication of their experiences, as opportunity may be offered.</p>
            <p n="3">3. And their expreſſions of loving reſpect may ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſter ſome relief unto the faint hopes of ſelf-ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecting ſoules, becauſe they are to be looked upon as beſt able (in regard of their principles and experiments) to judge of the ſpiritual conditions of other Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians.</p>
            <p>I proceed to the third circumſtance, conſiderable in the firſt part of the Text, <hi>viz.</hi> That Chriſt himſelf doth teſtifie the forementioned relation of friendſhip betwixt <hi>Lazarus</hi> and himſelf with his Diſciples: <hi>Our friend.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>3</label> 
               <hi>That Jeſus Chriſt knoweth and acknowledgeth them particularly, who are friends unto himſelf and his peculiar people. The Lord knoweth them that are his.</hi> This<note place="margin">2 Tim. 1. 14.</note> knowledge comprehends obſervation, approbation, and commemoration As he owned <hi>Lazarus</hi> here, his friend; So likewiſe he did his Diſciples under the relation of<note place="margin">Matth. 28. 10.</note> brotherhood after his Reſurrection, <hi>Go tell my brethren.</hi> And ſince his Aſcenſion into glory, ſuch is his reſpect un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all ſanctified ones, <hi>That he is not aſhamed to call them</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 10. 11.</note> 
               <hi>brethren.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If more clear Scripture-proof be demanded, let theſe two paſſages be obſerved.</p>
            <p>1. That Chriſt knoweth who love him, while they are alive. This is manifeſt by <hi>Peters</hi> atteſtation, <hi>Lord, thou knoweſt that I love thee.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Joh. 21. 15, 16, 17.</note>
            </p>
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:133592:24"/>
            <p>2. That the Lord remembreth after the death of his friends, that they were ſo during life. As dead <hi>Lazarus</hi> is thus ſpoken of, <hi>Our friend.</hi> And long after <hi>Abrahams</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſe, God ſpeaking of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> thus expreſſeth himſelf, <hi>The</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 41. 8.</note> 
               <hi>ſeed of Abraham my friend.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſons. </seg>
               </label> I ſhall only point at the Reaſons whence this truth may be concluded.</p>
            <p n="1">1. God knoweth his friends, becauſe himſelf maketh them ſo. And therefore becauſe he underſtands his own actions, he cannot be ignorant in whoſe boſomes there<note place="margin">Pſal. 33. 14, 15.</note> are theſe friendly diſpoſitions.</p>
            <p n="2">2. And God will acknowledge them, becauſe he hath undertaken torecompence them. <hi>He is not unrighteous to forget labours of love.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 6. 10.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The Application followeth.</p>
            <p>This conſideration may be a cooling card unto two ſorts of people.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>1</label> 1. To all them whoſe conſciences bear witneſſe, that they have no friendly frame of heart unto ſuch godly ones, whoſe holy converſations diſcover them to be cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen and called out of the world. <hi>If mens hearts condemn them, Gods is greater and knoweth all.</hi> There will be many<note place="margin">1 Joh. 3. 20.</note> rejected at the laſt day, who have pretended much re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to Chriſt.<note place="margin">Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 7. 22, 23.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. To all thoſe who are aſhamed to own Chriſt in his cauſe, and his friends in their holy converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: for all theſe our Lord obſerveth, and of them he will be <hi>aſhamed when he cometh in the glory of</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mark 3. 32.</note> 
               <hi>his Father with the holy Angels.</hi> And I leave it to your conſideration, how miſerable their caſe will be at the laſt day, when Chriſt who knoweth all his friends and foes, ſhall <hi>ſeparate the ſheep and the</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth. 25. 32.</note> 
               <hi>goats,</hi> And ſhall come to <hi>execute judgment upon all, and to convince all that are ungodly amongſt them</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jude 15.</note> 
               <hi>of all their ungodly deeds, which they have ungodly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, and of all their hard ſpeeches which ungodly ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners have spoken againſt him;</hi> And of the individual
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:133592:24"/> unfriendly neglects of his neceſſitous ſervants: theſe muſt <hi>depart with a curſe from Chriſt, and go away into e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 25. 41. 46.</note> 
               <hi>puniſhment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>2</label> This truth adminiſtreth ſweet comfort unto all them who are faithful friends unto the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and his real Relations. The <hi>teſtimony of their own conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 1. 12.</note> will in this caſe reflect refreſhing; and this will be a great addition unto their comfort, that expreſſions of friendly reſpect both to God and his ſervants, are thus obſerved, and will be acknowledged. The Lord himſelf to en<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ourage <hi>Iſrael</hi> in captivity, giveth them to<note place="margin">Jer. 24 5.</note> underſtand that he will own them in that eſtate. No doubt it was good news to <hi>Cornelius,</hi> when he heard<note place="margin">Acts 10. 4.</note> from heaven, <hi>Thy Prayers and thine Alms are come for a memorial before God.</hi> So the Pſalmiſt cheareth himſelf by this conſideration, <hi>I have preached Righteouſneſſe in the</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 40 9<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 10.</note> 
               <hi>great Congregation. Lo I have not refrained my lips, O Lord thou knoweſt it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This conſolation will be admirably ſweet at two ſeaſons.</p>
            <p>Firſt, When we may be injuriouſly ſuſpected and cenſured for falſneſſe and unfaithfulneſſe, either to God, or to his people. How well was it for <hi>Morde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cai</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſther 2. 21.</note> (when himſelf with his Countrey-men, were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cryed and condemned as enemies to the State) that his fidelity in a particular inſtance was recorded? And to bring this home to the knowledge that God taketh of his ſervants ſincerity: <hi>J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>b</hi> being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proached<note place="margin">Job 23. 10.</note> as an hypocrite, hath recourſe to this, <hi>He knoweth the way that I take.</hi> And <hi>Jeremiah</hi> being ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected to be one ill-affected towards the place where he lived, maketh this appeale to the Lord,<note place="margin">Jer. 17. 16.</note> 
               <hi>I have not deſired the wofull day, thou know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, At the day of Judgement, when God will meaſure out unto people according to their wayes.</p>
            <pb n="38" facs="tcp:133592:25"/>
            <p>The Prophet <hi>Malachy</hi> having mentioned both Gods hearing the good conferences of ſuch who feare his Name in evil times, and the book of Remembrance recording all; he addeth, <hi>And theſe ſhall be mine</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mal. 3. 16, 17.</note> 
               <hi>ſaith the Lord of Hoſts, in the day when I make up my jewels, &amp;c.</hi> And this cordial is contained in <hi>Pauls</hi> Prayer for <hi>Oneſiphorus, The Lord give mercy to the houſe of Oneſiphorus, for he refreſhed me, and was</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Tim. 1. 16, 17, 18.</note> 
               <hi>not aſhamed of my chaine; But when he was at Rome, he ſought me diligently, and found me. The Lord grant unto him, that he may finde mercy of the Lord in that day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But moſt comfortable is that full promiſe of Chriſt himſelfe unto all ſuch who are friendly unto him in his<note place="margin">Matth. 25. 34. 40. 46.</note> relations, recorded in <hi>Matthew</hi> 25. from <hi>ver.</hi> 34. to <hi>ver.</hi> 40. from whence theſe particulars are worthy conſideration.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That he will at the laſt day remember all the indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidual offices of friendſhip to his members, and will mention much that themſelves never minded. <hi>And they ſhall ſay, when ſaw we thee an hungred,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ver. 37.</note> 
               <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. That all acts of love and pitty towards his rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions (even the leaſt and loweſt) ſhall be interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted as a ſpecial kindneſſe ſhewed unto himſelf, <hi>In as</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ver. 40.</note> 
               <hi>much as you have done it to one of the leaſt of theſe my bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, you have done it unto me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. And the recompence ſhall be exceeding great. <hi>Then ſhall the King ſay, Come ye bleſſed of my Father, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herit</hi>
               <note place="margin">Verſe 34. 46.</note> 
               <hi>the Kingdom prepared for you. And the Righteous ſhall go into eternal life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>3</label> I will conclude this Doctrine (and this firſt part of my Text) with a double ſhort Exhortati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            <p>Firſt, to real friendlineſſe both unto Chriſt, and to all thoſe who peculiarly belong unto him. Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe ye ſaw Chriſt ſitting in a chaire of Majeſty, and
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:133592:25"/> heard him ſpeaking thus in the audience of all the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants on earth, Who is on my ſide! Let all my faithful friends gather themſelves before me: In this caſe would not multitudes come in with pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſions and proteſtations of love? Now it is thus in truth: for our Lord looketh from heaven, and conſidereth exactly who are his friends, and who are not. Therefore bethink your ſelves what you will do. And if you be content to come in to Chriſt as faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful friends, then befriend (for his ſake,) <hi>thoſe eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal. 6. 10.</note> 
               <hi>who are of his houſhold,</hi> for this will be obſerved and rewarded. <hi>Therefore my beloved, be ye ſtedfaſt and</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 15. 58.</note> 
               <hi>unmovable, alwayes abounding in the work of the Lord, for as much as you know that your labour is not in vaine in the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, to beware of all kinds of doubling and hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie both in the profeſſion and practice of love, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther towards Chriſt or faithful Chriſtians.</p>
            <p>It is the admonition of the Apoſtle, <hi>Let love be</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 12. 9.</note> 
               <hi>without diſſimulation.</hi> And the Doctrine is a ſtrong Argument to back it, becauſe of the notice which our Saviour taketh thereof. Chriſt himſelf by this conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration moveth ſincerity in all ſervices, whether of <hi>piety towards God,</hi> or <hi>charity towards men,</hi> becauſe an eye<note place="margin">Mat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h. 6. 4, 6.</note> from heaven doth eſpie whatſoever is done on earth with greateſt ſecrecy.</p>
            <p>This motive will be the more prevalent, if we minde Chriſt, who as the Judge of all men, will <hi>manifeſt and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke 12 1, 2. 2 Cor. 5. 9, 10.</note> their ſervices according to their nature and manner of performance.</p>
            <p>The ſecond part of my Text followeth; in the hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling whereof I ſhall be the ſhorter, becauſe I have been ſo large in the former.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Lazarus ſleepeth.</hi> In the diviſion of the Text there were three things noted thence; which I ſhall ſpeak
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:133592:26"/> unto very briefly, in three points of Doctrine.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>1</label> 1. <hi>That ſuch who are Chriſts, and his peoples friends, are ſubject to death.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This word [<hi>Sleepeth</hi>] is by our Evangeliſt himſelf thus<note place="margin">Verſe 13. Verſe 14.</note> expounded, <hi>Jeſus ſpake of his death:</hi> and it is added, <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus ſaith to them plainly, Lazarus is dead.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is no need of Scripture quotations here, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe experiences from age to age every where give in ſufficient proof of this Truth. When the Apoſtle<note place="margin">Heb. 11. 13.</note> had particularized many Worthies as examples of faith and holineſſe, he addeth theſe words, <hi>All theſe died.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſons. </seg>
               </label> The reaſons are not only,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Becauſe of <hi>Adams</hi> ſin tranſmitted, <hi>Sin entereth into the world, and death by ſin;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 5. 12.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. And by reaſon of Gods determination, with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference to his own glory, many wayes to be manifeſted in the conſequence of death, <hi>It is appointed unto men once to die, and after this the judgement,</hi> (For upon theſe<note place="margin">Heb. 9 27.</note> accounts the wicked who are Chriſts enemies do die alſo)</p>
            <p>But there are peculiar Reaſons wherefore Chriſts and the Churches friends do die.</p>
            <p>I will not here ſpeak unto that which was extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary in this death of <hi>Lazarus;</hi> viz. <hi>for the glory of God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Verſe 15.</note> that the <hi>Son of God might be glorified thereby,</hi> and for the <hi>ſakes of them who ſhould beleeve,</hi> upon the obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on<note place="margin">Ver. 4.</note> of Chriſts power in a miraculous raiſing him from the dead)</p>
            <p>I will only inſtance in thoſe ends which God intends in a way more ordinary, with reſpect unto his people themſelves.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Sometimes that they may be ſecured from common calamities coming upon the world. As men do houſe their cattel before the ſtorme falleth; Thus God takes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way<note place="margin">Iſa. 57. 1.</note> the <hi>righteous from the evil to come,</hi> wherof the caſe of <hi>Joſiah</hi> is a famous inſtance.<note place="margin">2 Chro. 34. 28.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:133592:26"/>2. That they may reſt <hi>from their labours,</hi> both of ſervice<note place="margin">Rev. 14. 13.</note> and ſuffering, when their task and exerciſes are over; when their work is done, and the Lord hath ſufficiently proved and purged them by variety of providences, both croſſe and comfortable, in this world, then he calleth them off this ſtage, and cauſeth their departure hence.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That they might enjoy immediate communion with Chriſt in heaven, which is <hi>farre better</hi> then the beſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition<note place="margin">Phil. 1. 23. Heb. 12. 23.</note> attainable in this life; and that their <hi>ſpirits might be made perfect</hi> in glory, before the day of the general Reſurrection, when their ſouls and bodies ſhall be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>united.</p>
            <p>There are many profitable Uſes to be made of this Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine,<note place="margin">Application.</note> which I ſhall only point at.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 1. Therefore natural death is not the greateſt evil, neither are thoſe comforts whereof death doth deprive the beſt good; becauſe it is abſurd to imagine that the moſt godly ſhold undergo the heavieſt evils, and be ſtript of the chiefeſt comforts. This inference is obvious, and might be uſefully enlarged. But I muſt forbear.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 2. Therefore death is not alwayes to be looked upon, as a demonſtration of Gods anger againſt them who die: neither is any ſickneſſe bringing death, to be judged a ſigne of divine wrath and ſeverity. <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarus</hi>
               <note place="margin">Verſe 3.</note> Chriſts friend died, and it was ſaid before, <hi>He whom thou loveſt, is ſick.</hi> This is alledged as the reaſon of the death of <hi>Jeroboams</hi> childe, becauſe <hi>there was ſome goodneſſe in him.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Kings 14. 13.</note> 
               <hi>Hezekiah</hi> was ſick unto death; and it's conjectured, that his diſeaſe was the Plague, both becauſe of the ſwelling mentioned, and the medicine adviſed. <hi>Let them take</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 38. 21.</note> 
               <hi>a lump of figs, and lay it for a plaſter upon the boile;</hi> And how ſad <hi>Jobs</hi> condition was, I need not to relate, who yet (according to Gods own teſtimony) was a man of incomparable piety: <hi>Satan ſmote</hi> Job <hi>with ſore boiles, from</hi>
               <note place="margin">Job 1. 8. &amp; 2. 3. Job 2. 7, 8.</note> 
               <hi>the ſole of the foot unto his crown. And he took him a potſheard to ſcrape himſelfe withall, and he late down among the aſhes.</hi> This I do rather note, 1. Becauſe people are ſubject to cenſure ſeverely thoſe who undergo unuſual
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:133592:27"/> afflictions. <hi>When the</hi> Barbarians <hi>ſaw the venomous beaſt</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 8. 4.</note> 
               <hi>hang on</hi> Pauls <hi>hand, they ſaid among themſelves, No doubt this man is a murtherer, vengeance ſuffereth not him to live.</hi> 2. Becauſe by this uncharitable cenſoriouſneſſe, men do ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe themſelves unto Gods diſpleaſure. Hence it was, that the Lord thus ſpake unto <hi>Eliphaz the Temanite, My wrath is</hi>
               <note place="margin">Job 42. 7.</note> 
               <hi>kindled againſt thee, and againſt thy two friends, for you have not ſpoken of me the thing that is right.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 3. Therefore Gods people ſhould the rather hold up with hope, comfort, and patience under all ſorts of their ſufferings here, becauſe their death (which is certain) will put a period, an end unto all. Though the Sea<note place="margin">Nubecula eſt, &amp; citò tranſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit.</note> be ſtormy, yet the voyage is ſhort, we ſhall ere long come ſafe to ſhoare. For <hi>this cauſe we faint not, though the outward man periſh</hi> (ſuppoſe rotting and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſavoury,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 4. 16, 17.</note> &amp;c.) <hi>for this light affliction is but for a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Do you not remember how the holy Martyr com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted his fellow-ſufferer, (<hi>viz.</hi>) that death would cure the one of his blindneſſe, and the other of his lameneſs? And doubtleſſe in this ſenſe, it may be ſaid ſafely, that death unto the godly is the beſt Phyſician, curing them perfectly of all diſeaſes whatſoever. Therefore chear up, ye Saints of God, under all your grievances, upon the thought of death. Say to your ſelves, as the good Martyr did, <hi>But one stile or two more, and then I am at my journeys end.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 4. Therefore Gods ſervants ſhould be the more induſtrious in doing all the good which poſſibly they can, with ſpeed, becauſe they muſt die, and death will take them off their work. This is <hi>Solomons</hi> inference, <hi>What<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever thine hand findeth to do, do it with thy might; for there</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 9. 10.</note> 
               <hi>is no work, nor device, nor knowledge, nor wiſdome in the grave whither thou goeſt.</hi> How did our Saviour beſtirre him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, <hi>when he knew that his houre was come?</hi> What a great deal<note place="margin">Joh. 13. 1.</note> of good work did he then diſpatch in a ſhort time? And it ſeemeth to be the reaſon, why <hi>Paul</hi> at <hi>Troas</hi> preached till <hi>midnight, becauſe he was ready to depart on the morrow.</hi> The<note place="margin">Acts 20. 7.</note>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:133592:27"/> nearer unto the center, the ſwifter is the motion. Famous Doctor <hi>Sibbs</hi> would ſay, Could we ſuppoſe ſorrow in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, this would be our ſorrow there, that we did no more work for God, before we came thither to receive ſo great wages.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 5. Therefore we all ſhould be perſwaded, to improve our Chriſtian friends, both Miniſters and others<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> in all their gifts, graces and experiences, ſo much as may be, and that with ſpeed, becauſe they muſt die: Upon this ground the Prophet <hi>Zachary</hi> quickeneth obedience, <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord of hoſts, Turne ye now</hi>
               <note place="margin">Zach. 1. 4, 5.</note> 
               <hi>from your evil wayes,—Your fathers where are they? And the Prophets, do they live for ever?</hi> Our Saviour is often in this exhortation, having foretold his own de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture, <hi>Yet a little while is the light with you, walk while</hi>
               <note place="margin">John 12. 35. Eph. 5. 8. Mat. 5. 16. John 5. 35.</note> 
               <hi>you have the light.</hi> As all godly ones are called <hi>light:</hi> So Miniſters are <hi>the lights of the world;</hi> John <hi>was a burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and a ſhining light:</hi> Beloved, death will blow out theſe your candles, and your Torches; therefore while they live, while they give out their ſhine and their light, make a profitable uſe of them, to Gods honour and your own ſouls welfare.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 6. Therefore I hence exhort all the friends of Chriſt, to prepare themſelves for death, and to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine upon their Spirits a prepared poſture for natures diſſolution. Although I know, that they being united unto Chriſt, and reconciled to God through him, they<note place="margin">Rev. 14. 13.</note> ſhall undoubtedly (whenſoever they die) be tranſlated from earth to heaven: yet there is ſomething more to<note place="margin">Luke 16. 22.</note> be minded by Chriſtians, that they may be ready to die. How much might be comprized in <hi>Jobs</hi> expreſſion, <hi>All</hi>
               <note place="margin">Job 14. 14.</note> 
               <hi>the dayes of mine appointed time will I wait until my change ſhall come?</hi> I ſhall not undertake to diſcover; but I deſire to leave theſe foure words of advice, in the boſomes of Chriſtians, in tendency unto their preparation for death. 1. Seek well grounded aſſurance of your intereſt in Chriſt, and of undoubted title unto heaven, through him. This foundation being laid, <hi>Paul</hi> could triumph
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:133592:28"/> over death,—<hi>Oh death, where is thy ſting? thanks be to</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 15 55.</note> 
               <hi>God, who hath given us victory through Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> And <hi>Simeon</hi> could ſing when ready to die, <hi>Now letteſt thou thy</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 2. 19, 30.</note> 
               <hi>ſervant depart in peace; For mine eyes have ſeen thy ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi> Whereas there are ſad ſhiverings upon ſome gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious hearts, when death looketh in at the windows, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they queſtion their admiſſion into heaven, upon na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures diſſolution.</p>
            <p>2. Take heed of all ſcandalous ſinnes, ſinnes againſt conſcience, the commiſſion whereof may blemiſh Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and lie as blocks of offence in the wayes of others. It is conceived by ſome Divines, that in this regard Saint <hi>Paul</hi> died with the more confidence, becauſe after his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion he was no way ſcandalous: <hi>I have fought the</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Tim. 4. 7. 8.</note> 
               <hi>good fight, and I have kept the faith, and henceforth is laid up for me a Crown of righteouſneſſe.</hi> Whereas <hi>Peter</hi> having diſhonoured Chriſt, diſgraced his profeſſion, wounded his own conſcience, and prejudiced others (how farre we know not) by his fearful, threefold deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al; was ſo full of perplexity, that Chriſt ſaw cauſe (before<note place="margin">Joh. 21. 15, 19</note> the foretelling of his death) to confirme his heart in help<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on the diſcovery of his ſincere love, notwithſtanding that ſad offenſive Apoſtacy. Broken bones, though knit, will ake towards change of weather. And the remembrance of ſcandalous miſcariages, may occaſion anguiſh in the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomes of dying Saints.</p>
            <p>3. Settle your outward eſtate and concernments, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to divine prudence and holy principles, remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring that you muſt be accountable unto the Lord, (whoſe <hi>ſtewards</hi> you are) how you diſpoſe of the things of this life<note place="margin">Luke. 16. 2.</note> with which he hath entruſted you. This was Gods own ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice unto <hi>Hezekiah. Thus ſaith the Lord, ſet thine houſe i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſay 38. 1.</note> 
               <hi>order, for thou ſhalt die.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Many good people deare unto God, upon this neglect are leſſe comfortable to themſelves, and leſſe ſerviceabl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> unto others upon their death-beds, becauſe they ſuſpe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the many ſad conſequences of their not endeavouring t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> prevent ſinne and trouble by an orderly ſetling of all the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> earthly enjoyments.</p>
            <pb n="45" facs="tcp:133592:28"/>
            <p>4. Leave with gracious gravity and ſeriouſneſſe, charges<note place="margin">Appropinquante morte multò es divinior.</note> and convictions upon the conſciences of your neareſt rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, that Chriſt, heaven and their immortal ſoules may be principally cared for. Warne your friends to beware of the ſinnes of the times, and of their own inclinations. Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate your experiences for future profit, prudently. Here I might expatiate upon the examples of <hi>Jacob</hi> bleſſing<note place="margin">Gen. 49. Deut. 31. 2. &amp; 32. &amp; 33. Joſh. 23. 1, 2. &amp; 24. 1.—Joh. 13. 1. &amp; 14. &amp; 15. &amp; 16. &amp; 17.</note> his ſonnes, when on his death-bed; of <hi>Moſes</hi> and of <hi>Joſhua</hi> their plaine dealing with <hi>Iſrael,</hi> when ready to die; yea, and of Chriſt himſelf: But I am neceſſitated to abbreviate theſe things with this hearty requeſt, that my friendly, faithfull counſell in theſe things may not be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten.</p>
            <p>And do not (I pray you,) do not deferre theſe things, for death may ſteale upon you ſuddenly, unexpectedly, as a man falls aſleep ſometimes, when he thought not of it.</p>
            <p>This lets in the next point.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Doct.</hi> 2. That Chriſts friends by death, do fall aſleep. The Protomartyr <hi>Stephen</hi> his death is thus expreſſed: <hi>He</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 7 60. 1 Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 15. 16, 18, 20, 51.</note> 
               <hi>fell aſleep.</hi> And the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> doth often in the fif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth Chapter of his firſt Epiſtle to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> atteſt this truth.</p>
            <p>This ſleep is not to be applied unto the ſoule after its<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 12. 7. Luke 23. 43. Phil. 1. 23. Heb. 12. 23.</note> departure from the body (as ſome fondly dreame;) for it goeth <hi>to God</hi> immediately, forth-with <hi>enjoyeth fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip with Chriſt,</hi> and <hi>becometh perfect;</hi> But it belongs to the dead body, laid in the grave, which in this regard<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Mr. <hi>Calamy</hi> his Sermon upon Acts 7. 60.</note> is called a ſleeping place. I ſhall not dilate upon the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblance betwixt death and ſleep, which is fully done by others: But I will only touch upon two things which are here intended. 1. Death is a ſleep unto the godly, becauſe thereby they are laid to reſt. There is a<note place="margin">Verſe 13.</note> 
               <hi>taking of reſt by ſleep. They ſhall reſt in their beds,</hi> ſaith the Prophet, ſpeaking of the death of righteous ones. <hi>And</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 57. 2.</note> 
               <hi>they reſt from their labours,</hi> (ſo ſaith the Spirit) <hi>who die in the Lord.</hi> 2. Becauſe their bodies ſhall be raiſed, as<note place="margin">Rev. 14. 15.</note> men are awakened out of ſleep: This is expreſſed in the words which immediately follow the Text: <hi>Our
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:133592:29"/> friend Lazarus ſleepeth; but I go that I may awake him out of ſleep.</hi> And the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> is much upon this Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taphor,<note place="margin">Cor. 15.</note> in that place where he undertaketh to prove the Reſurrection.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 1. Therefore true beleevers, real Saints ſhould not be afraid to die.</p>
            <p>I grant that death unto nature is the King of feares, and it hath its poiſonous ſting with which it will wound the wicked, whom it doth uſher into hell. This (with many other uſeful truths relating unto death) is admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably<note place="margin">Dr. <hi>Tuckney</hi> his Sermons upon 1. Cor. 15. 55.</note> laid open of late by a worthy ſervant of Chriſt; and it would be a digreſſion, if I ſhould undertake that diſcovery: But I only move Gods people, to arme them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves againſt the ſinking feare of death, becauſe unto them it is no worſe then falling aſleep. And indeed there is great need of this counſel among Gods own ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants every where, who like fooliſh children are afraid to put off their cloathes, and go to bed in a dark chamber.<note place="margin">As <hi>Baxter</hi> in his Saints e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting reſt.</note> Herein the forementioned Authour, and others, have adminiſtred much good help, in which regard I may be ſilent.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 2. Neither let us mourne immoderately becauſe of the death of our Chriſtian friends; ſeeing they are on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fallen aſleep. When our Saviour had ſpoken the<note place="margin">Verſe 12.</note> words of the Text, <hi>Then ſaid his Diſciples, If he ſleep, he ſhall do well.</hi> And by the argument the Apoſtle ſeeks to prevaile with the <hi>Theſſalonians,</hi> that they might not mourne exceſſively upon ſuch occaſion. For <hi>thoſe who ſleep in Jeſus, will God bring with him.</hi> Then he ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth,<note place="margin">1 Theſ. 4. 13, 14 17, 18.</note> 
               <hi>We ſhall be ever with the Lord; wherefore comfort one another with theſe words.</hi> Love moveth joy, when our weak, weary, pained, diſeaſed friends are fallen into a ſound ſweet ſleep. This conſideration therefore ſhould cheere our drooping ſpirits, in reference unto godly friends, who died in the Lord. Let us minde this the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, becauſe God who propoundeth this ground of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, obſerveth both when we have need of this cordial, and alſo what improvement we make thereof, as it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:133592:29"/> in the next and laſt Doctrine, which remaines to be handled.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Doct.</hi> 3. The Lord knoweth when his own and his Churches friends do fall aſleep by death. As Chriſt, though now at a bodily diſtance from <hi>Bethany,</hi> the place of <hi>Lazarus</hi> his abode, yet told his Diſciples of his death, <hi>Our friend</hi> Lazarus <hi>ſleepeth.</hi> As God ſpake this to <hi>Joſhuah, My</hi>
               <note place="margin">Joſh. 1. 2.</note> 
               <hi>ſervant</hi> Moſes <hi>is dead.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This truth may be concluded ſtrongly by theſe arguments.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reaſ.</hi> 1. Becauſe Chriſt hath the <hi>keys of death</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rev. 1. 18.</note> in keeping; the ſoule cannot be let out of the body, without his leave. And he knoweth all his own grants.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reaſ.</hi> 2. Becauſe he alſo hath power in heaven, keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing (as it were) the gate hereof, into which none can enter without his allowance. This is manifeſt by his promiſe to the penitent thief: <hi>This day thou ſhalt be with me in Paradiſe.</hi> Therefore he exactly obſerveth, when any perſons or perſon<note place="margin">Luke 23. 43.</note> hath admiſſion thither.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 1. Hence the deity of Chriſt may be proved un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deniably; for though there be thouſands dying hourely in the ſeveral places of the world, yet Chriſt knows particularly, 1. Both their qualification, whether his friends and his Churches friends, or no. 2. And the time, when every one of them giveth up the ghoſt. As the inſtance under diſcourſe doth evince. 1. He underſtood infallibly that <hi>Lazarus</hi> was a faithful friend, both unto himſelfe and his ſervants: <hi>Our friend</hi> Lazarus. 2. And though he was not corporeally preſent with <hi>Lazarus</hi> in the place where he died, yet he knew without any creature-intelligence, that now he was fallen aſleep by death.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 2. This truth ſpeaketh manifold comforts unto Gods children: For, 1. This hints his reſpect to them; <hi>Precious in</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 116. 15. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>the ſight of the Lord is the death of his Saints.</hi> He will not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer any of them to loſe life without his ſpecial obſervation thereof, together with cauſes and concomitants therein conſiderable.</p>
            <pb n="48" facs="tcp:133592:30"/>
            <p>2. It ſuggeſts his care of every ſoule; when it removeth out of the body the place of its habitation, it ſhall not miſcary or be loſt through Chriſts regardleſſeneſſe. Though thouſands of devils may watch to intercept the ſoule, yet Chriſt who obſerveth when it leaveth the body, will un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly, according to his charge and promiſe, ſecure its Paſſages to glory. This is a Cordial to the pooreſt Chriſtian, for there is no reſpect of perſons with the Lord. <hi>It came to paſſe that the beggar died, and was carried by the Angels into</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 16. 22.</note> Abrahams <hi>boſome.</hi> And,</p>
            <p>3. It may relieve the ſad hearts of godly ones, mourning for their loſſe in the death of their dear Chriſtian friends; for their God and Saviour is quickly and fully acquainted with this their affliction: he ſaw when our beloved relations breathed out their laſt gaſp. Queſtionleſſe it cheered <hi>Hagar,</hi> when ſhe underſtood that God took notice, when the bottle was empty; and heard the cry of <hi>Iſhmael,</hi> becauſe he wanted water. And you may be<note place="margin">Gen. 21. 16, 17.</note> confident, that Chriſt who underſtands when your Parents, your Paſtors, your yoakfellows, your friends die; he doth alſo conſider what counſel, what comfort, what ſupports, what ſupplies, what encouragements you be deprived of by meanes of their death. Is not this a choice Cordial to Gods children, that <hi>their heavenly Father knoweth they need ſuch things?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 6. 32.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 3. Laſtly, this Doctrine yields matter of ſeaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able and needful admonition. Therefore upon the death of Gods ſervants, we ſhould ſeek after ſuch diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions, as may be pleaſing unto his Majeſty, who obſerveth together with ſuch providences, how we are affected there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with.</p>
            <p>Here then I would adviſe two particulars, wherein I in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat the Lord to make us ſerious.</p>
            <p n="1">1. To be rightly affected with ſuch like diſpenſations, laying to heart the publick loſſe ſuſtained, when the friends of Chriſt and his ſervants are taken away by death. The Lord obſerveth and complaineth, when peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple do not herein anſwer his expectation, <hi>The righteous
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:133592:30"/> periſheth, and no man layeth it to heart.</hi> And our love unto<note place="margin">Eſay 57. 1.</note> the publick, together with the conſideration of the great uſe of ſuch perſons, would help forward our humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation in ſuch caſes. You heard before that they are friends to Chriſt, and much befriended by Chriſt, yea, that they are lovers of the cauſe and people of God. Now is not the death of ſuch to be bewailed? When <hi>Elijah</hi> went up by a whirlewinde to heaven, <hi>Eliſha</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 King. 1. 11, 12</note> 
               <hi>ſaw it, and he cryed, My father, my father, the Charet of Iſrael, and the horſemen thereof.</hi> And when <hi>Eliſha</hi> was<note place="margin">2 Kin. 13. 11, 14</note> ſick, <hi>Joaſh</hi> (though not a good man) <hi>wept over him, and ſaid, Oh my father, my father, the Charet of Iſrael, and the horſemen thereof.</hi> Becauſe they beleeved that the publick ſafety depended much upon the intereſt of god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly men in God, therefore their death was thus lament<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. And truly ſuch friends of God are the chief ſtakes in the hedge, and maine pillars in the building, both of Church and Common-wealth. Therefore in ſuch caſes, it may well become us to imitate the <hi>devout men, who</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 8. 2.</note> 
               <hi>carryed</hi> Stephen <hi>to his grave, and made great lamentation for him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. To imitate the deceaſed Saints in their graces and holy converſation; we ſhould lay their lives, as ſo many faire copies before our eyes, and labour to write after them, by conſciencious imitation. The Apoſtle having given in a catalogue of Old-Teſtament-beleevers, who in their ſeveral places and ages did worthily, he earneſtly perſwadeth Chriſtians to be followers of them. And<note place="margin">Heb. 11. com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared with Heb. 12. 1.</note> ſeeing God hath given us to behold the beauty of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe, and the power of godlineſſe in their courſes, it will much aggravate our ſinne, if we labour not to be like them.</p>
            <p>This leadeth me to that which you all look for, (<hi>viz</hi>) to ſpread before you the exemplary life of Maſter <hi>Jeremiah Whitaker</hi> the late Paſtor of this place, whoſe Funeral hath occaſioned this great Aſſembly and my Sermon; in refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence unto whom, that I may ſpeak unto your edification, I will (with the change of one word only) undertake
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:133592:31"/> my Text again, <hi>Our friend</hi> Whitaker <hi>ſleepeth.</hi> And truly I am very confident, that if Jeſus Chriſt was here in his bodily preſence among us, he would not be unwilling to ſpeak theſe words, <hi>Our friend</hi> Whitaker <hi>ſleepeth.</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I begin my Narrative, I crave leave to premiſe this, (<hi>viz.</hi>) that though (in ſome reſpects) I know a more meet man might have been choſen for this work; who could have done it more exactly and gracefully: yet I acknowledge that my ſelfe am not the unmeeteſt, conſidering my long and familiar acquaintance with him, eſpecially if this be added, (<hi>viz.</hi>) that in Summer was twelve-moneth—I riding with him unto <hi>Tunbridge</hi> Wells, he was pleaſed to give me the Hiſtory of his life, from his youth till that time; and ſince that time, it is well known to many, that no one hath had more frequent and familiar converſe with him, then my ſelfe. Oh how often, and with what meltings hath he pour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed forth his heart into my boſome, in reference to all concernments, perſonal, relative, private, publick, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable and uncomfortable, which have deeply affected him! My forgetfulneſſe will neceſſitate the omiſſion of many things, and my faithfulneſſe with prudence com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand me to conceal much of that, which to my heart ſpake aloud his great goodneſſe and high commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. I will ſuggeſt the ſum of what I judge moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient to diſcover, in the report whereof my ſoul deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth (I hope) to honour God, and to profit his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</p>
            <p>He was borne at <hi>Wakefield</hi> in <hi>Yorkſhire</hi> in the yeare 1599. When he was ſixteen years old, he was ſent to <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge,</hi> and placed a Sizar in <hi>Sydney</hi> Colledge, where he was much valued for his pregnant parts, and Scholarſhip. At twenty yeares of age, having commenced Batchelor of Arts, he was ſent unto <hi>Okeham</hi> (the chief Town in <hi>Rutland<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire</hi>) to teach the free-School there. About foure yeares after he married <hi>Chephtzibah</hi> the daughter of Maſter <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam Peachy</hi> Miniſter of <hi>Okeham,</hi> an eminent linguiſt, a godly man, and (as I am informed) a painful Preacher of
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:133592:31"/> the Goſpel, who dearly loved, and highly valued Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Whitaker,</hi> from his firſt acquaintance to his end; whoſe affections to him, wrought on the marriage be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt him and his daughter. By whom God gave him foure ſonnes and three daughters; one ſonne died at <hi>Cambridge,</hi> two are ordained Miniſters, and the other is to be educated for the Miniſtery. Having ſtayed about ſeven years at <hi>Okeham,</hi> he was removed unto a Paſtoral charge at <hi>Stretton</hi> in the ſame County, where he continued thirteen yeares, from whence he was called to <hi>Mary Magdalen Bermondſey,</hi> (with the approbation of many godly Miniſters, whom he conſulted in the caſe) where he after twelve yeares ſpent in his Miniſterial charge fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed his courſe upon the firſt day of <hi>June,</hi> 1654. and fell aſleep in Jeſus. He was betwixt fifty five and fifty ſix yeares old when the Lord was pleaſed to take him unto himſelf. He was buried in <hi>Bermondſey</hi> Church <hi>June</hi> the ſixth, with expreſſions of much love from a very great multitude of godly perſons, both Miniſters and others of ſeveral ranks and conditions, who attended his corps to the grave. By reaſon of much ſtudy, and manifold imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in his calling, he was filled with various bodily diſtempers from his youth. In the latter part of his time, he was for ſundry yeares exerciſed frequently with the painful diſeaſes of the gowt and of the ſtone. Notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the reiteration of theſe tormenting paines, he at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended upon his Miniſtery both at home and abroad, while he was able to creep into the Pulpit, or to crawle unto the Congregation.</p>
            <p>But about the beginning of <hi>November</hi> laſt paſt, the vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent paine of the ſtone did in ſuch meaſure and manner ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt him, that from that time, he continued Gods priſoner in his bed, or chamber, till he was ſet free by a long expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed death. Moſt Phyſicians in the City were conſulted, and were from time to time very ready to ſerve him with their advice: who did unanimouſly conclude, his ſharp paines to proceed originally from an ulcer in the kidneys, but im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately from an ulcer in the neck of the bladder, cauſed
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:133592:32"/> by a continual flux of ulcerous matter dropping down up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that part. And by reaſon of the acuteneſſe and quickneſs of the ſenſe there, his paines were almoſt altogether in that place, though the fountaine of them was from the kidneys. Towards his end, (about two moneths) the paine grew more extreame, yet divine indulgence vouchſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fed ſome abatements and intermiſſions, both in the night &amp; day. As his death drew nigh, his fits of pain were more fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent, either every half hour, or many times every quarter, yea, two or three times in a quarter of an hour, wherby na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture being quite ſpent he died in the Lord. After his death, Maſter <hi>Holiard</hi> opend his body in the preſence of D<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Cox,</hi> D<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Micklethwaite,</hi> and D<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Bevoyr,</hi> (ſome other more anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Doctors would have been there, if either their being out of Town, or preſent urgent occaſions had not hindred) who found both his kidneys full of ulcers, and one was ſwelled to an extreame bigneſſe, by the abundance of pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rulent matter in it. Upon the neck of his bladder, they found a ſtone, (which was about an inch and an half long, and one inch broad, weighing above two ownces, when firſt taken out, and withal, an ulcer which was gangrened, and this was judged the cauſe of his death. All other parts of his body were found firme and ſound. Now that which I ſhall relate concerning him in all thoſe places and changes of life wherein God diſpoſed of him, I will caſt under the ſeveral heads upon which I did diſcourſe in my Sermon. And this method I do the rather reſolve upon, both becauſe it beſt ſuits with mine own thoughts, and may prove the moſt profitable unto them who ſhall be pleaſed to read the Sermon, when they perceive the maine parts thereof, applied and verefied in this providential Text, <hi>Our friend</hi> Whitaker <hi>ſleepeth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The firſt Head, <hi>He loved Christ.</hi> He loved Chriſt, 1. Quickly. 2. Strongly. 3. Conſtantly. The Lord did win his heart unto himſelfe, while he was a Scholar at <hi>Wakerfield,</hi> where he had his education. For then and there his affections did flow out towards thoſe who were moſt religiouſly diſpoſed, with whom he went frequently eight or ten Miles to heare a wakening-ſoul-warming Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:133592:32"/> and he was wont to joyne with them in prayers and other holy exerciſes. And being able to take Sermon-notes, both underſtandingly and largely, he was very helpful to Chriſtians in the repeating of what they had publickly heard, being from his childhood ful of affections in whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever buſineſſe he undertook. Thus this plant did both bloſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome and put forth fruit quickly, which providence did af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards make a very fruitful tree. For the more cleare diſcovery of his abundant love to Jeſus Chriſt, I will give theſe demonſtrations.</p>
            <p>Firſt, from his early, and conſtant vigorous workings of heart towards the calling and work of the Miniſtery; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he alwayes conceived, that therein a Chriſtian might enjoy moſt fellowſhip with Chriſt, and do him the beſt<note place="margin">Joh. 21. 15, 17.</note> ſervice. And he conſidered Chriſts ſpeech to <hi>Peter, If thou love me, feed my ſheep, feed my lambs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here I judge theſe particulars very worthy of conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation. 1. That while he was a Grammar-Scholar, this calling he choſe; and though his father endeavoured of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten and earneſtly to divert his thoughts from the Miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, yet he was unmovable in his deſires to be a Miniſter. 2. That he never repented of this his choice, but would all his life long, upon all occaſions, <hi>magnifie this his office.</hi> I have many times heard him ſpeak theſe words, <hi>I had much ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 11. 13.</note> 
               <hi>be a Preacher of the Goſpel, then an Emperour.</hi> And when a motion was once made to him for a Maſterſhip in the Univerſity, he readily returned this anſwer, <hi>My heart doth more deſire to be a conſtant Preacher, then to be the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of any College in the world.</hi> 3. That when he was moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned to marry her whom God afterwards made his wife; he was the rather inclined to accept the motion, becauſe ſhe was daughter to a pious, painful, learned Miniſter of the Goſpel, and would occaſionally tell his friends, that he was the better pleaſed with his choice, becauſe of that relation. 4. That he was never ſo well pleaſed with any imployment, as that of his Miniſtery. In the Pulpit he ſtill was like a fiſh in the water. Though many times he went halting and full of paine thither; yet he would not manifeſt any ſenſe of diſtemper, while he was there.
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:133592:33"/> How often hath he gone upon crutches unto the Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of his own people, to fulfil his Miniſtery! yea, once (at leaſt of my knowledge) he adventured to Preach at <hi>Michaels Cornhil,</hi> when he was ſcarce able to get into the Pulpit, and his friends with much difficulty helped him out of the Church homeward. 5. That when he was by extreame paines taken off from his Miniſtery, he would ſometimes profeſſe unto ſome ſpecial friends, that the paine felt was not ſo grievous to his Spirit, as his inability (by reaſon thereof) to manage his wonted work. Many times theſe were his words, <hi>If I could but Preach, I ſhould be much better.</hi> And he would rejoyce with chearfulneſſe, and thankfulneſſe, when in the times of his weakneſſe, he found not himſelfe more diſtempered by his preaching, and would mention ſuch experiences as arguments to move his friends to yield unto his preaching, when they did diſſwade it as prejudicial 6. He did zealouſly, upon all occaſions, both in publick and private defend the office of a Goſpel Miniſtery, and eſpecially amongſt thoſe perſons, and in ſuch places, where (as he conceived) there was moſt need. This paſſage fell from him with affection, in one of his morning Lectures at <hi>Weſtminſter:</hi> Though I have read and heard of ſome good men, who unadviſedly in their paſſion have perſecuted the perſons of ſome godly Miniſters, (as <hi>Aſa was angry with the Seer, and caſt him into priſon</hi>) yet I never knew, I never read, nor heard of any godly perſon, who did dare to oppoſe the calling of the Miniſtery. And whereas at the end of his Sermon, a ſouldier (expreſſing himſelfe diſſatisfied with the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon) came to him in private and asked him, whether he meant this Miniſtery of <hi>England,</hi> as now conſtituted? he returned this anſwer, <hi>Although I will not juſtifie the calling of every individual Miniſter in the Church of</hi> England (<hi>as you dare not juſtifie the Saintſhip of every member in your in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dependant Congregations</hi>) yet I will be ready when and where you pleaſe to <hi>maintaine the office and calling of</hi> En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glands <hi>Miniſtery at this day.</hi> 7. And that he continued unchanged in this his eſtimation of the calling Miniſterial, may be manifeſted by one paſſage in his laſt Will and Teſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tament,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:133592:33"/> (though it was not long) which I will put down in his own words, writ with his own hand: <hi>For my ſon</hi> Jere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miah, <hi>my deſire is, that he be bred a Scholar, and that the Lord would ſpiritualy incline his heart, freely to give up him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to the Lord, to ſerve him in the work of the Miniſtery, which calling and employment (though now deſpiſed) I do e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem above all other in the world, and do commend it to all mine, that if the Lord bleſſe them with ſons, they would com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend this calling to their poſterity.</hi> Before I paſſe from this my firſt demonſtration of his love to Chriſt, I heartily de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, that this may be ſeriouſly conſidered, whether there be not herein much to credit and incourage the Miniſtery of the Goſpel; That a learned man, and ſo eminent for piety, who alſo had throughly ſtudied the Controverſies of the times againſt the Miniſtery, ſhould upon his death-bed, give ſuch a teſtimony unto it, when he daily expected to make up his account before God, and alſo give ſo great incouragement unto his poſterity, to undertake this cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling now, even now when ſuch diſgrace is caſt upon it, and when the Miniſters ſetled maintenance is threatned to be taken from them? And may not thoſe men who know Mr. <hi>Whitaker</hi>'s worth be hereby awed, and moved to take heed how they oppoſe or ſlight that calling of men, whom he (living and dying) judged to be ſo highly honoured by God himſelf? To all this adde, that it was an ordained Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery, which he thus valued, as is evident by theſe two things (as by many living teſtimonies,) <hi>viz.</hi> 1. That he joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the Claſſis whereof he was a member in ordaining Miniſters. 2. That he had an hand in the book lately pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed by the Province of <hi>London</hi> in the defence of ſuch a Miniſtery, not only by aſſent, but alſo by aſſiſtance.</p>
            <p>Secondly, his love to Chriſt was proclaimed, by his un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wearied laboriouſneſſe in his Miniſterial ſervices. 1. While he continued Schoolmaſter at <hi>Okeham,</hi> he undertook a Lec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture there weekly, beſides many Sermons preached occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onally in neighbour Congregations. 2. During his abode at <hi>Stretton,</hi> beſides his Paſtoral imployment twice every Sabbath, his conſtant weekly Preaching at <hi>Okeham,</hi> he was a principal prop to hold up the Lectures in the neighbour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood.
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:133592:34"/> His manner was to ſet apart every holy day (if but one in the week) as a day of ſeeking God, in reference to the neceſſities of the times, and no man was more fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent in aſſiſting in dayes of humiliation in private, both in <hi>Rutland ſhire,</hi> and the adjacent Counties, when ever invited thereto. 3. And ſince Gods good providence brought him to the neighbourhood of <hi>London,</hi> he was <hi>in labours more abundant</hi> (2 Cor. 11. 23.) For the moſt part, his ſet task was foure Sermons weekly, (<hi>viz.</hi>) two at home, and two elſewhere, (<hi>viz.</hi>) at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> and Chriſts Church <hi>London,</hi> or <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> and <hi>Stepney,</hi> (ſince he laid down Chriſts Church Lecture) together with two Sermons eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry quarter at <hi>Michael Cornhil.</hi> Adde hereto his Preaching monethly at the morning-exerciſe, or aſſiſtance on the faſt day at the concluſion thereof, beſides occaſion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Sermons for preparation to the Sacrament at his own place, and at Funerals, both at home and abroad: Yea, I will cloſe up the evidencing of the <hi>labours of his love,</hi> with this true report, (<hi>viz.</hi>) that he would never deny any mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for preaching, and praying, if God gave bodily ability, and other unavoidable occaſions did not neceſſarily hinder. Many week-dayes he preached twice, yea, then when he attended the work of the Aſſembly of Divines, (<hi>viz.</hi>) the morning-exerciſe, either at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> or elſewhere, &amp; af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards in the afternoon. I here remember the commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation which St. <hi>Paul</hi> gave of <hi>Epaphroditus,</hi> in his Epiſtle to the <hi>Philippians; For the work of the Lord he was nigh unto</hi>
               <note place="margin">Phil. 2. 30.</note> 
               <hi>death, not regarding his life.</hi> How farre this is appliable to painful Mr. <hi>Whitaker,</hi> multitudes do well know, yea, many conceive that his painful diſtempers (which haſtened his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moval from us) were cauſed and increaſed by his many con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant labours in this kind. Neither were his Sermons jejune and dry, becauſe thus frequent; but always full of Scripture<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrength, ſavoury &amp; affectionate, as his Auditors will teſtifie.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Such was his love to Chriſt, that his publick Imployments did not take him off from family-duties, nor from more private exerciſes of communion with God. His ordinary courſe was, together with prayers, to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound ſome parts of the holy Scriptures in his own family
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:133592:34"/> twice every day: and beſide other parts of Scripture which he daily read in ſecret, he uſually read over all the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtles in the Greek Teſtament twice every fourtnight: yea when by reaſon of pain and weakneſs he himſelf could not read, he herein imployed others for his help. Hence it was that he was a man mighty in the Scriptures (like un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Apollo, Acts</hi> 18. 24.) as was obſerved by all who con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſed with him. And this courſe he earneſtly commended to the practice of his dearly beloved eldeſt ſon, as an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent means to make him both a ready and a profitable Preacher.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> His courage in Chriſts Cauſe did much commend his love, whereof I will ſuggeſt theſe evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences.</p>
            <p n="1">1. While he lived in <hi>Rutland-ſhire,</hi> he refuſed to read the book allowing of ſports upon the Sabbath, though it was with commands and threatnings preſſed upon him. And when he was called to give in his anſwer, about the collec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion amongſt Miniſters to maintain the War againſt <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> he openly told the Biſhop or Chancellor that his conſcience could not yield thereto. This his anſwer ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing him to great danger both to loſe living and liberty in thoſe times, a neighbour through miſguided love (com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſionating him and his family) payed the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, and ſubſcribed Mr. <hi>Whitakers</hi> name without his knowledge. This he was long ignorant of; and when he heard it, he expreſſed, with many complaints, much grief of heart.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Since our times of woful deſertion and Apoſtaſie both from Goſpel-truths and practices, he would undaunt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly in private conferences and in his publick Miniſtery expreſs his diſlike, yea, deteſtation thereof to the faces of them who too much favoured Errour, Hereſies and rant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing courſes, though he knew that thereby he did run ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zards and procure many frownes. He refuſed to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe the late Engagement, though thereby he was in danger to be taken off from his <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> Lecture. And if his Sermons preached there, upon <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2. 2, 3. (concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:133592:35"/> mens <hi>walking according to the courſe of this world, &amp;c. fulfilling the luſts of the fleſh &amp;c.</hi>) could be collected and publiſhed, thereby it would be manifeſt that M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Whitaker</hi> in love unto his Lord Chriſt, was a man of good metal and magnanimity.</p>
            <p n="3">3. One more private proof of the good mans valiant love to Chriſt I will make bold to inſert; becauſe my ſelf can knowingly atteſt its truth<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Since theſe ſtormy dayes, wherein the liberty and livelihood of Miniſters have been maligned and ſtruck at, he riding with an intimate friend by <hi>Tiburn,</hi> (which he had not known or not obſerved before) demanded what that was? and anſwer being made this is <hi>Tiburn,</hi> where many Malefactors have loſt their lives, he ſtopped his horſe, and uttered theſe words with great affection, <hi>O what a ſhame is it that ſo many thouſands ſhould die for the ſatisfaction of their lusts, and ſo few be found willing to lay down their lives for Chriſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Why ſhould not we in a good Cauſe, and upon a good call, be ready to be hanged for Jeſus Chriſt? It would be ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting honour; and it is a thouſand times better to die for Chriſt, to be hanged, to be burnt for Chriſt, then to die in our beds.</hi> And how much he condemned life, in reſpect un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Chriſt Jeſus, there are many who from his own mouth can witneſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fifthly,</hi> So great was his love unto his God and Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, that he maintained and expreſſed high eſtimations, and honourable thoughts of his Majeſty, when under tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menting providences, nothing being more feared then this, leſt he ſhould do or ſpeak any diſhonours unto his Name. Theſe were ſome breathings of his large love, when through paine he was, as in the fire, and upon the Rack, <hi>Good Lord, keep me from diſhonouring thy Name by impatiency. O, who would not even in burnings have honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able thoughts of God! Who that knoweth thee would not fear thee, O Lord, love thee, and honour thee! Lord, thou giveſt me no cauſe to have any ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d thought of thee! Bleſſed be God, there is nothing of hell in all this. Bleſſed be his Name for Jeſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Chriſt, and the revelation of the everlaſting
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:133592:35"/> Goſpel. Who knoweth the power of thy wrath? If it be ſo heavy upon thy ſervant here, how heavy ſhall it be to all thoſe who ſhall endure it without mixture? Bleſſed be God for the peace of mine inward man, when my outward man is ſo full of trouble. This is a bitter cup, but it is of my Fathers mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and ſhall I not drink it? yea, Lord, through thy ſtrength I will: this is my burthen; and I will beare it.</hi> Upon any abatement of his paines, he was conſtantly much in bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing God, uſing theſe and ſuch like expreſſions<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>O! what a mercy is it that there is any mitigation, any intermiſſion! Lord, make me thankful.</hi> And turning himſelfe towards thoſe who ſtood by, he would ſpeak thus. <hi>O help me to be thankful! O lift up a prayer for me that I may be thankful! O what a mercy is this! How much worſe might this afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on have been! I might have been diſtracted or laid roaring under diſquietneſſe of ſpirit.</hi> By theſe workings of his ſpirit (which my ſelf and others do well remember, and I could heartily wiſh that all the reſt had been recorded) who perceiveth not the ſparklings of his love to God? I will annex one more, which hath much affected my heart, <hi>viz.</hi> theſe words he hath often ſpoken to me; <hi>Brother, through mercy I have not one repining thought against God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now upon all theſe conſiderations, I appeale unto the conſciences of all ingenuous ones, whether there be not ground<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to beleeve, that Chriſt (if here with us) would give him the honour of this compellation, <hi>My loving friend Whitaker.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond head of my Narrative followeth, That <hi>Chriſt loved Mr. Whitaker.</hi> (For as I diſcovered in my Sermon, this love is alwayes mutual.) The diſcovery hereof will be clear upon a double account, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Becauſe of the graces with which he was enriched.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Becauſe of the Comforts with which he was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhed.</p>
            <p>As for the firſt. Love-tokens are real meſſengers of his love who ſendeth them: and what ſurer ſignes of divine love then the graces of the holy Ghoſt? Now of theſe
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:133592:36"/> the Lord had given him, in meaſure, more then ordinary. That which was hinted before in his love to the Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, (expreſſed by laborious, couragious endeavours to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance his praiſe, and to continue communion with him) doth manifeſt that he was very rich in Grace; but there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto I will add five more graces which were very ſhining in his crown.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Tenderneſſe of heart.</hi> Who ever knew man of a more melting frame before God, whether in confeſſions, petitions, or thankſgivings? Is there any one living that can ſay, I have ſometimes joyned with him in Prayer, and he ſhed no teares? How did his own ſinfulneſſe, (though no more then the ordinary imperfections of the faireſt Saints on earth) the evils of the times, and the teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of Gods diſpleaſure breaking out, break his heart into pieces? Truly I beleeve that for the ſpace of many years, he did never come off from the ſerious conſideration of theſe things with dry eyes. And how many thouſands would account it a ſigne of much love from Chriſt, if they could finde ſuch thawings in their frozen breaſts?</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Meekneſſe of ſpirit.</hi> With this precious Jewel he was adorned richly. Who ever ſaw him tranſported by paſſion, on a fire through fooliſh anger, or diſguiſed by diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>content? Though he would be warm for God; yet he was a man of a cool ſpirit, meek, like <hi>Moſes,</hi> in all his own concernments. Among many other manifeſtations here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, this one was remarkable, that when upon warm diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putes with men of diſſenting principles and opinions, his ſpirit was ſo even, that unhanſome provocations would not diſcompoſe him. Hereof I could give inſtances; but I muſt forbear.</p>
            <p n="3">3. For <hi>Patience</hi> he may well be called a ſecond <hi>Job.</hi> Many who ſaw him under his racking pains, ſo frequently reiterated, and ſo long continued, are confident that God did put him, and keep him in his furnace to be a pattern of patience unto poſterity. It's true, he did roar many times till his throat was dry, but who ever heard
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:133592:36"/> him ſpeak one word of murmuring or diſcontent becauſe of Gods afflicting providence? He himſelf indeed would ſometimes through tenderneſſe charge himſelf of impati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ency, becauſe he made a noiſe, whereas that expreſſed on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Natures ſenſibleneſſe, not ſinful frowardneſs. And when (accuſing himſelf in that kinde cauſeleſly) he was minded of Chriſts roarings, though free from all ſin, he would be ſilent. I confeſſe that in deſires to be diſſolved, he would take up <hi>Jobs</hi> complaint: <hi>Wherfore is light given to him that is in miſery, and life unto the bitter in ſoul? Which long for death, but it cometh not, and dig for it more then for hid trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, &amp;c. for my ſighing cometh before I eat, and my roar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings are poured out like waters,</hi> Job 3. 20, 24. But he always concluded with ſubmiſſion unto the good pleaſure of God. When he had been asked how he did? this was frequently his anſwer, <hi>The buſh alwayes burning, but not conſumed; and though my paines be above the ſtrength of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, yet they are not above the ſupports of grace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. The Lord gave him ſo much of the <hi>Spirit of grace and ſupplications,</hi> that his ſoul was never out of tune for that ſervice. Moſt of his words when under torment, were ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly complaints and prayers to God: ſome of them I will record, that they may not be forgotten. <hi>O my God help! Father of mercies pity! Do not contend for ever, conſider my frame, that I am but duſt! My God that hath made hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and earth help me! O give me patience, and inflict what thou wilt! If my patience was more, my pain would be leſſe. Dear Saviour, where are thy bowels! Why doeſt thou make me an aſtoniſhment to my ſelf and others? Why doeſt thou co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver thy ſelf with a thick cloud, that our prayers cannot paſſe? Bleſſed is the man that endureth temptation. Lord, this is a ſad temptation; ſtand by me and ſay, It is enough! Am I not thy ſervant? Conſider, Lord, that I am thy ſervant. O theſe bitter waters of</hi> Marah! <hi>Lord, drop ſweet comfort into theſe bitter waters of</hi> Marah. <hi>O the blood of sprinkling, Lord: Lord, the blood of ſprinkling! That blood which extinguiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the fire of thine anger, O that it might allay my burning pains! I am in a fiery furnace; Lord, be with me, as thou
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:133592:37"/> waſt with the three children, bring me out refined from ſinne. When I have ſailed through the Ocean of theſe paines, and look back, I ſee none of theſe can be wanting. I flie unto thee, O God, hide me under the ſhadow of thy wings till theſe terrible ſtorms be over-paſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. God added <hi>Humility</hi> as a crown to all his other Graces, which did ſhine very bright in the eyes of all who were acquainted with him. Hence it was, that he would converſe familiarly with the pooreſt Chriſtians, and with them who were of low parts for knowledge. This his or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary expreſſion of himſelf before God, ſpake loud: <hi>Poor worm, ſinful wretch! O pardon my tranſgreſſions, for they are very great.</hi> Hereupon he would weep much when he was told how much he was prayed for, wondering at Gods goodneſſe, that ſo worthleſs a wretch ſhould have ſo much intereſt in the hearts and prayers of the people of the Lord. And his language in his Will reports how little he was in his own eyes: The words are there, <hi>I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire that at my Funeral there may be no pomp, but that ſo poore a worthleſſe wretch may be privately laid in the ground.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus from the rare Graces received, I proceed to the rich Comforts vouchſafed, as manifeſtations of Chriſts ſingular love towards this Saint of the moſt High God. O what kiſſes of Chriſts mouth, and what embraces from the arms of his love were beſtowed upon this man of God! He enjoyed all along his affl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cted condition, an uninter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted aſſurance of Gods fatherly love in Chriſt. In his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſes to God he conſtantly claimed propriety, <hi>My God, and my Father.</hi> His inward peace and joy, were the ſupport of his heart under all his g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>inding paines. He was confident of mercies mixtures with all his grievous diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempers, not at all doubting of the Sanctification of them through grace. Thus he ſpake many times in his Applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to God: <hi>Conſider and ſave me, for I am thine. How long, Lord, how long ſhall I not be remembred? yea, I am remembred, bleſſed be thy Name. This is a fiery chariot, but it will carry me to heaven. Bleſſed be God that hath ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:133592:37"/> me hitherto, and he that hath delivered, will deliver. Thou, Lord, never forgetteſt them that put their truſt in thee.</hi> Alwayes when the extremity of pain was over, he would, with ſmiles ſpeak of Gods mercies. Though trembling took hold upon him when his violent paines began, yet he would with confidence ſay, <hi>Now in the ſtrength of the mighty God I will undergo theſe paines. O my God put under thine everlaſting arms, and ſtrengthen me.</hi> Many times he hath told me, that notwithſtanding all his rent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings and roarings (from which he expected no deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance but by death) he would not for a thouſand worlds change eſtates with the greateſt man on earth, whom he looked upon as in a way of ſin. And let me tell you one providence of fatherly indulgence towards him<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> That <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan never ſhaked his confidence, nor aſſaulted his hopes, all the time of his tireſome, irkſome exerciſe.</hi> There is but one paſſage more which I ſhal point at under this ſecond head of my Narrative, <hi>viz.</hi> That he accounted all theſe inward chearings the fruits of Prayers made for him, though God ſaw cauſe to deny that eaſe and recovery to his body which was much begged; withal valuing thoſe ſpiritual cordials much beyond deliverance from the Gowt and Stone, and death it ſelf.</p>
            <p>All theſe things I have the rather mentioned, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent that diſcouragement or offence, which ſome may be too apt to take at the continuance of his waſting, torment<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing paines, notwithſtanding his own godlineſſe, and the unceſſant Prayers, both ordinary and extraordinary, which were made unto God in his behalfe: for he found the ſweet fruits of them in his own boſome, when he felt the continuance and increaſe of his bodily griefs.</p>
            <p>I proceed to the third head of my promiſed Narrative, which will ſpeak Mr. <hi>Whitakers</hi> love to his fellow-Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans. He was a man made up (as it were) of love: His delight was in the Saints upon earth, whom he eſteemed moſt excellent, and their ſociety was a conſtant cordial unto his ſpirit. H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>equent viſits of them who were in trouble, and his ſtirring up others to the like practice,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:133592:38"/> were teſtimonies of his friendſhip. His love was not only verbal, but real. Truly I know no man of his eſtate more liberal. He would often ſay. <hi>It's a brave thing when a man with a full estate hath a charitable heart.</hi> Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times upon ſpecial occaſions he himſelf hath given away all the money he had in his houſe. It was not unuſual with him to give twenty ſhillings unto a poor Saint, and he had many experiences of Gods gracious returns in ſuch caſes. By his Will he gave 20. <hi>l.</hi> to the godly poor of his own Pariſh.</p>
            <p>There were two caſes wherein his loves were moſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larged to the people of God, whereof I ſhall give in two inſtances. The one when their ſufferings were pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick. He hath often told me that <hi>Englands</hi> late breach with <hi>Scotland,</hi> and the blood ſhed, with other ſad conſequences thereof, had taken ſuch impreſſion up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his heart, that the ſorrow would never be removed till his death. And the ſufferings both in <hi>Holland</hi> and <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> upon our late Sea-fights, were great burdens upon his ſpirit. The other caſe was in reference to the inward perplexity of ſuch as were afflicted in minde. Having moved me the week before his death to beſtow a viſit up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on one in that condition, the morning before his death, (when ſpeech was grievous in reſpect of his weakneſſes) he asked me whether I had remembred the party troubled in ſpirit? which is a remarkable evidence of ſtrong loves. Beſides all that hath been mentioned, I could relate his many wreſtlings with God to prevent the flood of trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles which he apprehended the Proteſtant Churches are now in danger to be overflowed withal; as alſo his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſionate reſpect to Congregations in the Country, who were like ſheep wandring upon the barren mountaines without a ſhepherd.</p>
            <p>The fourth head of my Narrative ſhould hold forth the love which he received from the Saints of God. What godly heart that either knew him, or heard of his fame, did not love him? I will not ſpeak of the frequent friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly viſits of the Religious ones in the neighborhood round about. I never heard of any man ſo much prayed for,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:133592:38"/> both in publick and private. There was no particular caſe ſo frequently, ſo affectionately ſpread before God in moſt of the Congregations about <hi>London</hi> as his. Three dayes were ſet apart by Miniſters, and many other pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing friends to ſeek God in his behalf; one in private, and two in publick, which alſo were obſerved much better then ſuch dayes uſually are; yea, in remote Countreys, beſides the ordinary prayers made for him, there were ſome Faſts kept, with ſpecial reference to his affliction. The multitude of people attending his Funeral, with the many weeping eyes, did witneſſe how much he was belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved. Here I might remember the readineſſe of <hi>London</hi>-Miniſters to ſupply his place at home, and Lectures elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where, as alſo the willingneſs of fellow-Lecturers at <hi>Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter</hi> to preach for him there, when he himſelf by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of weakneſſe could not poſſibly do his own work: But I may be ſilent, for ſtill every where upon the naming of him, love is ſome way diſcovered by ſuch who had know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of him.</p>
            <p>Though I have related much concerning the worth of this good man; yet my conſcience tells me, that I have rather been defective then exceſſive in my relation. I have not told you of his humility, expreſſed by fears, leſt Gods people praying for him ſhould ſpeak too well of him before the Lord. Neither have I mentioned his ſelf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denial, never daring to look after great matters in the world, whereby he condemneth many whoſe ſelf-ſeeking in earthly advantages, rendereth them very offenſive and unſavoury in the Church of Chriſt. Towards his end neither faith nor patience did abate, though his grievous paines were more frequent and violent; in which regards his longings for death were much increaſed, yet attended with holy ſubmiſſion unto the good pleaſure of God: Theſe were ſome of his expreſſions, <hi>O my God, break open the priſon-door, and ſet my poor captive ſoul free; but enable me willingly to wait thy time! I deſire to be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved; never did any man more deſire life then I do death! When will that time come, when I ſhall neither ſin more, nor
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:133592:39"/> ſorrow more? When ſhall mortality put on immortality? When ſhall this earthly be diſſolved, that I may be cloathed upon with that houſe which is from heaven? Bleſſed are the dead which die in the Lord, for they rest from their labours, and follow the Lamb whereſoever he goeth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Sabbath ſeven-night before God releaſed him, though his paines were very ſharp, yet he beſtowed moſt part of the time of publick Ordinances in prayer with thoſe that were with him, and his petitions were moſt for Miniſters, that God would cloath his Ordinances with his own power, and enable Miniſters to ſpeak unto the ſouls of people. Then alſo he did with many tears bewail his detainment from the Sanctuary and Sabbath-opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, which had been his delight; profeſſing alſo, that his being taken off from ſervice was a greater affliction to him then all his pains. And becauſe this apprehenſion, (<hi>viz.</hi> his unſerviceableneſſe) did much afflict him; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this was often ſuggeſted to him, (which alſo was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving to his ſpirit,) <hi>viz.</hi> that now by the practice of Faith, Patience, Contentment, and Spiritualneſſe (which he had formerly preached) he was very profitable unto them who did viſit him, and might alſo prove very advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tageous unto others who might be acquainted therewith, through Gods grace by Chriſt. So great was his tender reſpect unto his friends, that when his pains were coming with violence, he would intreat them to with-draw from him, that they might not be grieved with his roarings. He would often bleſs God, that his compaſſionate friends were not neceſſitated to abide within the reach of his doleful lamentations.</p>
            <p>I hearing, the night before God tranſlated him, that he was not likely to live another day, I went early in the morning to take my leave of him (whom my ſoul loved) and found his bodily ſtrength almoſt ſpent. And becauſe he could not ſpeak without difficulty, I ſpake the more unto him, in relation to the approach of his happy hoped for change: my diſcourſe through Gods mercy was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhing unto his ſpirit. Minding him that many of his
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:133592:39"/> friends intended to ſet apart that day in ſeeking the Lord for him, I asked him in what things eſpecially he deſired to be remembred before the Throne of Grace? His an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer was, <hi>Do not complaine, but bleſſe God for me, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat him to open the priſon-door.</hi> Hereupon laying my hand upon his cold hand, covered with a clammy ſweat, I took my laſt farewel with an aking heart: and upon my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture from him, theſe were his laſt words unto me, <hi>Brother, I thank you, I pray God bleſſe you, and I bleſſe God for you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That day was ſpent in addreſſes to God for him at <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters Cornhil,</hi> where M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Newcomen</hi> quickened and guided our prayers in his Sermon from <hi>John</hi> 11. wherein he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted eſpecially upon theſe words, <hi>Lord, behold, he whom thou loveſt is ſick,</hi> ver. 4. And M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Jenkyn</hi> endeavoured to moderate and regulate our ſorrows from <hi>Luke 23. 28. Weep not for me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus his friends having by prayers, with praiſes (on his behalf) given him up to God, and having prepared their hearts for their loſs of him, the Lord was pleaſed that evening to take him unto himſelf.</p>
            <p>And now <hi>our friend</hi> Whitaker <hi>ſleepeth. 1. He is dead,</hi> that ſpeaketh ſorrow. 2. <hi>His death is a ſleep,</hi> this yieldeth relief.</p>
            <p>Firſt, His death is ground of lamentation, becauſe Chriſt and his Church have now one friend leſs on earth to be ſerviceable unto both. I would awaken your hearts unto ſenſibleneſſe under this great loſſe, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore wiſh that his great parts, many intereſts, frequent opportunities of ſervice, together with the unmovable faithfulneſs of his heart to improve all for good, may be duly remembred, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. As for his Abilities, he was an univerſal Scholar, both in the Arts and Original Languages; by much ſtudy he had digeſted the whole Body of Divinity, he was well ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted both with the Schoolmen and the Fathers, a good Diſputant, judicious in Caſes of Conſcience, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond unto none in acquaintance with the holy Scripture.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:133592:40"/>2. He had much intereſt in the hearts of perſons of chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt places and power in the Nation: for the plainneſſe of his ſpirit, together with the power of godlineſſe (which did ſhine in his converſation) gained him much Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in the conſciences of all ſorts with whom he converſed, whether in the City or Countrey.</p>
            <p n="3">3. And his opportunities of ſervice were many, not only in <hi>Southwark,</hi> but alſo in <hi>London, Weſtminſter, Stepney,</hi> where he had much imployment.</p>
            <p>We read when <hi>Dorcas</hi> was dead, that the <hi>widows ſtood weeping, and ſhewing the coats which ſhe had made,</hi> Acts 9. 39. and that upon <hi>Pauls</hi> departure the people <hi>wept, becauſe they ſhould ſee his face no more,</hi> Acts 20. 38. And is there not reaſon that we ſhould be in like manner affected, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membring how truth hath been defended, error confuted, holineſs cheriſhed, wickedneſſe checked, the cauſe of the poor pleaded, and the violence of ſome paſſionate ſpirits allayed by M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Whitaker?</hi> But now this able, publick-ſpirited man muſt be ſerviceable on earth no more; now we ſhall not be edified by his Miniſtery any more, nor warmed by his prayers any more, nor cheared by his company and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference any more. But let us moderate our ſorrow by this following conſideration, That <hi>our friend Whitaker is not dead, but ſleepeth:</hi> For this aſſureth us both of his preſent eaſe, and future Reſurrection. Now being aſleep he is well, he reſteth, (as in a bed) and we ſhall not ſee his pale face, his weeping eyes, his trembling hands any more, we ſhall no more hear his deep groans, and doleful lamentations. He is fallen aſleep <hi>in the Lord,</hi> and he and we ſhall have a better meeting at the general Reſurrection then ever heretofore, and then ſhall we ever <hi>be with the Lord.</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>let us comfort one another with theſe words,</hi> 1 Theſ. 4. 15, 18.</p>
            <p>I have but one thing more to hint; <hi>viz.</hi> That Chriſt now knoweth that this our precious friend ſleepeth From whence I infer, 1. <hi>Comfort. 2. Counſel.</hi> This may be chear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing unto all his mourning Relations, Domeſtical, Paſtoral, Claſſical. For Chriſt underſtandeth that his wife hath loſt
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:133592:40"/> a dear husband, his children an indulgent father, his people a faithful Paſtor, the Claſſis a chief Pillar, and all good Chriſtians a real friend.</p>
            <p>And ſeeing Chriſt (conſidering that M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Whitaker</hi> is dead) doth alſo obſerve how we all are affected with this providence; therfore I beſeech you, and beſeech you again, to ſtudy in good earneſt the gracious improvement of this ſad diſpenſation. Let us hear the voice of this rod, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentingly remember the forfeitures made of this bleſſing, and make conſcionable imitation of the good example he hath left us.</p>
            <p>Though M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Whitaker</hi> is dead, yet <hi>his holy life ſpeaketh.</hi> My Narrative hath told much of that which it ſpeaketh, and my prayers are, that it may ſpeak (through the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currence of Gods grace) that unto all our hearts, which may be for ſpiritual and eternal benefit by Chriſt.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="poems">
            <pb n="70" facs="tcp:133592:41"/>
            <head>POEMS, And ELEGIES On the Death of Mr. JEREMIAH WHITAKER.</head>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>On the Death of my dear Friend Mr. <hi>Jeremiah Whitaker.</hi>
               </head>
               <lg>
                  <l>IF death be but a ſervant ſent to call</l>
                  <l>The ſouls of Saints to their original:</l>
                  <l>Dear St thine was a noble ſoul, to whom</l>
                  <l>Three Meſſengers were ſent to call thee home;</l>
                  <l>A ſtone, an ulcer, and a gangrene too,</l>
                  <l>Three deaths to haſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that which one ſhould do.</l>
                  <l>'Twas not becauſe thy ſoul was deeper ſet</l>
                  <l>Then ours within its houſe of clay; nor yet</l>
                  <l>Becauſe thou wert unwilling to depart</l>
                  <l>Thither; where long before had been thine hear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
                  <l>They were not ſent to hale by violence</l>
                  <l>A ſoul that lingered when 'twas called hence.</l>
                  <l>God ſhewd how welcome one death was to thee</l>
                  <l>Who did, ſo meekly entertain all three.</l>
                  <l>Thus many deaths Gods <hi>Iſrael</hi> did incloſe,</l>
                  <l>The ſea before, behind a ſea of foes,</l>
                  <l>On either ſide the jaws of mountains high.</l>
                  <l>No way from death but unto death to flie.</l>
                  <l>Not to deſtroy them, but to let them ſee</l>
                  <l>The power of love, which then would ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> them free.</l>
                  <l>Thus <hi>Jobs</hi> four Meſſengers which did relate</l>
                  <l>The doleful ſtory of his ruin'd ſtate</l>
                  <l>And his three friends, which acted Satans part</l>
                  <l>(He on his fleſh, and theſe upon his heart)</l>
                  <l>Who by diſputing him unto a curſe</l>
                  <l>Would make his ſpirits torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts the far worſe,</l>
                  <l>Were by Gods wiſe diſpoſal ſent to ſhow</l>
                  <l>The ſtrength he on his Champion would be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow.</l>
                  <l>Thus Painters put dark grounds, where they intend</l>
                  <l>To overlay with fineſt gold, &amp; lend</l>
                  <l>By deeper ſhadows luſter to that face,</l>
                  <l>On which they mean their choiceſt skill to place.</l>
                  <l>Thus workmen ſeaſon much with ſun &amp; wind</l>
                  <l>Thoſe greateſt beams which muſt the build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing binde</l>
                  <l>Whilſt ſmaler peeces haply are put in</l>
                  <l>When they come bleeding from the wood &amp; green.</l>
                  <l>Oft where is greateſt grace, God's pleas'd to ſend</l>
                  <l>Great conflicts thoſe great graces to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mend</l>
                  <l>As the ſix finger'd Giants ſword did bring</l>
                  <l>The more renown to little <hi>Davids</hi> ſling.</l>
                  <l>The vanquiſht Lion, and the conquered Bear</l>
                  <l>Prepar'd that holy head a Crown to wear.</l>
                  <l>The Angel wraſtled firſt, and then did bleſs</l>
                  <l>And made the greater ſervant to the leſſe.</l>
                  <l>Pain was to great for thee, Gods grace for pain,</l>
                  <l>And made the greater ſerve the leſſe again.</l>
                  <l>Thy pains ſerv'd thee to glory, and did ſit</l>
                  <l>The head on which a Crown of life muſt ſit.</l>
                  <l>This is Gods method to fetch joy from grief,</l>
                  <l>To turn our ſorrows unto our relief,</l>
                  <l>To ſave by killing and to bring to ſhore</l>
                  <l>By the ſhips planks which was quite broke before.</l>
                  <pb n="71" facs="tcp:133592:41"/>
                  <l>And thus a barren womb firſt took the ſeed</l>
                  <l>Which did ſix hundred thouſand people breed.</l>
                  <l>That ſeed too muſt from knife and alter riſe,</l>
                  <l>And be before a fire a ſacrifice.</l>
                  <l>Great Preacher of thine heavenly Fathers will</l>
                  <l>Thy tongue did many years with Manna fill.</l>
                  <l>Thy life out-preacht thy tongue, O bleſſed ſtrife!</l>
                  <l>Thy ſickneſſe the beſt Sermon of thy life.</l>
                  <l>Before each Doctrine muſt be prov'd anew,</l>
                  <l>Thine end was one great proof that all was true.</l>
                  <l>Before thou preacht by weeks, but now by houres,</l>
                  <l>Each minute taught thy mourning Auditors,</l>
                  <l>Each patient groan, and each beleeving eye</l>
                  <l>Was a new Sermon in Brachygraphy.</l>
                  <l>When nature roars without repining words,</l>
                  <l>Grace in the mouth whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the bowels ſwords,</l>
                  <l>In midſt of torments to triumph o're hell,</l>
                  <l>To feel Gods Arrows, yet his praiſes tell.</l>
                  <l>Through thickeſt clouds to ſee the brighteſt light,</l>
                  <l>In blackeſt darkneſs to have cleareſt ſight,</l>
                  <l>And with our Lord to cry, my God, my God</l>
                  <l>Upon a Croſſe under the ſharpeſt rod.</l>
                  <l>This is indeed to preach; this is to ſhow</l>
                  <l>Faiths triumph over natures greateſt wo.</l>
                  <l>Then welcome fiery Serpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts ſcortching ſting,</l>
                  <l>Which did thee thus to th' brazen Serpent bring.</l>
                  <l>Then welcom Whale, which though it firſt devour,</l>
                  <l>Renders at laſt the Prophet to the ſhore.</l>
                  <l>Well might'ſt thou bear the ſtone which death did throw,</l>
                  <l>Who hadſt the white ſtone the new name to ſhow:</l>
                  <l>Wel mightſt thou be with ſuch an ulcer calm</l>
                  <l>Whoſe ſoul was heal'd before with heavens balm.</l>
                  <l>When ſpirits wounds are cur'd though na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture groan,</l>
                  <l>An heart of fleſh can heal a back of ſtone:</l>
                  <l>Let conſcience have her feaſt, and let fleſh roare,</l>
                  <l>This pain ſhal make the others joy the more,</l>
                  <l>As many times thoſe flowers moſt fragrant ſmell</l>
                  <l>Which neareſt to ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e noiſom weeds do dwel.</l>
                  <l>Thus have you ſeen the forge moſt clearly glow,</l>
                  <l>On which the Smith doth drops of water throw.</l>
                  <l>Keen froſts make fire the hotter, &amp; deep night</l>
                  <l>Cauſeth coeleſtial lamps to ſhine more bright.</l>
                  <l>And by a dear Antiperiſtaſis,</l>
                  <l>The childs diſtreſs ſweetens the father kiſs.</l>
                  <l>A wounded body yields to a ſound ſoul</l>
                  <l>The joys of this do th' others paines controle.</l>
                  <l>As in the day that the Sun beams appear</l>
                  <l>All other leſſer ſtars do diſappear.</l>
                  <l>When heaven ſhines and divine love doth<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> raign,</l>
                  <l>The ſoul is not at leaſure to complain.</l>
                  <l>Internal joyes his heart ſo well compoſes,</l>
                  <l>That they have judg'd their flames a bed of Roſes.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>Mr. <hi>Gataker.</hi> Mr. <hi>Whitaker.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>But what ſhall <hi>England</hi> do from whence are lopt,</l>
                  <l>Two of her richeſt acres to heaven dropt.</l>
                  <l>By loſſe of theſe two acres ſhee's more poor,</l>
                  <l>Then if ſhe'had loſt a hundred Lordſhips more.</l>
                  <l>'Twere a good purchaſe to gain theſe agen,</l>
                  <l>By giving to the ſea all <hi>Lincoln-fen.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Two little mines of gold do far ſurpaſſe</l>
                  <l>Huge Mannors where th' whole veſture is but graſſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Learn we by them what al men wil once ſay,</l>
                  <l>One Pearch of heaven, 's worth the whole globe of clay.</l>
               </lg>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Ed. Reynolds. <hi>D. D.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>To the memory of Mr. <hi>Jeremy Whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taker</hi> powerful in Prayer and Preaching, pious in life, patient in ſickneſſe, &amp;c.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>NAy, now forbear; for pity ſake give o're,</l>
                  <l>You that would make the Clergy none, or poor:</l>
                  <pb n="72" facs="tcp:133592:42"/>
                  <l>We are made miſerable enough this year,</l>
                  <l>That we have loſt our Reverend <hi>Whitaker;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Loſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e above Deans and Chapters! had but he</l>
                  <l>Liv'd ſtil &amp; preacht—<hi>Ziba</hi> take all (for me.)</l>
                  <l>Nay I beleeve, had Sacrilegious hands</l>
                  <l>Finger'd our poor Remains of Tyths, &amp; Lands</l>
                  <l>Whilſt he ſurviv'd they had but ſin'd in vain,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Whitaker</hi> would have pray'd them back again,</l>
                  <l>As <hi>Luther</hi> did a young mans ſoul repeal</l>
                  <l>Giv'n to the Devil under hand and Seal.</l>
                  <l>A Chariot and an Horſman we have loſt</l>
                  <l>In whoſe each ſingle pray'r incamptan Hoſt.</l>
                  <l>How have I heard him (on ſome ſolemn day</l>
                  <l>When doubtful War could make all <hi>London</hi> pray)</l>
                  <l>Mount up to heav'n with armed crys &amp; tears,</l>
                  <l>And rout as far as <hi>York</hi> the Cavileers,</l>
                  <l>Have you not ſeen an early-riſing <hi>Lark</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Spring from her turf, making the Sunne her mark;</l>
                  <l>Shooting her ſelf aloft, yet highe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, higher,</l>
                  <l>Till ſhe had ſung her ſelf into heav'ns Quire?</l>
                  <l>Thus would he riſe in pray'r, and in a trice</l>
                  <l>His ſoul become a Bird of Paradiſe,</l>
                  <l>And if our faint devotions prayers be;</l>
                  <l>What can we call his leſſe then Extaſie?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>On his Preaching.</head>
                  <l>If with th' Almighty he prevailed ſo,</l>
                  <l>Wonder not that he wonders wrought below;</l>
                  <l>The ſon of conſolation, and of thunder</l>
                  <l>Met both in him, in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>thers are aſunder.</l>
                  <l>He was (like <hi>Luke</hi>) Phyſitian of both kindes,</l>
                  <l>Wrought cures upon mens bodies and their mindes.</l>
                  <l>The falling ſickneſſe of Apoſtaſie,</l>
                  <l>Dropſie of drunkenneſſe, prides trimpany,</l>
                  <l>The Megrim of opinions new, or old,</l>
                  <l>Palſy of unbelief, Charities Cold,</l>
                  <l>Luſts burning Feaver, Angers Calenture,</l>
                  <l>The Collick in the conſcience he could cure:</l>
                  <l>Set the ſouls broken bone<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>; by holy Art</l>
                  <l>He hath diſſolv'd the ſtone in many a heart</l>
                  <l>Harder then that he dy'd of.—O come in,</l>
                  <l>Yee multitudes whom he hath heal'd of ſin,</l>
                  <l>And thereby made his debtors—pay him now</l>
                  <l>Some of thoſe tears which he laid out for you;</l>
                  <l>Intereſt-tears I mean, for ſhould you all</l>
                  <l>Weep over him both uſe, and principal</l>
                  <l>'Twould waſh away the ſtone, which covers him</l>
                  <l>And make his Coffin (like an Ark) to ſwim.</l>
                  <l>Now wipe thine eyes (my Muſe) and ſtop thy verſe,</l>
                  <l>(Thy ink can only ſerve to black his herſe)</l>
                  <l>Yet (ſtay) I'le drop one tear, ſigh one ſigh more,</l>
                  <l>'Tis this: Although my Poetry be poor,</l>
                  <l>O what a mighty Prophet ſhould <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> be,</l>
                  <l>Had this <hi>Elija's</hi> mantle falne to me!</l>
                  <l>Oh might I live his life! I'de be content</l>
                  <l>His ſore diſeaſes too ſhould me torment,</l>
                  <l>And if his Patience could mine become,</l>
                  <l>I would not be afraid of Martyrdome.</l>
               </lg>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Robert Wilde.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>Upon the Pious, and painful Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Mr. <hi>Jeremy Whitaker.</hi>
               </head>
               <lg>
                  <head>An Epitaph.</head>
                  <l>I <hi>Eremy</hi>'s not here into the dungeon thrown,</l>
                  <l>'Tis heav'ns Whit-acre (onely) newly Mown;</l>
                  <l>Now Angel-reapers gather'd have to Barne</l>
                  <l>The ſeedſman of Gods Word like full ripe Corne.</l>
                  <l>In teares he ſow'd, &amp; now the heav'nly Q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ire</l>
                  <l>To give him joy of Harveſt all conſpire.</l>
                  <l>In his ſick bed this Paradox we found,</l>
                  <l>The thorny, and the ſtony are good ground.</l>
                  <l>The gowt and ſtone (as milſtones) ground the man</l>
                  <l>To fineſt flower for Mancher; here no Bran</l>
                  <l>Theſe ſiſting times could finde: nere did man ſay,</l>
                  <l>The Preacher ſpake as mealy-mouth'd to day.</l>
                  <l>Gallants (you mealy heads &amp; capes that have)</l>
                  <l>Go take perfumed powder from his grave,</l>
                  <l>The duſt off's feet was beautiful, and he</l>
                  <pb n="73" facs="tcp:133592:42"/>
                  <l>Your powder; and your looking-glaſs may be.</l>
                  <l>His life a Sermon was, his duſt doth cry</l>
                  <l>All fleſh is graſſe, go home, and learn to die.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>England</hi> may ever glory, <hi>Rome</hi> deſpaire</l>
                  <l>In Whit ac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e i'th Pulpit, and i'th Chaire.</l>
               </lg>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Thomas Hodges, <hi>B. D.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>An Elegy upon the Death of Mr <hi>Whitaker.</hi>
               </head>
               <lg>
                  <l>IF paſſion can make Poets, or grief raiſe</l>
                  <l>Expreſſions great enough to ſpeak thy praiſe,</l>
                  <l>Then might <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>Whitaker,</hi> thy worth reherſe;</l>
                  <l>And with my ſtrowings deck thy ſacred Herſe.</l>
                  <l>A Synod's only fit to ſpeak thy fall,</l>
                  <l>And bear a part in this their Funeral.</l>
                  <l>Divines muſt grieve that with thee tomb'd doth lie.</l>
                  <l>What now we vainly ſeek, Divinity.</l>
                  <l>If we would hear ſuch pray'rs as could hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven move</l>
                  <l>And tune the ſpheres into a Quire of love</l>
                  <l>Sweeter then Angels Anthemes, then we muſt</l>
                  <l>Ranſack thy grave, and reinſpire thy duſt.</l>
                  <l>There ſcatter'd lies that voice, which could inſpire</l>
                  <l>All hearts, and fill them with an holy fire</l>
                  <l>As flames get flames: Who thunder did defie</l>
                  <l>Six words of thine could melt, and purify</l>
                  <l>Such Callous ſouls, which at their ſins ne're vext.</l>
                  <l>Did finde thy Sermons keener then the Text.</l>
                  <l>Thy Doctrine ſtill was edg'd againſt mens crimes</l>
                  <l>And ſerv'd to lance the ulcers of the times:</l>
                  <l>Who now ſhall teach the wicked their ſad doomes?</l>
                  <l>Or elſe convince that faith by hearing comes?</l>
                  <l>For whoſoe're heard thee, were caught by th' eare</l>
                  <l>And went out converts, that came curious there.</l>
                  <l>But thoſe who n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>'re were wearied with thy voice</l>
                  <l>Do now complain of too much length and noiſe.</l>
                  <l>For ſince, bleſt O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ator, thou parted'ſt hence,</l>
                  <l>The Pulpit only ſuffers violence.</l>
               </lg>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Edw. Bagſhaw.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>On the much lamented death of that Reverend man of God, Mr. <hi>Jeremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah Whitaker,</hi> his dear friend and old neighbour, both in City and Countrey.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>IF Reaſon, Vertue, Wiſdom make a <hi>man,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>If Faith, Hope, Charity the <hi>Chriſtian;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>If faithful, uſeful, cheerful grace a <hi>friend,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Arts, Tongues, choice Wit, rare Memory com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Scholar;</hi> if Humanity, Divinity,</l>
                  <l>Candor, Humility, bowels, integrity;</l>
                  <l>If parts, pains, zeal, ſound Doctrine, utterance, tears,</l>
                  <l>Faith, courage, prudence, patience, faſting, prayers,</l>
                  <l>Succeſs crown <hi>Preacher;</hi> Lo, of thouſands ten</l>
                  <l>That <hi>Man, Friend, Chriſtian, Scholar, Preacher</hi> then.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Never in times <hi>unfixt</hi> a man more <hi>fixt;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Never in heart ſo <hi>pure,</hi> graces more mixt;</l>
                  <l>Mildnes with boldnes, courage with courteſie;</l>
                  <l>High parts, low thoughts, yielding with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy:</l>
                  <l>Well to <hi>conceive</hi> and ſpeak, to <hi>ſpeak</hi> and <hi>do,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And do ſo much, ſo much to ſuffer too.</l>
                  <l>For Love a <hi>Jonathan,</hi> for Truth <hi>Nathanael;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>For Meekneſſe <hi>Moſes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi> and for courage <hi>Daniel;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Call'd when a child a ſecond <hi>Jeremiah;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>For ſpirit, prayer, power the third <hi>Eliah,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>For firmneſſe <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>phas,</hi> for ſympathy a <hi>Paul,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>For pains, ſucceſs exceeding moſt or all.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>One thing was lacking yet to make him high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er,</l>
                  <l>As gold, or <hi>Job,</hi> he muſt into the fire.</l>
                  <l>As gold, or <hi>Job</hi> he was unto the laſt,</l>
                  <pb n="74" facs="tcp:133592:43"/>
                  <l>For <hi>patience</hi> prov'd, <hi>Integrity held faſt.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Who ere ſaw ſuch ſharp pains? heard ſuch ſweet prayers?</l>
                  <l>Strong cryes, but ſtronger faith, praiſes with tears?</l>
                  <l>Ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Lord by ſuffering did to <hi>perfection</hi> grow:</l>
                  <l>In ſuffering <hi>obedience</hi> he did <hi>learn</hi> and ſhow,</l>
                  <l>This man of God came to that altitude</l>
                  <l>By ſuffering, of ſore pains, that multitude.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The racking <hi>Gowt</hi> &amp; the tormenting <hi>Stone,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>In <hi>Kidneys</hi> Ulcers two, in <hi>bladder</hi> one,</l>
                  <l>Made pains ſharp, ſore, long, thick, but reſpite ſmall;</l>
                  <l>Yet faith and patience overcame them all.</l>
                  <l>Now after well ſpent life, and reſtleſſe pains,</l>
                  <l>And heave<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aſſur'd, we reckon death for gains:</l>
                  <l>Death when by ſelf deſired, by friends be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayl'd,</l>
                  <l>And a ſweet memory left have ſtill prevail'd</l>
                  <l>To call dead happy. Then our loſs to thee</l>
                  <l>Was greateſt gains compleat felicity.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Weep <hi>Berm'ſey, London</hi> wail, mourn <hi>England</hi> all,</l>
                  <l>He<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e did thy <hi>Crown, Chariots</hi> &amp; <hi>Horſmen</hi> fall.</l>
               </lg>
               <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>John Sheffield,</hi> Paſtor of <hi>Swithins London-ſtone.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>Of the ſame Author.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>OLd <hi>Jeremy</hi> a Prophet was and <hi>childe,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Yet was a <hi>brazen wall</hi> and <hi>Pillar</hi> ſtil'd.</l>
                  <l>He liv'd in troublous times, ſad changes ſaw,</l>
                  <l>He ſuffered much, yet kept he faſt Gods Law.</l>
                  <l>By all good honour'd by enemies approved:</l>
                  <l>By many cenſur'd, by none faulty proved.</l>
                  <l>He dealt with perſons higheſt, and with low;</l>
                  <l>He warned all, but wiſhed no mans woe.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Son of Contenti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n</hi> called when of peace,</l>
                  <l>The greateſt friend and of his Lands increaſe.</l>
                  <l>He preached much of Chriſt &amp; Goſpel-days,</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Covenant new</hi> he taught, and its rich grace.</l>
                  <l>Yet was his laſt a doleful <hi>lamentation,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Sad to himſelf, ſadder to the Nation.</l>
                  <l>Thou art or waſt the ſame. His <hi>Baruch</hi> he</l>
                  <l>Companion had to him, let me to thee.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>An <hi>Elegy</hi> upon the much lamented death of my late dear and reverend Friend Mr. <hi>Jeremiah Whitaker.</hi>
               </head>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>ENgland</hi> wil ſoon grow poor, if in one year</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Kent</hi> loſe a <hi>Wilſon,</hi> we a <hi>Whitaker.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>A <hi>Thames,</hi> and <hi>Medway</hi> from our heads ariſe,</l>
                  <l>Their ſtreams our tears, their channels are our eyes.</l>
                  <l>Our many <hi>loſſes</hi> call for <hi>teares,</hi> not fewer;</l>
                  <l>The breſt a <hi>Baſon</hi> makes the eye an <hi>Ewer.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>No longer (now) ſhall <hi>Iſis</hi> part the <hi>Burrough</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>From <hi>London,</hi> ſince that <hi>both</hi> ſides meet in ſorrow.</l>
                  <l>Not (as of old) by ſtriving whether ſide</l>
                  <l>Should for their <hi>own</hi> obtain the Silver tide;</l>
                  <l>No, not to <hi>gain</hi> the water wee'l contend;</l>
                  <l>But wee'l by weeping ſtrive who moſt can ſpend.</l>
                  <l>Conduits give wine (indeed) when th' Crown's put on,</l>
                  <l>Now run they tears, becauſe our Crown is gone.</l>
                  <l>Our Friends <hi>Deceaſe</hi> and <hi>Death</hi> our troubles were,</l>
                  <l>We nor his <hi>Sickneſs,</hi> nor his <hi>Med'cines</hi> bear.</l>
                  <l>His Pulpit he eſteem'd his <hi>reſt,</hi> his <hi>bed;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>We thought his bed a <hi>Pulpit,</hi> where he read</l>
                  <l>Lectures of patience; theſe he loudly utter'd,</l>
                  <l>By ſilence oft he groan'd, but never mutter'd.</l>
                  <l>Of mournful <hi>Magdalen, Bermonſey</hi> bears</l>
                  <l>The <hi>name,</hi> and with her <hi>Title</hi> hath her <hi>tears,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And our dear <hi>Whitaker</hi> was <hi>Jeremy</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>In <hi>name,</hi> in <hi>weeping,</hi> and in <hi>Prophecy;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>But he (no Prophet <hi>now</hi>) no <hi>ſackcloth</hi> wears,</l>
                  <l>His <hi>work</hi> is done, and ſo are all his <hi>teares.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>May <hi>Bermonſey</hi> of him the late <hi>poſſeſſor</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Mourn for her <hi>ſins,</hi> but joy in his <hi>ſucceſſor.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <closer>
                  <signed>GUIL. JENKYN, <hi>Paſtor of Black-fryers,</hi> London.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="75" facs="tcp:133592:43"/>
               <head>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon the Death of the Reverend, his never to be forgotten friend, Mr <hi>Jeremiah Whitaker.</hi>
               </head>
               <lg>
                  <l>O That affection could but make a Poet!</l>
                  <l>If grief could rhime with Art, ſure I ſhould do it,</l>
                  <l>(Though ſo diſuſ'd to verſify.) We'l try:</l>
                  <l>The Subject's ſad, and ſo's the Poetry.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The tender ſon that never ſpake before,</l>
                  <l>To ſave his fathers life turn'd Orator.</l>
                  <l>Shall I forbear in ſilence? Write I muſt,</l>
                  <l>When ſuch a friend lies ſleeping in the duſt.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The bleſſed Saint, dear <hi>Jeremy</hi> is gone,</l>
                  <l>And who ſhall write his <hi>lamentation?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Had we his eyes (which always ſhowry were)</l>
                  <l>Such is our loſs, each word ſhould have a tear!</l>
                  <l>Another <hi>Whitaker</hi> in a Coffin plac'd,</l>
                  <l>The firſt the <hi>Chair,</hi> &amp; this the <hi>Pulpit</hi> grac'd.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Reader, would'ſt know his worth, then caſt thy eye</l>
                  <l>Upon the Narrative; there's his excellency.</l>
                  <l>Rings hold not Hiſtories; who can rehearſe</l>
                  <l>His vaſt perfection in a narrow Verſe!</l>
                  <l>Take Vertues, Graces, Gifts, and all you can,</l>
                  <l>All are concentred in this holy man.</l>
                  <l>A brighter ſtar in all our orb there's none,</l>
                  <l>None do exceed, few equal him that's gone.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Ah pious ſoul! What mortal man can ſpeak out</l>
                  <l>Thy rare humility! Who ere meanly thought</l>
                  <l>Of thee beſides thy ſelf? What mov'd thy paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions,</l>
                  <l>But Eulogies and Commendations?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>'Tis well th' art gone from us, ſhouldſt thou but look</l>
                  <l>Into and read thy praiſes in this book,</l>
                  <l>I'm ſure by this thou would'ſt be ſomewhat moved,</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Simeon</hi> himſelf ſhould be reproved.</l>
                  <l>He ſpeaks thy worth ſo much, &amp; yet but little</l>
                  <l>'Tis ſcarce enough (but true to every tittle.)</l>
                  <l>Thy perſonal endowments who would com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend,</l>
                  <l>Should neither know where to begin nor end.</l>
                  <l>Thy Miniſter'al accompliſhments were rare,</l>
                  <l>Thy conſtant pains, thy diligence, thy care</l>
                  <l>For ſouls in holy things. who can expreſſe?</l>
                  <l>Thou might'ſt have longer liv'd, had'ſt thou liv'd leſſe.</l>
                  <l>O melting Suppliant! who e're did know</l>
                  <l>Thy prayers to heaven without ſome tears to go?</l>
                  <l>The ſecret raviſhings which poor ſouls have found</l>
                  <l>When from thy mouth the Word of life did ſound!</l>
                  <l>Our very Pulpits wonder where thou art,</l>
                  <l>In w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> thou didſt ſuch ſpiritual gifts impart:</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But 'tis enough! we'l weep the reſt; we can</l>
                  <l>Launch out no farther in this Ocean.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Could prayers and teares have kept thee here, thy ſtay</l>
                  <l>It had been longer in this houſe of clay.</l>
                  <l>Pray'r barr'd thee in ſome time, till death would throw</l>
                  <l>Open the door by force to let thee go;</l>
                  <l>At laſt thy ſoul did finde the way to bliſſe,</l>
                  <l>And now is ſteep'd in heavens happineſſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>O bleſſed change for thee! the painful bed</l>
                  <l>Is now a Throne, where not a tear is ſhed.</l>
                  <l>No diſmal groa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ings now from thee do come,</l>
                  <l>But everlaſting Triumphs in their room.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Farewel (bleſt Saint) farewel, and ſince 'tis thus;</l>
                  <l>We'l haſt to thee, thou wilt not come to us.</l>
               </lg>
               <closer>
                  <signed>THO. JACOMB. <hi>of M. Ludg.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="76" facs="tcp:133592:44"/>
               <head>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon the death of the reverend, Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and Faithful Servant of Jeſus Chriſt, Mr. <hi>Jeremiah Whitaker,</hi> late Miniſter of Magdalene <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſey</hi> in <hi>Southwark.</hi>
               </head>
               <lg>
                  <l>WHat ſpeaks this ſudden ſtorm of bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh teares?</l>
                  <l>What means this doleful volley in mine ears?</l>
                  <l>Is the Sun darkned? Do the Lamps above,</l>
                  <l>Reſolve their fiery ſtation to remove,</l>
                  <l>And ſhine no more on earth? Doth the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</l>
                  <l>Intend to melt it ſelf with Lamentation?</l>
                  <l>The holy <hi>Whitaker</hi> is ſtept away,</l>
                  <l>Late Angel of the Church of <hi>Bermonſey.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>A Pillar in Gods houſe, a ſweet Muſitian</l>
                  <l>That gladded drooping hearts; A ſoul-Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian,</l>
                  <l>A Sun whoſe beams did conſolation ſhine,</l>
                  <l>A faithful, skilful guide, a rare Divine.</l>
                  <l>He was a Watchman could not wel be blamed;</l>
                  <l>A workman needed not to be aſhamed.</l>
                  <l>No <hi>Proteus,</hi> that could change to every ſhape,</l>
                  <l>No ſervile ſpirited Preacher, that could ſcrape</l>
                  <l>And cringe to pleaſe the luſts of wanton men:</l>
                  <l>He could not ſay, and then unſay agen.</l>
                  <l>Learned, yet very humble, prudent, dear</l>
                  <l>To God, to men; meek, holy, wiſe, ſincere.</l>
                  <l>He lov'd the Truth, he hated Hereſie,</l>
                  <l>A ſtrong oppoſer of all Blaſphemy.</l>
                  <l>His heart was toward a holy Reformation,</l>
                  <l>But ſet againſt a godleſſe toleration</l>
                  <l>Of lewd Opinions. Great was his care</l>
                  <l>To keep the holy Covenant which he ſware.</l>
                  <l>The marrow of Gods O acles was i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> him,</l>
                  <l>No Scripture Myſtery was hidden from him.</l>
                  <l>Caſes of Conſcience he could well unty,</l>
                  <l>Scruples and Doubts from Scripture ſatisfie.</l>
                  <l>His holy Function was his conſolation,</l>
                  <l>His Pulpit work to him was recreation.</l>
                  <l>His pray'rs were zealous, heavenly ſteep'd in teare:</l>
                  <l>His Doctrine Orthodox, convincing clear.</l>
                  <l>Ful of the ſpirit of life and Power, his words</l>
                  <l>Did pierce like nailes, did cut like ſharpned ſwords:</l>
                  <l>He durſt tell <hi>Ahab</hi> of his great oppreſſion;</l>
                  <l>What! doſt thou kill and after take poſſeſſion?</l>
                  <l>He durſt tell <hi>Herod</hi> though it coſt his life,</l>
                  <l>'Tis wickedneſſe to take thy brothers wife.</l>
                  <l>Had ſtrangers heard him Preach, they would have ſed,</l>
                  <l>Sure <hi>John the Baptiſt</hi>'s riſen from the dead.</l>
                  <l>His carriage holy, harmleſſe, free from ſtrife,</l>
                  <l>His Sermons were imprinted in his life.</l>
                  <l>His body was infirm, diſeaſed, weary,</l>
                  <l>His ſoul ſtill vigorous, active, ſtrong and cheary.</l>
                  <l>The more the Cabinet did waſte and wear,</l>
                  <l>The brighter did the Jewel ſtil appear.</l>
                  <l>Goodneſs of nature made the world admire him,</l>
                  <l>The brightneſs of his grace made Saints de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire him.</l>
                  <l>The Church on earth hath loſt a precious plant,</l>
                  <l>The Church in heaven hath gain'd a glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Saint.</l>
               </lg>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Ra. Robinſon, <hi>Miniſter of</hi> Mary Wol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noth, <hi>Lumbard ſtreet</hi> London.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>Jeremiah Whitaker.</head>
               <lg>
                  <head>ANAGRAM, <hi>I have hit everi Mark.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>THou didſt not ſhoot at rovers in the dark,</l>
                  <l>Thy poliſht ſhaft could hit the ſmalleſt mark,</l>
                  <l>Gods glory was thy ſcope, his Word thy guide,</l>
                  <l>His ſtable Spirit did teach thee to divide</l>
                  <l>The word of truth aright: A ſignal Teacher,</l>
                  <l>An uſeful, pious, fruitful, powerful Preacher</l>
                  <l>God made thee to his Chu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>th. None better knew</l>
                  <l>Then <hi>Whitaker</hi> to carve to each his due:</l>
                  <l>The mark of ſaving grace was firſt obtain'd,</l>
                  <l>And now the mark of glory thou haſt gain'd:</l>
                  <l>Enjoy it; and let other Archers ſee</l>
                  <l>Thy happy pattern, and take aim by thee.</l>
               </lg>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Ra. Robinſon <hi>Miniſter of Mary Wolnoth;</hi> Lombardſtreet, London.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="77" facs="tcp:133592:44"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon the death of his moſt dear friend, that eminent ſervant and Miniſter of Jeſus Chriſt, Mr.</hi> Jeremiah Whitaker, <hi>Paſtor of</hi> Mary Magdalen Bermonſey <hi>in</hi> Southwark.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>THus Cedars fall, thus Stars do diſappear,</l>
                  <l>Prophets though Angels, yet but mortals are.</l>
                  <l>Our <hi>Prophet Jeremy</hi>'s dead, and now there's none</l>
                  <l>That's fit to make his Lamentation.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Plato</hi> once wiſht that vertue could appear</l>
                  <l>To mortal eyes, his wiſh was granted here.</l>
                  <l>If any Breviator would comprize</l>
                  <l>All vertues in a word, then let his eyes</l>
                  <l>Be fixed here, keep <hi>Whitaker</hi> in minde.</l>
                  <l>And there you have the vertues all defin'd.</l>
                  <l>Or would you know what all the graces are?</l>
                  <l>In ſhort hand writing, they make <hi>Whitaker.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Would any have the Bible in a word,</l>
                  <l>And what the vaſteſt comments can afford?</l>
                  <l>Read <hi>Whitakers</hi> Works, peruſe his converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</l>
                  <l>And there's the Bible and th' Interpretation;</l>
                  <l>That Book was in his breſt ſo well ingroſt,</l>
                  <l>He could reſtore it, if it had been loſt.</l>
                  <l>He that by thee (bleſt Saint) ſhall calculate.</l>
                  <l>Will finde that Miracles are not out of dare.</l>
                  <l>Who e're was ſo far bleſt to hear him teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</l>
                  <l>Was prone to think a Seraphim was preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</l>
                  <l>'Twas <hi>Auſtin</hi>'s wiſh i'th'Pulpit <hi>Paul</hi> to hear;</l>
                  <l>He had been ſatisfied, hadſt thou been there.</l>
                  <l>Me thought when thy ſweet ſoul was poured out</l>
                  <l>In fervent prayer, I began to doubt</l>
                  <l>Whether <hi>Elias</hi> was come down again,</l>
                  <l>And mounting heaven-ward with his fiery train.</l>
                  <l>In this thou didſt excel; he ſcal'd the ſort</l>
                  <l>Alone, but thou thy hearers didſt tranſport.</l>
                  <l>But whither goes my doleful Muſe? to ſpan</l>
                  <l>I'th'hollow of thy f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſt the Ocean.</l>
                  <l>Or to deſcribe his boundleſs hidden worth?</l>
                  <l>Nor tongue nor pen can ſet his praiſes forth.</l>
                  <l>This only I will adde, he that would draw</l>
                  <l>His Portraiture, muſt uſe <hi>Apelles</hi> Law,</l>
                  <l>When to paint Lady <hi>Venus</hi> with a grace,</l>
                  <l>This beauty gave a hand, that gave a face;</l>
                  <l>The third a colour gave, the next a feature,</l>
                  <l>Al joyn'd together made that lovely creature.</l>
                  <l>In the ſame manner, whoſoe're would paint</l>
                  <l>The beauty of this thrice illuſtrious Saint,</l>
                  <l>Muſt rifle all the world, and look apart</l>
                  <l>For that wch ſhines moſt in each noble heart.</l>
                  <l>One muſt Humility give, another Zeal,</l>
                  <l>Another Prudence brethrens rents to heal.</l>
                  <l>Learning a fourth in its high'ſt elevation.</l>
                  <l>A fifth muſt give a ſpotleſs converſation.</l>
                  <l>His preaching one man cannot imitate;</l>
                  <l>Here we muſt have <hi>Beza</hi>'s <hi>triumvirate.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And when we'ave travel'd all the world to find</l>
                  <l>Or make a copy of this matchleſſe minde,</l>
                  <l>When other mens perfections al do fail,</l>
                  <l>We muſt with that old Limner draw a vail</l>
                  <l>Upon his peerleſſe parts, or for the reſt,</l>
                  <l>Say, here lies that which cannot be expreſt.</l>
               </lg>
               <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>Sic flevit</hi> Mat. Poole <hi>Miniſter of Michaels at the Quern in</hi> London.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>An Epitaph.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>HEre lies Saint</hi> Whitaker, <hi>the reſt</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Cannot, need not be expreſt.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Great ſorrows noiſe not, Give ſome years</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>For the world to ſpeak in tears.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>First this age muſt vent its grief</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>In ſighs, the next may finde relief,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And joyn their ſorrows to compute</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Till grief returning ſtrikes them mute,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And makes them ſilently confeſſe</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Their loſs; his worth was fathom'eſſe.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>Another Epitaph.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>UNder this ſtone intombed lies</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>An heap of contrarieties,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>One that's dead, yet doth remaine</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>For perſon, place, and work the ſame.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>His precious perſon was combin'd</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Of ſoul and body firmly joyn'd.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>So ſtill theſe parts though diſtant, yet</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>In Chriſt are to each other knit.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="78" facs="tcp:133592:45"/>
                  <l>
                     <hi>To earth his body was confin'd,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Alwayes heaven had and hath his minde,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>His work was preaching, ſo 'tis ſtill,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And preach his name for ever will.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Mat Poole.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>To the memory of the learned that e<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>minently Religious Miniſter of the Goſpel (his Reverend brother de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſed) Mr. <hi>Jeremiah Whitaker.</hi>
               </head>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>WHitaker</hi> ſleeps; ſpices you need not bring</l>
                  <l>For's body; death it ſelf's embalm'd to him.</l>
                  <l>Ah bleſſed Saint! his Sermons were not done</l>
                  <l>When preach'd, he liv'd the Application:</l>
                  <l>When ſick, his pangs were mercy, for when e're</l>
                  <l>A ſigh was breath'd out, God breath'd in a pray'r.</l>
                  <l>Lie gently on him duſt, this ſeed is ſown</l>
                  <l>To ſpring again at th' Reſurrection.</l>
                  <l>Oh for a verſe in black! Reader prepare thus</l>
                  <l>For every drop of ink to melt a tear.</l>
                  <l>Yet ſtay, with grief there's cauſe of joy: then</l>
                  <l>Joy ſhal ſhed tears for him, and grief for us.</l>
               </lg>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Benjamin Needler. Miniſter of the Goſpel at <hi>Margarce Moſes Friday-ſtreet,</hi> Lond.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>In obitum eximii tam Doctrinâ quam pietate Theologi, <hi>Jeremiae Whitakeri,</hi> funebre 'ΕΤΚΩΜΙΑ 'ΣΤΙΚΟΝ.</head>
               <lg>
                  <head>Dr. <hi>Gouge.</hi> Dr. <hi>Walker.</hi> Mr. <hi>Whitaker.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>DEfleat occiduos aetas ingrata Prophetas,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Liquit Evangelicum collapſa ſynaſtria caelum:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Lugentem &amp; moeſto</hi> Whitakerus <hi>funere mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Deſeruit; lachrymis ſquallentem liquerit ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bem:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Jam pereat mendax de florido opinio ſeclo,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Mortuus hic Vates noſtrum ſepelivit honorem,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Corruit &amp; Verax foecundi gloria roſtri:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Patronum amiſit Pauper, populuſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> Lutherum,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Amiſitque pium mutilata eccleſia gnatum,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Paſtorem coetus, Patrem amiſere Miniſtri:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Gens mala praeconem, immotam ſynoduſque co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumnam.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <closer>
                  <signed>J. Wells, <hi>Old Jewry</hi> Lond. <hi>Paſtor.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>To the memory of his dear friend and Paſtor, Mr. <hi>Jeremiah Whita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker,</hi> deceaſed.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>BEhold the ſhadow whoſe admired worth</l>
                  <l>Nor pen, nor tongue is able to ſet forth!</l>
                  <l>He whoſe vaſt ſoul walk'd through the Iſle of Man,</l>
                  <l>Is here confined in a ſhorter ſpan.</l>
                  <l>Whoſe worth the world though 'twere as big again</l>
                  <l>Were much too ſhort and narrow to contain.</l>
                  <l>Sweet were his life and death, his well ſpent dayes</l>
                  <l>Began with goodneſs, and expir'd with praiſe:</l>
                  <l>His lamp was ever burning, never hid;</l>
                  <l>And when his tongue preacht not, his actions did;</l>
                  <l>And to his death he ſtill fought faiths good fight,</l>
                  <l>And then his Lamp exchang'd his borrowed light</l>
                  <l>For an immortal luſtre, and here lies,</l>
                  <l>Enſhrin'd, not dead, for Vertue never dies.</l>
               </lg>
               <closer>
                  <signed>R. B. Pariſhioner.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="79" facs="tcp:133592:45"/>
               <head>Upon the Life and Death of that precious Servant of God, Mr. <hi>Jeremiah Whitaker,</hi> whoſe name (like that of his Lord and Master) is an ointment poured forth.</head>
               <head type="sub">JEREMIAH WHITAKER, <hi>or</hi> Etymologie.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>He ſhall exalt God.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>His work, <hi>Jer.</hi> 20. 13.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>God ſhall exalt him.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>His wages, <hi>Jer.</hi> 5. 10.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>White-aker.</head>
                  <item>
                     <hi>A field white for Harveſt,</hi> John 4. 35.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>His fitneſſe for Heaven.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <lg>
                  <l>BLeſt Saint, how well thy name and worth agree!</l>
                  <l>In name and office thou art <hi>Jeremie.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>A God-exalter, and by God exalted;</l>
                  <l>A <hi>Prieſt,</hi> a <hi>Prophet:</hi> one that never halted</l>
                  <l>Twixt God &amp; <hi>Baal,</hi> twixt the truth &amp; error,</l>
                  <l>Nor couldſt be made to ſtart for hope or terrour.</l>
                  <l>Heroick Champion, thou deaths venemous ſting</l>
                  <l>Haſt conquer'd, and with Chriſt now raign'ſt as <hi>King.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>A wiſe and faithful <hi>Labourer</hi> for thy Lord,</l>
                  <l>To gather in his harveſt by the word,</l>
                  <l>Thou haſt approv'd thy ſelf to Earth and Heaven,</l>
                  <l>Witneſſe thy life and Doctrine purg'd from Leaven.</l>
                  <l>Both <hi>Labourer</hi> and <hi>Harveſt</hi> were thy part;</l>
                  <l>The former living, this thou dying art.</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Field</hi> being for <hi>Harveſt, Jer. White-aker</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Is reapt, and of a better ſoile partaker.</l>
                  <l>Thy melting tears now cordial-water be.</l>
                  <l>Let me thy ſorrows taſte, thy joys to ſee.</l>
               </lg>
               <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>Roger Drake</hi> Paſtor of <hi>Peters Weſt-cheap.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>A Funeral Elegy upon the reverend his deare deceaſed friend, Maſter <hi>Jeremiah Whitaker.</hi>
               </head>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>O Let me weep, and even like a ſpring</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Unto the ſea of grief ſome tribute bring.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Theſe cheeks of mine with tears bedew'd ſhall ſwell</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>For this Seraphique St. who lately fel.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>To loſe a Friend is ſad, but for our Nation</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>To loſe a</hi> Jeremy <hi>is</hi> Lamentation.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Could he from death ſome way releaſed be</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>His vertues ſurely might have ſet him free;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>But 'twas a debt; and what enflam'd deſire</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Had he to leave his mantle and flie higher!</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>How ſhal I praiſe his worth, and not diſpraiſe?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Say more, and not ſay leſſe? darkning his rays.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Meekneſſe, humility in this Orbe ſhin'd,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>In him the chaine of</hi> Graces <hi>was combin'd:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>How was he fir'd with zeal, even fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his youth,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And though he loſt all, would hold faſt the truth.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>With</hi> Jeremy <hi>he was a man of ſtrife,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Yet not for</hi> Tyths <hi>but</hi> Souls: <hi>this was his life;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>A downright, upright man he was, a Star</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Whoſe ſacred influence diffuſed far:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And that of theſe an end I may incloſe,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>His faith in Chriſt he ſolely did repoſe.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="80" facs="tcp:133592:46"/>
                  <l>
                     <hi>This made him when he felt the ſharpeſt paine</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Upon the flinty rack, not to complaine;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Nay when he at the point of death did lie,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Did as the milky Swan moſt gently die.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>What did he die? his ſoul as in a C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ll,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>In heav'ns bright Paradiſe is gone to dwell</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Among the Cherubims, where he doth ring</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>With them that joyntly Hallelujahs ſing:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Where he for tears in joy doth much encreaſe,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Pleaſure doth him of former pain releaſe;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>He never ſhall of Stone, or Ulcer heare,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>He never need any more ſickneſſe feare.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Dear Saint! I ſooner had adorn'd thy hearſe,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>But grief firſt vents by weeping, then by verſe.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Thomas Watſon, <hi>Paſtor of</hi> Stephens Walbrook, London.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon the Death of that reverend Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine, Mr. <hi>Jeremiah Whiraker.</hi>
               </head>
               <lg>
                  <l>STay and lament all you that travel by;</l>
                  <l>'Tis <hi>ſin</hi> to paſſe, and not to caſt an eye</l>
                  <l>Upon this mournful <hi>ſpectacle,</hi> the <hi>herſe</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Of one whoſe name can dignifie a <hi>verſe.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Loe here th' <hi>exuvium</hi> of that heavenly ſoul,</l>
                  <l>Who living did by'<hi>s words &amp; works</hi> controul</l>
                  <l>The pow'r of <hi>ſin</hi> and <hi>Satan</hi> &amp; whoſe breath</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Redeem'd</hi> poor ſouls from <hi>darkneſs,</hi> and from <hi>death.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And by his pious <hi>Doctrine</hi> did convince</l>
                  <l>The ſly <hi>Temptations</hi> of that airy <hi>Prince.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>He whoſe whole life was a continued <hi>Tract</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Of practical Divinity,</hi> each <hi>Act</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>A <hi>Sermon,</hi> and each word an <hi>explanation;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>So that his <hi>Audionts</hi> might, by <hi>imitation</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Of him, and of his life, to Heaven come,</l>
                  <l>Although they had been <hi>deaf,</hi> or he bin <hi>dumb.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>But that <hi>Almighty pow'r</hi> who from above</l>
                  <l>Does all things order, and in whom we move</l>
                  <l>Wrapt all theſe <hi>treaſures</hi> up in brittle <hi>Clay;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Death</hi> gav't a crack, and ſo took all away.</l>
                  <l>And now our <hi>griefs</hi> amount to ſuch a ſum</l>
                  <l>That to expreſſe them beſt is to be <hi>Dumb.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>They that can <hi>count</hi> their wealth, are <hi>counted</hi> poor,</l>
                  <l>And who can <hi>ſpeak</hi> his griefs can ſuffer more.</l>
                  <l>'Tis diminution to his <hi>worth,</hi> to weep</l>
                  <l>With <hi>ſingle</hi> tears, we his whole flock of ſheep</l>
                  <l>Joyne in one <hi>Lamentation,</hi> and let fall</l>
                  <l>Our <hi>general</hi> tears at this ſad <hi>Funeral</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Of our <hi>Dear Shepherd,</hi> in whoſe fatal <hi>grave</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Both he and we one joint <hi>interment</hi> have.</l>
                  <l>From hence there's no <hi>return</hi> for him to us,</l>
                  <l>But we muſt by degrees all follow thus.</l>
                  <l>He's gone before to <hi>uſher</hi> us, now dead</l>
                  <l>What all his life he wrought is perfected,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Living he ſhew'd the way to heaven, whither</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Now dead he's gone to clear our paſſage thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>Pariſhioners of</hi> Bermonſey.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>BEſides the overſights of the Printer in falſe ſpelling, ill pointing, and miſquoting ſome Scripture proofs, thou art intreated to correct theſe Errata's following. <hi>p. 4. l.</hi> 8. for me, <hi>r.</hi> was. <hi>p. 6. l.</hi> 25. for hater, <hi>r.</hi> hatred. and <hi>l. 26. r.</hi> poyſonous ſting. <hi>p. 8. l. 9. r.</hi> in the. <hi>p. 9. l. 4. r.</hi> friends, and <hi>l.</hi> 13. for be, <hi>r.</hi> by, and <hi>l. 20. r.</hi> reviewing. <hi>p. 10. l.</hi> 3. for Firſt, <hi>r. viz.</hi> and <hi>l. 17. r.</hi> relations, and <hi>l. 23. r.</hi> diſcovereth, and <hi>l. 24. r.</hi> leſt, <hi>p. 11. l.</hi> 7. for diligent <hi>r.</hi> affectionate, and <hi>l. 9. r.</hi> diſſatisfactions. <hi>p. 13. l. 4. r.</hi> of my. <hi>p. 16. l.</hi> 27. for beautiful. <hi>r.</hi> bountiful. <hi>p. 13. l.</hi> 33. for him, <hi>r.</hi> himſelf. &amp; <hi>l. 34. r.</hi> which did coſt. <hi>p. 20. l. 9. r.</hi> being alſo the fountaine. <hi>p. 21. l.</hi> 23. for theſe, <hi>r.</hi> the, <hi>p. 24. l. 12, r.</hi> which I have, <hi>p. 36. l.</hi> 22. for gods <hi>r.</hi> God. <hi>p. 46. l. 26. r.</hi> this, <hi>p. 47. l. 11. r.</hi> in his, <hi>p. 53. l. 1. r.</hi> Sermons, <hi>p. 58. l. 22. r.</hi> contemned.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:133592:46"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
